In this video,
I'm going to show you how to constructing user truth table.
You recall from a previous topic that truth tables are used
to determine whether an overall argument is true or false.
So when you're making a declarative statement and
statement of truth, for example something simple,
the sky is blue, that statement is either true or false.
And you can assign it a truth value of t or f and
that's pretty clear, we understand what that means.
You wanna do the same thing for entire arguments.
And so, what we're gonna do is look at a truth table and
how a truth table can help you determine the overall truth
value of an argument.
I did also describe this in written form in a previous
topic, so if you wanna see the written version of this,
you can go back and take a look at that topic.
There are also some concepts in here,
we're gonna look at compound statements, and how you
determine the overall truth value of a compound statement.
I'm assuming that you know what that means.
We've looked at this in previous lesson, so
if you need to go back and review that.
Before you watch the video,
I'd take some time to look at those concepts first and
then the video will make a lot more sense.
But as we look at this truth table, what we're gonna do is,
this is our argument here on the right.
And we're gonna look at how you can get to a single truth value
for that over all argument by breaking the pieces down into
individual components.
And as you can see in the argument,
we're using a number of variables.
Our variables are listed in the table on the left-hand side.
And the left-hand side is sort of like a ledger.
Just tells us what variables we're using and
what truth values those variables we're gonna have.
Then we're gonna use those values in the argument itself.
So that's really what a truth table looks like.
We're gonna have one more row in this truth table, and
you'll see how those rows can help us determine what
the overall truth value of the argument is.
So let's get started.
The first thing we wanna do is assign our variables values,
our truth values.
We wanna sign each variable a specific truth value.
Now in this example, all of this is completely arbitrary.
These values, these variables aren't referencing or
pointing to any specific propositions.
I just picked the letters p, q, r, s, and t.
And I'm gonna randomly assign them truth values.
When you're analyzing an argument,
you're gonna assign your propositions variables.
And you're gonna work to determine what the truth value
or possible truth value is of those propositions.
And that's how you'll proceed to analyze your argument.
But this this argument is completely arbitrary and
just used for the purposes of this example.
So let's take a look at what this will look like.
So here I have assigned truth values to each of our variables.
Again, this is some arbitrary, I just assigned true
to the variable p, false to the variable q and so forth.
And these truth values are gonna get us started with this whole
process of using a truth table to determine the truth
value of the argument.
We have to have a way to kinda prime the pump and
that's what we're doing by assigning these values, okay?
Now the next step that I'm gonna do is carry those values
into the argument itself.
Since we know what each variable is assigned,
the truth value of each variable,
we can then use those values to look at our argument itself.
So let's do that next, let's carry these values over
into the argument and that will allow us to get started.
So there you have it, so now I've just taken the values for
each of the variables and
put them under the variable in the argument itself.
So here I've taken obviously the T from p and
put that under the p in the argument.
I've taken the false from q and
put the false under the q in the argument itself.
Now what we've done here is since we know what the variable
values are,
that allows us to now work on the compound statements.
And again if you don't know what that means, you'll need to go
back into a previous lesson and take a look at that lesson so
you understand what we're talking about there.
But now that we know the values for the variables,
we can start to break apart the values for
the individual compounds statements.
When you're working on an argument, or
when you're working on a truth table, liking algebra,
or other mathematics, you're gonna look at the way
that the parenthesis, and brackets are assigned.
And you're gonna work from the inside out.
You wanna work on what's called the operator
of the smallest scope.
Another way to think about the operator of the smallest scope
is that, it's the operator that has the least
impact on the other variables in the argument.
So as we look at this argument, obviously there's a disjunction,
we can see here.
There's two conjunctions, and there's a conditional.
Right, so we have four compound statements that we're gonna have
to work on.
And we can see that the parentheses and the brackets
help us determine which is the operator of the small scope.
And hopefully, your eyes went to this guy right here,
this innermost disjunction.
So that's the one that we'll start to work on
as we work through this argument, okay?
So we're gonna work on the operator of the small scope and
then work outward to help us figure out what the overall
argument is.
All right, so let me get rid of some of the text here.
So now let's work on that first argument, or sorry,
that first compound statement.
So we have a false for r and
a T for s, and those of the are variables which
the truth now is being assign to the variables.
And now we need to figure out with the overall truth value is
for that disjunction.
Now you remember that the rule for disjunction says, that if
at least one disjunct is true, the entire disjunction is true.
If at least one disjunct is true,
the entire disjunction is true.
If both are false, the entire thing is false.
So if we look at our disjunction,
we have r is false but s is T.
So that gives us, that follows the rule one disjunct is true,
so we can assign the entire disjunction as true.
And that looks like this So
you can see, because we followed our rule,
we're gonna assign the disjunct, as a whole, the value of T,
or true based on the values in the disjunction, all right?
So that now we have our first compound statement solved for.
We know what the truth value of that is.
But we need to still continue to work on the other compound
statements to get to our overall argument value, truth value,
all right?
So how do we do that?
Well, the next one, we're gonna work outwards,
as I said earlier.
The next compound statement is gonna be this ampersand,
this convention.
And, we're gonna end up with two conjuncts in this convention.
The first one should be easy for you to see,
it's gonna be T here, and it has a value of true, but
what is the second conjunct?
Well since we solved the disjunction as a whole,
we no longer have to worry about these two variables.
We can now only focus on the value of the disjunction
as a whole.
So this disjunction value is our second conjunct
in the conjunction, all right?
And again, that follows the rules and
the setup that we talked about earlier.
So now that we have those established,
we know what the truth values are for both the conjuncts,
we can solve for the conjunction.
And our rule for conjunction says that if both conjuncts
are true, the conjunction, as a whole, is true.
If one or more conjuncts is false, then the conjunction,
as a whole, is false.
So as we look at our conjunction, we have a T for
the first conjunct and a T for the second conjunct, so
that means both conjuncts are true.
So that makes our whole conjunction true.
And so that's gonna look like this.
And now we have our value for our second conjunction.
So as we continue to work outwards, we're solving for
each of the compound statements based on the values of
the previous compound statements we solved for.
And that's why it was so
important to have truth values for our variables,
because that allows us to work on these compound statements.
Now again, we still don't have the overall argument yet,
we're still working on our statements here.
So we've gotta work on the next conjunction which is the next
one out in terms of our layers, so if we look at this,
we have two conjuncts again.
So the q is the first conjunct.
Again, since we solve now for the second of the first
conjunction, we're gonna use the overall truth value for
that as the second conjunct, okay.
So these two now become the conjuncts for this conjunction.
Right, so again, let's look at our rule.
Our rule says, if both conjuncts are true,
the conjunction as a whole is true, if one or
more is false the conjunction as a whole is false.
So since the q has a value of false, or F, then it
follows the rule that the whole conjunction has been false.
So we're gonna assign an F to the conjunction as a whole.
And that looks like this.
So now we've solved for the truth value of the second
conjunction, and that's here, and that has a value of false.
So we're not quite there yet.
We still don't have the truth value for the overall argument,
we still have to look at the conditional.
So we're gonna solve for that next.
As we look at our conditional, we have our antecedent
which is the part that comes before the if.
Remember this says F, p, then the rest of the statement.
So the part that come before the F is antecedent,
that's the p and it has a T or true.
And then the consequent of our conditional is gonna be this
whole phrase here we just solved for.
The conjunction, the value of the conjunction is gonna be
the consequent of this conditional and that's false.
So T for the antecedent, and false or F for the consequent.
Now a rule says for conditional, if the antecedent is true and
the consequent is false,
then the conditional as a whole is false.
And remember the rules says that, that's only conditions
under which the entire conditional would be false.
So that follows this pattern, so
we have overall false conditional.
And so we assign the conditional as a whole as false.
Now what we've done is, we've solved now for
the entire argument.
We have our final value, and this final value,
we assign to the operator which is a conditional operator.
And because it's the last in line,
it's the furthest out, it has the largest scope.
We call it the operator of the largest scope.
This is the operator of the largest scope because it impacts
the entire argument.
This is the final compound statement,
we would need to solve for once we solve for all the others.
So if we're looking for the truth value of the overall
argument, this is it, it's false.
The truth value of this entire argument here turns out to be
false based on how we structure the argument,
and how we worked on our truth table.
So if someone would ask you,
what is the truth value of this entire argument?
You would point to the operator of the largest scope,
the conditional, and
you would say the entire argument is false.
Okay, and that's how you use a truth value, sorry,
this is how you use a truth table to determine the truth
value of an overall argument,
by assigning the individual variables' values.
You can then plug those truth values into the argument as
a whole, and then work on your compound statements until you
get the operative scope.
And the truth value of the operator of the largest scope is
the truth value of the entire argument.