>> Hi and welcome to Logic and Computational Thinking.
If you haven't gone through the course yet,
we're really excited for you to dump into
the material and before you get started in that material,
I wanted to spend some time here with Dr. Paul Herrick.
Thank you for joining us today Paul.
>> Thank you, Paul.
>> Dr. Herrick's book is
the book called Think with Socrates.
A lot of the content that you're going to experience in
the course actually comes from Paul's book.
So, I thought it would be a lot of fun to
spend a few minutes just chatting with Paul.
He's had a long career teaching logic.
He's written a couple of textbooks and so,
I thought it'd be good to get some background.
Logic can be a little stodgy for
some people and seem very academic.
So, I thought I would give a little bit of
a human face to talk about what goes into logic.
So, again, were are going
to talk a little bit about this book in a minute.
I want to talk a little bit about your career.
So you graduated from the University of Washington.
I don't want to maybe date you here,
but how long ago?
>> Quite a few years ago.
>> Quite a few? Good.
>> Yeah.
>> So you have your Ph.D. in philosophy,
and you've taught philosophy and logic
now from many years?
>> 35 years.
>> Wow. You're in your thirty-fifth year. That's amazing.
So Paul and I have been friends
for a decade and a half, just about.
>> Well, I met you 18 years ago.
>> Okay, Yes. Just about.
>> At the philosopher's talk.
>> That's right.
>> Yeah.
>> I remember exactly where we were.
And so, we've been talking logic
and philosophy for those 18 years.
You have two texts published, logic texts.
One with Harcourt Brace
was called The Many Worlds Of Logic,
which was a great book, I use
that in many of the courses that I taught.
And now, you have a new logic texted out with
Oxford University Press which is no small feet.
Oxford University Press is
probably the premier publisher of philosophy.
So it's quite an accomplishment
to get that book published.
So, let's talk about both those logic texts.
As I look through
textbooks like the ones that you've written,
I just can see an enormous amount of work there.
Why did you write your first logic book
or your logic text with Harcourt Brace?
>> Well, I taught logic for
10 or 12 years with various textbooks
and they were wonderful books but every book I use,
there were features of
logic I wanted to include that the book didn't include
and the textbooks that I
used didn't explain things as
thoroughly as I wanted to explain them.
And a lot of students these days are so
busy that they'll attend class just a few times a week.
And I wanted a textbook that
explained everything more thoroughly so
that a student could learn it at home and not
have to come to class every day.
And I wanted the textbook to include certain topics
that weren't in the books I was using.
So, I began writing my own.
And I spent five years
trying to incorporate modal logic
into the introductory logic textbook.
I thought this was an important branch of
logic that isn't covered very often.
>> Why don't we take a quick tangent.
We don't cover modal logic in this course.
Can you just briefly explain what modal logic is?
>> So, modal logic is the logic
of possibility and necessity.
And it turns out that a lot of
the great philosophical arguments
employ modal logic in their reasoning.
So it's a fascinating branch of logic.
It actually goes back to the beginning of the discipline.
Aristotle, the founder of logic
is also the founder of modal logic.
But in this branch of logic,
philosophers study necessity and
possibility with respect to propositions.
So propositions can be
necessarily true or necessarily false,
possibly true, possibly false,
with respect to properties.
So an entity can possess
a property necessarily or contingently.
And with respect to existence,
which is the most controversial part of modal logic.
But modal logicians believe that
some things can exist necessarily
and other things can exist on a contingent basis.
And so, that's part of modal logic.
So, I wanted to incorporate modal logic into
the introductory course and I wanted to explain
things as more thoroughly
than usual and that's what led me to write
my first book and I
developed a passion for putting everything into a system.
It was exciting to try to get all the right elements in,
in all the right places in a systematic form
that would flow and the students would follow.
And so, that was exciting for me.
>> Is that where the title "Many Worlds" came from?
As you had all these different systems?
>> Actually, Many Worlds of Logic
was an illusion to modal logic.
>> I see. Okay.
>> And I don't know if I should go into why it was,
But modal logicians refer to
things they call possible worlds.
And the semantics of
modal logic is all defined in terms of
theoretical entities called possible worlds.
Ways the universe could have been or could be,
and so, it was an allusion to that.
Very interesting aspect of modal logic.
>> So that was a big distinguishing factor
of your book relative to other that you wrote.
>> Well, that's I think why it
was published because it integrated
modal logic into the standard logic course.
And as far as I know, only one other book did that.
>> Yeah.
>> And so, it's exciting because I could bring in
arguments about free will and about time and fatalism.
Whether their future's already been fated
to happen into the logic course
and develop those arguments
using the symbols of modal logic.
And that was kind of fun.
>> Sure.
>> Yes.
>> So, how do you do research for a book like this?
One of the questions I actually have never asked you this
personally so I can ask you now on camera.
When you're preparing to write a book
like on logic or even mathematics or something like that,
it's been done for so many decades and centuries,
how do you approach it uniquely?
Like when you're writing your examples or you're
writing the definition of
a Modus Ponens or a Modus Tones,
a lot of the definitions that we use in
this course are definitions I pulled from your book
and other logic textbooks and I couldn't
really reword them that much
because it's a definition right?
Modus Ponens is what a Modal Tonens is.
So, how do you approach
the topic so that you're giving it
your own voice and writing it in your way and
not just copying what someone else has done?
>> Yeah, that's a good question.
I've always walked into the classroom without notes.
I've never taken notes into the classroom.
>> I prepare ahead of time but
when I walk into the classroom,
I am explaining things to students as
clearly as I can at the moment, spontaneously.
And then, what works
in the classroom is what goes into my textbook.
So, for many years,
I taught Logic three times a day,
and I got a lot of feedback from students
and I used that to
try to explain things as clearly as I could.
And as I'm writing the book,
I'm thinking back on my classroom experiences,
what explanations work best,
and what parts of Logic connect with students,
and what parts aren't really necessary.
Because you really have to be
selective when you write a textbook.
No textbook can cover everything.
>> Right.
>> Yes
>> So, talk about your book with Oxford University Press.
That's a very different book from
many worlds in some ways.
I mean, there's obviously some overlap.
Where were going after there?
>> Well, the third Logic book I
wrote was a complete revision of the previous two.
And I revised it from the ground up and
Oxford had it reviewed by a number of
teachers and liked it and published it.
I actually went further on explaining everything.
It ended up 800 pages,
but I tried to explain things so
thoroughly that a student can still be at home studying,
and would find complete explanations
of everything all the way through.
And so, it's even more
explained I think than the first two books.
The second Logic book I wrote
expanded the coverage into
a lot of Inductive Logic that wasn't in the first book.
The first book was almost all Deductive Logic.
The second book brought a lot of Inductive Logic in.
And then the third logic book,
the one you're mentioning now
called "Introduction to Logic",
has everything from the previous
two but I just went through from
the ground up and re-explained everything.
It was really fun to try
to clarify even further everything I tried to say.
And I added some sections,
some more sections that I hadn't covered.
>> That's great. And I like"
Introduction to Logic" because of that,
the latest book for with Oxford University Press.
And in fact, throughout the course,
if the topics that you're studying
and that you're reading through interest you,
I highly recommend you take a look at
getting Dr. Herrick's "Logic" textbook.
This book is more of
an introduction to critical thinking,
the one that we've been using in this course.
But Dr. Herrick's textbooks are definitely going into
more depth in the formal logic spaces.
And I think there's an e-book correct?
For the Oxford University Press?
There's a digital version if you want?
>> Yes, both books have a e-text version.
>> And they're relatively inexpensive as textbooks go.
A lot of textbooks are in the couple hundred
dollar range and these are what?
50-60? Or something like that?
>> Yes. Around 60.
>> That's a good price.
>> Oxford is a non-profit publisher.
>> Right.
>> And they produce quality books
that are quite a bit
less than the big commercial publishers.
>> And that's why I don't feel bad recommending
these books too.
They're great, great texts,
one of the things about this latest book,
is that you can study from it on your own.
So, if you get the good foundation in
this course, "Logic computational Thinking",
then you can expand your studies by taking
Dr. Herrick's book and working through it on your own.
I think you can get a lot of value there.
So, let's talk a little bit about "Think with Socrates".
"Think with Socrates" is a really fun book.
I really enjoyed reading through it,
it covers a lot of topics very nicely,
which is why I wanted to use the book in this course.
We license a lot of the content from
Oxford University Press and
a lot of the content that's in the book,
you'll find directly in the course.
There's other things that are not in the course itself.
So if you want to go and do more study,
the book is a nice option there.
But what gave you the idea to
come up with the book "Think with Socrates"?
And what was your goals of producing them?
>> Well, alongside Symbolic Logic
I've always taught critical thinking.
And critical thinking is a different course.
Although it's hard sometimes to
distinguish Logic and Critical Thinking,
but the Critical Thinking course is
logic applied to everyday life,
and that's one way to think of it.
So, Critical Thinking literally means
criterial thinking or thinking by criteria.
So, criteria are standards, standards of evaluation,
and critical thinking literally is thinking by standards,
standards of good thinking.
And Critical Thinking courses are
generally pitched towards improving
the reasoning abilities we use in
everyday life to make
them more realistic and more effective.
So, I always taught Critical Thinking
and Socrates always came up,
because he's generally considered the
founder of critical thinking.
He was the very first philosopher to teach
Critical Thinking as a means of improving your life,
and to give his life for teaching it.
Because the Athenian democracy executed him
primarily because of the critical thinking
he was teaching the citizens.
And so, he's considered the founder.
But most critical thinking books, they honor Socrates,
they mention him, but
they don't build the course around him.
And students, when they meet Socrates,
they fall in love with him.
He's a remarkable human being, a remarkable character,
he's so inspiring and I fell in love with Socrates
and the idea came to
me to build a critical thinking course
around his persona.
That was sort of what led me to write the book.
The book introduces students to Socrates, his person,
his life, his method of thought,
and then the whole rest of the book
builds on that and refers back to him.
And so the course is built around a person,
but a remarkable person.
A person who sometime in the middle of his life
realized that a lot of people think they know what
they're talking about when they haven't a clue.
They think they're an expert in
things then they really
have no idea what they're talking about.
And he could have
just grab people by the collar and shook them,
he could have been angry,
but he had so much respect for
the individual and so much love
of his fellow human beings,
that he couldn't be
harsh with people and yell at them and shake them.
His method turned out to be different.
He asked people questions,
but they were questions designed to cause people to look
in the mirror and examine their own assumptions,
and find out for themselves where they were going wrong.
>> Right. And it's become known as the Socratic method.
>> That is the Socratic method.
I would put it this way,
looking in the mirror,
and evaluating your assumptions and
your actions on the basis of realistic criteria.
Criteria related to truth and justice.
And he gave his life for that vision,
the vision of a life in which a person
constantly examines his assumptions
is willing to admit he's wrong,
is willing to correct his actions and his views.
And so that became known as Critical Thinking.
And so, I wanted to organize
the book around that human vision, really.
>> Yes. And it really turned out to be a great result.
When we think about "Logic and Computational Thinking",
and applying logical principles
to writing computer programs,
there's a direct relationship between
the formal logic, the deductive reasoning,
inductive reasoning,
the categorical reasoning that
we talk about in the course.
But there's a whole aspect of working with other people,
and working in a business or a corporation,
or selling your work, that
takes those logical concepts and applies them to life.
And I think that we try to bring out
some of those topics as well in the course.
And you certainly do a great job
of relating kind of logic to real life.
Right? Logic can be fairly
academic and a little bit stodgy sometimes.
But you do a really good job of showing.
There's a huge practical side to
this discipline and taking
those concepts and applying them to a real problems.
>> Thank you. Yes. Well, once you're
aware of the nature of critical thinking,
you're looking at the criteria.
And if you're in an organization
and decisions are being made and you're
part of the decision-making process,
you can look at the criteria
that are being used and you can ask,
"Are these criteria appropriate for the goal?
For our goal?
Are these criteria grounded in reality?
Are these criteria realistic?"
You can ask questions like that.
That's what a critical thinker does.
And so, once you're aware of
the way critical thinking works,
it can be a tool that you use in an organization,
in a group, as well as just in your own personal life.
>> That's right.
>> So, yes. That's great.
>> Well, thanks. Thanks, Paul.
It was nice to hear a little bit about the textbooks,
and then of course about "Think with Socrates"
which has been a fantastic asset to our course.
What we'll do in the next video,
is talk a little bit about how
logic can be applied to real-world problems.
We'll talk a little bit about some of
the challenges that students face
when they just first start studying logic,
and we'll explore those topics
a little bit in the next video. We'll see you there.
>> Thank you.