>> Hey and welcome back. I'm here with Dr. Paul Herrick.
Dr. Herrick is the author of the book
"Think with Socrates" published
by Oxford University Press.
And this text is
the book that we've been using in our course.
A lot of the material and
the exercises and the exam questions that you are
working your way through are taken from
this book along with a bunch of
other supplementary material that we put together.
So Dr. Herrick authored that book,
and it's been a pleasure to have him in the studio,
and chatting with him a little bit in earlier modules.
We've recorded a couple of
videos that you probably want to check out.
We had a good conversation about Logic,
and the textbooks, and those kinds of things.
So before you get into
the sections and deductive and inductive reasoning,
I thought it would be helpful to talk with Dr.
Herrick on some of these topics.
You're going to run into some things that may be a little
confusing and a little counter-intuitive.
So, I thought it would be good to have
a conversation to talk about what you're going to see
in these upcoming modules
and talk about ways that you can get
past some of the challenges that
you may encounter as
you are working through the material.
Dr. Herrick has taught Logic in
the classroom and online for 35 years.
I've only been teaching for about half that, so,
I thought it'd be good to get a veteran, educator,
person that study this material
wrote three different Logic textbooks
and "Think with Socrates"
to talk you through some of these challenges.
So, we're going to look through
some slides that you had prepared ahead of time.
Can you talk a little bit about what's
on these slides and what
your goals were in putting these slides
together to help these students?
>> Sure. So, I have
some slides that are designed to give you
a quick little lesson on
how Logic can help you reason better.
So, these are just a few examples of arguments that
seem valid or seem reasonable at first glance,
but after you've studied Logic and
thought about the principles of Logic,
you can spot the problems.
So, I have a few examples to illustrate.
>> Great. So, when we're talking prior to doing
this recording about validity and deduction,
so you actually wrote a little example here that we're
going to take a quick look at
so you can help the student understand.
What are we going to be talking through?
What are we looking here on the screen?
>> Okay. So, logicians,
what you'll learn in Paul's course
is that logicians starting with Aristotle,
the founder of Logic,
divide all arguments into two categories.
Every argument is either deductive or inductive.
In deductive arguments,
tried to show that their conclusion must be true.
In other words, they aim to establish
their conclusion with complete certainty.
They attempt to conclusively prove their conclusion true.
Inductive arguments, on the other hand,
attempt to show their conclusion is
probably true but not certain.
So they aim for a little bit lower standard,
they aim to show the conclusion is likely probable,
reasonable, but not completely certain.
So, induction aims at probability but not certainty,
deduction aims at complete certainty.
Now, what we have here is an argument because the word
"Therefore" is a conclusion indicator word
indicating a conclusion is about to be given.
So this word here tells us we have an argument.
And then, this word here,
it's called a "Deductive indicator word".
This word tells us that
the argument is deductive in nature.
So the claim here is that,
if the premises are true,
the conclusion must be true.
Because necessarily means must
be so, cannot be otherwise.
>> And that definition you gave us
is the definition of validity.
And again, we're going to talk about this in
more detail in the course itself,
but that's what "Validity" means.
Assuming the premises are true,
the conclusion must follow with an assessment.
>> Yes. I'll add one thing to that.
What makes an argument deductive
is that it aims to show that its conclusion must be true.
If a deductive argument succeeds in its aim,
we call it a "Valid Deductive Argument" So this is
deductive because the aim is to
show that the conclusion must be true.
It is a "Valid Deductive Argument".
So I'll write, it is valid
because it does indeed succeed in its aim.
If the premises are true,
the conclusion must indeed be true just as claimed.
Now, you can think this through in your head.
If all cats are mammals, if that's true,
and if all mammals are animals, if that's true,
then it necessarily follows that all cats are animals.
And you can think it through with a little diagram.
We could let that circle
represent all the cats in the universe.
We can let this circle
represent all the mammals in the universe.
And this circle inside this circle
simply says that all the cats
belong to the mammal category.
So then, if we draw the animal category this way,
this says all the mammals belong to the animal category.
And so this lets us visually see
the relationship between the premises and the conclusion.
And that relationship is that,
if the premises are true,
the conclusion has to be true.
That is if all cats are
mammals and all mammals are animals,
then it has to follow.
It must be so that all cats are animals.
So this is this is a "Valid Deductive Argument".
>> Right. And we're going to look more closely at
exactly this in the categorical section of this course.
And we use a different type of diagram called a
"Venn Diagram" to illustrate the same thing.
So you'll get to practice some
of these and learn how to do it yourself.
>> Now, logicians will add one thing to this.
A student will often say,
what makes an argument valid? Why is it valid?
What makes it valid? And logicians will answer that,
what makes this argument valid is not its subject matter,
what it's about, cats and mammals and animals.
What makes it valid is what logicians
called the logical form of the argument.
This argument has a abstract structure
called a "Logical Form".
It's a structure that many different arguments about
many different things could fit or follow.
And so, it's that abstract form
or structure that makes this valid,
not what it's about.
So what we do is we distinguish
the form from the content.
So the form of this argument is,
all A's are B's,
where A and B are categories of things.
All B are C, and therefore,
all A are C. So,
this is called the logical form of the argument,
where the A and the B and the C are variables standing
for the words that stand for categories of things,
cat's, mammals and animals.
So this is purely abstract.
It's not about anything in particular, whereas,
this argument is about animals.
>> Correct.
>> So that we talk about the content of
the argument versus logical form of the argument,
and it's the form that makes this valid.
And then what Logic teaches you to do,
is it teaches you how to see the form above the content.
How to abstract the Form from
the Content and see whether it's a valid form or not.
That's a valid form.
>> And don't worry if you're not getting this at
this point in the course,
we're going to walk through all of this in
very specific details so you'll
learn how to recognize these.
What we're talking about here is
what logic will do for you.
And as you move through these lessons,
if you get stuck and you're
trying to figure out how this all works,
I think what Paul has explained is
the relationship between the Content and the Form.
And you'll see this as we
build the concepts out
through the next couple of modules.
So, in the next video,
what we're going to do is talk you
through fallacies of reasoning,
where the argument may appear valid but students
actually go wrong on it because
it has an appearance that's different from the reality.
So Paul is going to talk us through
a couple of these forms and
explain why they might appear to be valid but in reality,
they're not valid at all.
So we'll do that in the next video. Thanks.