Hi, and welcome to this module on categorical logic.
We've been looking at traditional syllogistic
logic and we're gonna transition now into what is called
categorical logic.
Which was largely developed by Aristotle back in the 400
BC era.
And categorical logic has a very specific
approach that Aristotle took.
And to introduce this topic, I'm gonna talk a little bit
about Aristotle's metaphysics, or ontology.
Those terms simply mean the way that Aristotle looked at
the world.
And his ontology really set up philosophy for the West.
Even to this day, we still use a lot of Aristotle's approach and
categories.
As I say in the module itself, in the written part of
the module, Aristotle really invented or discovered or
however you want to term it the methodology that we use for
modern science today and modern scientific discovery.
And so what he did as he developed his ontology is he
defined terms that we use.
He defined the vocabulary that we're gonna use and
he also helped us to categorize things.
And that's sort of where we get this idea of categorical logic,
is that Aristotle really helped us to come up with the buckets
that we're gonna use in which we wanna place different things.
So I thought it would be helpful to go through Aristotle's
basic ontology as we get into this module, and
this gonna provide largely background.
As I talk through this and then you go through the lessons in
this module, you'll see how the two are connected.
If you understand this ontology it's gonna help you understand
why Aristotle developed a logic and a way of talking about
the categories that he developed in a very specific way.
You'll see the connection between these two.
And by the way, ontology comes from the Greek,
literally means being.
So the study of being, onto, being, logic,
or logos is the Greek term, a study of, a discourse on.
So it's really the study of being and
that's really what we're looking at.
All right, let's get into some of what Aristotle and
the early Greeks.
We're gonna actually look at the early Greeks a little bit as
well, including Plato and Socrates, and
what they thought about ontology.
What they thought about how the world was structured.
All right, the first thing I wanna talk about is
this topic called properties.
This word cloud represents a bunch of nouns and
adjectives that we see and use everyday.
And, when we're talking about ontology, the building blocks of
that discussion really starts with properties.
Properties are the things that all of ontology, particularly
Aristotle and Plato's ontology, are built up from.
And so we wanna just
spend a couple of minutes looking at what properties are.
Right., so properties again are the basic
building blocks of things in the world.
They're the fundamental concept that we're gonna
use to talk about all these other topics.
All right, so
the best way to define a property is it's an attribute.
A characteristic of something or a component of what makes
that thing what it is and not something else, right?
So we can put it very simply, a property is the respect in which
things are the same or differ.
A property is the respect in which things are the same or
differ.
As we get into categorical logic, you're gonna see how
important properties are when you're starting to define terms.
As you move through the module we'll talk about how to use
the logic of the categorical syllogism and
the categorical statement to earmark properties and
to put them into classes or categories of things, okay.
So when you think about a property, think about redness or
think about something that makes a thing what it is.
I'm wearing a black shirt, right.
This is infused with properties.
You can talk about the property of the fabric it's made up,
the color, the shape, the size.
All of those things would be the properties of the shirt, okay.
So that's a very simple definition of what
a property is.
Let's get in to a little bit more specificity as we talk
through this.
Philosophers and logicians distinguish between simple
properties and complex properties.
A simple property is a property that cannot be reduced
to other properties.
Sounds simple enough, right.
Some philosophers believe that properties like evenness, size,
and shape are irreducible, you can't break them down into other
simpler, more primary properties.
There are philosophers, obviously,
that disagree with that, and so you have that conversation.
But when you think about a simple property,
if you can't break it down into other constituent parts then
you're kind of dealing with the basic property that you
wanna talk about, all right?
So think about something like color.
Is redness a simple property or a complex property?
When you think about redness you can talk about its hue,
you can talk about what type of red it is, how bright it is,
things like that.
So it might be actually not a simple property.
It might be something that we're gonna talk about next,
which is called a complex property.
Now, given this definition of a simple property,
then, a complex property is just a property that
has other properties that are part of it, okay?
One that you can talk about in terms of other things.
If you have other adjectives or nouns that apply to the property
you're talking about, then it's not a simple property.
All right I used the example here of a mammal.
A mammal can be reduced to other properties.
So that means it itself is not simple.
It's in the class of things that are alive,
it's in the class of things that give birth to live offspring,
right, those are all the other properties that we would put
into this idea of a mammal.
All right, so, properties,
simple and complex, these are fairly straightforward ideas.
And again, as you get into the module on categorical logic,
you're gonna see how these concepts play into how Aristotle
thought about constructing his logical system.
And then I would like you to think about how you relate that
to the syllogistic logic,
the propositional logic we looked at earlier in the course.
And there are similarities, but you can see that Aristotle's
approach takes a very distinctive perspective and
this idea of properties plays into that
heavily as you'll go through this.
I'm gonna give you one more lesson on properties and
how properties are used.
We tend to use properties in a very important concept in
philosophy and logic called the Theory of Identity, or
the Philosophy of Identity.
Identity is important because it helps you distinguish
between things.
It helps you figure out whether two things that you're
considering are the same thing or if they're individualistic.
And I'll give you some examples of where this is really
important in just a moment.
But let's talk through this idea of identity and
how properties are used.
All right, so
how do we tell if two things are the same or if they differ?
There was a debate in early astronomy
over the morning star and the evening star.
Hesperus and Phosphorus were their names.
And for a long time astronomers believed that they were actually
two different stars.
The morning star you'd see just after sunrise or just
before sunrise, the evening star you'd see just after sunset.
And astronomers didn't know that they were
actually the same star.
So they ended up being the same star.
They ended up being a planet, I think it's the planet Venus.
I have to check on that, but
it was essentially the same celestial body and
they had two different names, two different identities, but
at the end of the day it ended up being the same planet.
So when they talked about it,
they had to change their thinking, they had to change
the way that they referred to that celestial body.
So how do you tell?
How do you know if a thing is the same,
two things are the same or if they're different?
So identity does serve this role in our philosophy, right.
If we can come up with a criterion If we can come up with
a rule that helps us distinguish between two things,
then it's gonna allow us to have that conversation in a much more
profitable way.
We can now,
as we're debating over whether two things are the same or
different, we have a rule that we can put into play here.
Here's some areas of philosophy where this ends up being
very important.
Are the mind and the brain the same thing?
Philosophers debate this all the time, and
this is a very interesting, even current, debate.
When we're talking about the brain,
are we talking about the mind, and vice-versa?
Is color the same thing as a bandwidth of light hitting your
retina?
There's a science behind visualizing color.
But is the color that you see, the redness that you see,
the same thing as that science of light waves and
retinas and how those two things interact?
Then we can talk about things even like this.
This is a great philosophical topic.
How do we talk about equality when it comes to humans?
Is the humanist that the person sitting next to you or
your family member or a loved one, is their
humanness the same as your humanness or is it different?
Everybody's certainly different.
We all have a variety of different properties.
We've that term that we looked at earlier.
We're all different heights and
weights and different skin color and hair color.
So what makes us equal?
What part of our humanness is equal, if any part?
And the philosophy of identity helps us talk through that.
So there was a philosopher named Gottfried Wilhelm Leibniz
that gave us a rule, gave us a pattern, for
talking about identity and we're gonna look at his rule now.
This rule is widely accepted across both science and
philosophy and so it's a good thing to learn and know.
So let's talk about Leibniz identity.
So Leibniz said, take any two things that you're talking
about, the mind and the brain or Hesperus and Phosphorus.
Each of these things has a set of properties that
are true of them.
Complex and simple properties that are true of them.
So we're gonna take both things, the mind and the brain.
And he said take all of the properties of those two things.
So let's take the mind in the brain.
Well, actually that's probably a too complicated of entity.
So we wanna talk about it.
Let's talk about Hesperus and Phosphorus.
These are the morning star and the evening star.
So if we take those two objects, and we list their properties,
their brightness, their location in the sky,
the movement of the planet through the sky over time.
We look at all of those properties that are true of each
body, each of the celestial bodies, Hesperus and
Phosphorus and
we ask, is there any property that's different between them?
That's the rule.
Is there any single property?
It doesn't matter how small it is.
Is there any single property that's different between the two
bodies and we look at that list?
If there is a property that's different
then the two objects are different.
It's the property that distinguishes between the two
objects.
It's a property difference.
If there's a single property, it doesn't matter how small it is,
that it's different between Hesperus and
Phosphorus, we're talking about two different planetary bodies.
If there is no difference between the two celestial bodies
then we're talking about the same object,
we're talking about the same thing.
And what we would say is those two objects are identical to
each other.
They're not two objects,
they're only two in name rather than in reality or ontology.
They're all wrongly referring to them as two things,
when in reality there's one thing.
And that's the distinction.
Are we making what's called a semantic difference, or
is the difference a real difference?
Are they actually different objects?
And so this is kind of a formal way of writing this out.
The way this reads is a is equal to b,
Hesperus is equal to Phosphorus.
If and only if,
that double arrow means this is a necessary condition.
We talked about this earlier in the course.
It's necessarily true that for any property,
that's what the P means here, for any property, if P
is true of a and P is true of b, then a and b are identical.
If there's a single property difference, then a and
b are not identical.
So start thinking about this and
all the things that you care about,
this is a good way to come up with definitions for things.
Is your humanness the same as the humanness of the person
next to you?
Is the mind and the brain the same thing?
Is the color red and the wavelength of light that is
hitting your retina, are those identical?
Are there any property difference between those objects
that we're talking about?
And that at least gives us a starting point for
talking about whether there are different things.
Again, this is not necessarily a proof,
it doesn't necessarily prove that they're identical, but
it gives us a reason to believe that they're not.
And it gives us a good starting point with which
to discuss that.
That's the philosophy of identity.
As I studied philosophy, this has been one of
the most important principles that I've learned.
It's really helped me make important distinctions.
And, again, you're gonna see this idea as you move through
the module on categorical syllogisms.
You're gonna see this idea and
the relevance of it permeate the material and how Aristotle
developed his logical system using concepts like this.
So let's continue to talk about properties.
We have just a couple of more ideas here I wanna give you.
And the next concept that we wanna look at and this directly
relates to categorical logic, is the philosophy of universals and
particulars when it comes to properties.
And we're gonna go a little bit off topic and
talk about the Greeks in general here.
The Greeks had a very specific way of viewing properties in
terms of their universality or their particularness.
And so it's important to understand this and when you get
the idea here when we see what Aristotle and Plato were trying
to do, it's gonna help you understand why Aristotle
developed his categorical logic in the way that he did.
So one question that the the early Greeks asked is,
how do properties exist in the world?
Where is humanness after all?
Where is redness?
Where are these properties that we talk about each and
every day, multiple times a day?
How do they exist?
Do they exist in the things that have them or
do they exist in a different way?
And the way that the early Greek's talked about it is
they can exist in two different ways.
They can exist as a universal, or
they can exist as a particular, and again this directly relates
to this categorical logic that we're looking at.
Let me go to the next section here.
So the early Greek philosophers talked about
the individual things,
the redness of the apple, the blackness of this shirt.
They talked about these individual parts.
And then they said,
it's clearly that there's redness in the apple.
The redness appears to be a part of the apple.
But there's a lot of red things in the world.
So the idea of red seems to be abstracted
out of the individual things that have them.
There's redness.
And there in there are red objects.
And that's how the Greeks thought about these types of
properties.
So the way that they thought about the individual things,
as they said the individual red apple is a particular, or
what they called an instance of this property of red.
That red object is a particular red thing.
And we can talk about this at the macro level,
complex properties, things that chairs, trees, and
rocks have a whole set of complex and
individual properties and those are instance.
Those are particular instances of those properties.
But the properties themselves, the abstract version of them,
exists as what are called universals.
And not everybody buys this idea of universals,
sometimes called abstract objects.
This is heavily debated in philosophy.
But even if you don't buy that universals exist somewhere,
there's this idea of redness somewhere, you can still buy
into the idea that there is an abstract, even if it's mental,
even if it's a cognitive trick that we're playing.
There is this idea of red that stands over and
above the individual things that have redness.
So we can talk about redness as a category.
And that's where this whole idea of categorical logic comes
from, right?
We have these categories, we have these universals
that we can talk about in broad classes of things, okay?
So let's take this simple apple.
This is just kind of a corny example of how this works.
We have the form, right, or the universal.
The other term for this is a form and token or
form an individual.
We have the form apple, right?
It exists as a universal.
And then we have all the instances.
We have all the individual apples that exemplify
the properties of that thing, okay?
So that's how Aristotle thought about, and
Plato thought about the relationship between forms and
tokens, or universals and particulars.
All right, let's talk a little bit more about universals cuz
it's gonna be very important to understand this concept as we
get into categorical logic.
All right, for some of the Greeks, Plato in particular,
Plato thought that universals actually existed outside of
the instances, outside of the things that had them.
So for example, if every red object in the world were to
disappear, redness, as a universal, would still exist.
That's what Plato thought, okay?
So he thought that universals were neither temporal nor
spatial.
They did have to exist in the physical world.
He also had very specific views.
And by the way Aristotle didn't share a lot of these.
He also thought that universals could be thought
of as a type or an archetype of the thing.
So if you wanna understand what the properties of a universal
are, you have to take all of the instances, and think about
what those instances share, right, in terms of identity.
And then you can come up with all the properties of
that universal, right?
So the type informs what each of the tokens,
what each of the individual, particular things, have.
Right, the universe can be thought of a property,
particularly if you have, obviously, a simple property.
But you can have complex properties also that
are universals.
And one way to talk about these things is to talk about them as
abstract objects, and we use the suffix ness.
We put ness after it, like redness, blackness.
You can even have the property of humanness, right?
Or appleness, whatever the thing's nature is.
So when you are talking about a thing's nature,
you really are talking about that universal abstraction,
all right?
So universals then are the starting point.
That's how the Greeks thought about properties,
as these abstract objects.
And then again,
the particulars are the things that possess them.
So if you have the property,
the universal property of redness and you have a red
apple, the red apple, the instance that particular
thing participates in the universal by having red, okay?
So let's talk about these particulars.
Particulars then are instances or instantiations.
Don' t let these big words bother you.
It just means the particular takes the universal and
it exemplifies it.
It has it as a part of what it is, okay?
It instantiates it.
Particulars themselves are in time and space.
They're in the real world, right?
They're things that we can touch.
You can hold an apple, you can eat an apple.
You can taste an apple, you can participate in all of its
properties in a physical way.
So they have being in time and space, the Greeks thought, okay?
The word that the Greeks used for particulars is token.
Again, type is used for universal, token is used for
particular and it's the concrete instance of that thing, right?
Now this last concept is important for the Greeks.
Again, as I mentioned earlier, the Greeks thought that
the individual particular thing participates in the universal.
Plato particularly thought this.
He thought that if the universal went away, all the instances,
all the particulars would go away with it.
If redness, if God got rid of redness,
he thought, as a universal,
then all the particular red things would cease to exist.
Aristotle had a little bit of a different take.
His view was that the particular things, all the red apples and
the red objects in the world,
are what made the universal what it is.
So the universal in a sense is created by the fact that
the particulars exist.
And that's where we kinda get this idea that the universal is
an abstraction or an idea that's created out of all
the particulars that we see in the world.
But those details aren't terribly important for
understanding how categories work in categorical logic.
The important part is that we have these distinctions between
the universal, the category, the class.
Sometimes we use class.
You have classes of mammals, right?
You have classes of birds, you have classes of human, right?
Those classes exist, and then you have the particular things
in that class, the particular instances,
the individual humans walking around,
the individual birds flying around, those kinds of things.
Right, so that's the relationship between
the universal and the particular.
All right, all of this background again is to help
inform how Aristotle thought about categorical logic.
And he uses these concepts and
builds a logical system around these concepts.
And the more you understand how these concepts work, the better
you're gonna be at understanding how categorical logic works.
And when you get to the section on how categorical statements
are designed and developed, these ideas should make a lot
more sense to you as you put those statements together.
All right, I wanna give you one more lesson on Aristotle's
ontology and then we'll be done with this topic and we
can move on to actually working with categorical statements.
Aristotle's ontology included a methodology.
And that methodology, the method that he used to examine
the world and study the world, the scientific method we know it
as today, and we're gonna talk about how Aristotle actually
developed that method in the course.
But Aristotle came out with this idea of four causes.
And what he said is, you really can't understand something
unless you understand its four causes.
Now he doesn't mean causes in a way that we mean cause and
effect, the thing that created it or the thing that started it.
What he means is when we wanna understand its four causes,
we wanna understand its four components.
Everything has four components,
and those components are what inform how we understand it.
That's what he meant by cause.
Iit's more of an informational idea
rather than a cause effect idea.
All right, and he said understand these four causes
if you wanna understand how anything is made up.
The way that he categorizes these
is really really fascinating, and
I wanna try to show you why it's fascinating in a moment.
But again, this directly informs categorical logic, and
why his logic was developed in the way that it was.
His first cause, he said, is the material cause.
So let's take our red apple again.
We've got a red apple, and
we want to understand what that red apple is.
We want to scientifically study it, all right?
One thing we have to understand first is what is it made up of?
We wanna tear it apart scientifically.
And now we can do really complex chemical analyses
of these objects, right?
So we can look at the chemical make up.
We can weigh it.
We can measure its size.
We can look at all the other apples and
talk about what's identical between them, right?
But we have to understand the stuff of the thing.
We have to understand the material Make up of the object
that we're studying.
And he said this is true of anything that we want to study.
We have to understand the material cause.
All right, simple enough.
The next one relates directly to our topic of universals in
particulars.
So Aristotle said, if you want to understand something,
you have to understand what class it belongs to.
You have to understand what he called its formal cause, or,
remember we used the term the form of the thing, right?
The ideal, the necessary properties that that thing has.
And this goes back to identity, right?
The identity and property talk.
You have to understand what property or what properties
the object has that's identical to other things in its class.
So let's take the idea of a chair,
you're probably sitting in one right now.
If not, you can look around the room and
probably see a couple of different types of chairs.
All right, now, when I use the term chair,
I'm using a categorical term, aren't I?
I'm using a class of things,
I'm saying this individual object belongs to a class
of things that also participate in that class, all right?
The individuals participate in that class.
So what Aristotle would ask is,
what are the properties that all, and only chairs,
possess that makes them a part of that class?
Let's think about that for a moment.
If we have an object and it has a round thing at the top and
three legs coming out, we tend not to call that a chair,
we call that a stool, right?
There's something missing we might say,
it's not really a chair.
So we would say that a chair has to have probably something
to sit on.
Most of us would probably define a chair as having a back, so
something to rest your back against.
And most chairs that people sit in have four legs.
Let's just start there, so we have something to sit on,
something to support the back and four legs, and
we'll say those are the necessary properties
that chairs have and all chairs have.
There's not a single exception to our definition.
Now, we can debate this, this is just for
the purpose of giving you an example.
Let's talk about some other properties that chairs
must have.
Can they be this big?
Can they be two inches tall, in other words?
Probably not gonna work as a chair, right?
Because now it doesn't perform its function,
it's not functioning as a chair.
So we would say a chair has to be at least as big to hold up
a human person, either a child or an adult.
Can the chair be made out of whipped cream or
something solid, jello?
Probably not, right?
Again, chairs have to accomplish some goal,
they have to do something, and
a chair made up of whipped cream is a gonna function as a chair.
Can be shape like a chair, can look like a chair, but
it's not going to be a chair.
Okay, hopefully you see the idea.
So chairs have necessary properties,
all chairs have to have them.
And then individual chairs have those properties
as a part of that instance, that particular thing.
But we can abstract all those universal properties of a chair
and say now this is what is in the class of chair.
And philosophers, and logicians, and
scientist spend a lot of time debating what should be in and
what should be out of these classes.
This is how we come up with classifications in
biology, right?
You figure out what a species has to have, and then you say
if something doesn't have it, it's not a part of that species.
That classification exercise is being done all the time.
And so the formal cause was really, really important for
Aristotle, if you truly wanna understand something.
And he spends a lot of time emphasizing and
play the do as well, the importance of the formal cause.
So the formal cause is the ideal the form of the thing,
it's necessary properties.
Aristotle said, we also need to understand its efficient cause,
and put simply, this is just what brings the thing about.
So think about any object that you want to study.
It's always helpful to know how it came about,
how it came to be, what brought it about.
And this could be a human maker,
if I hold up this mouse, if you look at this mouse, we would say
engineers build this mouse, they're the efficient cause.
The engineers are what brought the thing into being.
The term that logicians like to use is that by means of which
something exists.
What brought it into existence?
And then finally, ironically, we have the final cause.
And this is the last thing that Aristotle said,
you needed to understand if you want to understand everything
about the object.
The final cause is the why that that for
the sake of which something exists.
Now this might strike you as a little odd.
Why do we care about the why?
The purpose of the thing?
The term that the early Greeks used was teleology,
or the goal for why the thing was brought about,
why did the efficient cause bring the thing into existence.
Now notice the important relationship between final cause
and formal cause.
We cannot come up with the necessary properties of
the thing until we understand why the thing exist.
Remember we said that whipped cream would be a really bad
material for a chair?
And the reason for that is because the chair exist for
the purpose of holding someone's weight,
allowing someone to sit down.
So if we didn't know that, we couldn't tell
that the chair could not be made out of wood frame.
We couldn't make that statement because we would have no idea
for the purpose of the chair.
So the final cause, Aristotle and
Plato thought, is super important to understand if
you're gonna understand what the formal cause is all about,
what its necessary properties are for that thing.
So Aristotle said, if you wanna understand something fully,
you have to understand its final cause.
And again,
this is gonna be important as you study categorical logic.
Cuz as you come up with categories of things,
as you make universal all and particular statements,
all statements and some statements, you're gonna have to
understand the relationship of the particular properties to
the categories of the things that you're discussing.
So this is Aristotle's four cause model.
And again, this informed a lot of Western philosophy in modern
scientific methodology.
So a lot of the methods that we use in modern science
were built up from Aristotle's basic model.
Now, to close out this section,
I just wanna give you a quick illustration.
I've been talking about different ideas and ways to
think about this, but let's talk about Aristotle's four causes
as we apply them to a house.
So if we're gonna describe the material cause of a house,
we would say things that make it up.
The wood, bricks, windows, all the material pieces,
all the stuff that the house is made up of.
Now, the formal cause gets a little tricky.
Remember we have to keep the final cause in mind
in order to talk about the formal cause.
So we're gonna say that the house has to have some essential
components, like walls.
It probably should have a roof and
it should have a door, why does it need a roof?
Well we would say the purpose of a house is shelter.
So if you have a house with no roof, it's not
providing that function, it's not meeting that purpose.
And therefore, fails to fit the category of house,
if it doesn't have a roof.
Why do you need doors?
Well, again, the purpose of a house is to provide shelter for
humans, right?
We're talking about obviously human built homes here.
It has to provide shelter for humans.
And so if the humans don't have a way to get in and
out, it seizes to function as a house.
Now, it's just a big box with a roof on it.
So our final cause, the purpose, has to inform our formal cause,
which is the things that make it up.
And then we have our efficient cause,
we would say builders, architects,
builders, everybody that goes into putting the house up.
And then of course the final cause is a dwelling or shelter.
Once we know that the house needs to function as a dwelling
a shelter,
then we can come up with a list of the unnecessary properties.
So this is how we might think, this is obviously a very crude,
very high level example of what we're talking about.
But you can apply this methodology to anything.
And that's where it becomes really magical,
you can take that method and tear something apart, and
really understand it by applying Aristotle's four causes to it.
All right, this provides us with some background with some ideas
of why Aristotle developed this categorical system of logic.
And as you go through this module, look for these ideas,
look at how these ideas informed how Aristotle thought
about logic.
And it will help you better understand putting categorical
statements together, and then when you get to categorical
syllogisms, this philosophy will help you and
help inform how you do that in a richer way.