In this video I'm going to walk you through
using Venn diagrams to test two
arguments for validity. So I've got
a couple arguments that we're going to
look at we'll start obviously with this
first one here that's on screen and to
begin we're going to draw our diagram
we're going to draw three overlapping circles to begin
the process of testing these arguments
for validity. And as we look at the--
argument we need to indicate
which circles represent which terms so
we're going to start with the second term
in the conclusion first and we indicate
that on the lower right circle, so we'll
put our poets, P there for poets
and then we use the middle term which shows
up in the second premise in the
conclusion and so we'll put logicians
here in the bottom right and then our
our first term the scientists we're
going to indicate on the top circle here.
Alright now we've got all of our
circles and they're labeled
appropriately so we want to start to
look at the argument and fill in
and represent those premises in the diagram itself.
So we'll start with the universal
statement so out of the two premises the
first premise obviously is the universal
statement, No scientists are poets and we
need to fill then and we'll look at the
areas in this on the both circles where
scientists and poets overlap
and remember we're going to fill in areas
for negative statements. So since it says
no scientists are poets, we're going to color
in this area here where the two overlap
which indicates that this is a null area
and Not this represent also no or not statement.
So this essentially says that
the area between scientists and poets
indicates that there's nothing in that
space, it's a null area and so that represents
that universal not statement.
And then the second premise is obviously a
particular statement says some
scientists are logicians remember some
means at least one, so we're going to put
an X in the area between the circle for
scientists in the circle for logicians,
and we'll put that X right there. So now
we have our two premises represented into
test the argument for validity we
have to look at the conclusion and see
if the Venn diagram does adequately
represent the conclusion, so our
conclusion is somewhat logicians are not
poets and so we're going to look at the
area between logicians and poets the
circles were those over the areas of the
circles were those overlap. And we can
see that we're going to focus on this
area here. Now the conclusion says some
logicians are not poets and you can see
that in that area that we write circled
here in green there is half of that area
where that's nulled out. So that does it
seem to indicate that the conclusion
is true, some logicians are not poets.
So based on the diagram we've now validated
that this is a valid argument
and so the Venn diagram has shown us
that this is valid. Okay, and we did that
simply by filling in the areas for the premises on our diagram
and then looking at the conclusion and hence we've conclusion is
represented by that diagram.
Okay! Now, let's look at our second one, Some actors are sculptors.
Some poets are not actors.
So, some poets are not sculptors, so let's go ahead
and start by creating our circles again.
And we'll go ahead and label those as well. We'll start with sculptors
here, put that down in the lower-- the lower right
and we'll put poets here in the lower left
and then actors at the top. Okay, since both
premises are particular statements it doesn't matter which when we start with.
We'll start with premise 1 and this essentially says-- this says that
some actors are not sculptors. So we're going put this in
ah, sorry, some actors are sculptors. We're going put our X in the
area between actors and sculptors.
But, since we don't know which side of this area we want to put our X
we have to straddle the line between the space between
the area that overlaps actors and sculptors.
So, we're going to stick our X there, if we put our X in either side
of that circle, we're going to over commit. We're going to state something
more than what the premise states, so we want to stick it in the on the line
there. So we don't overstate in the diagram what stated in the premises.
And then we're going to do the same thing for premise 2.
Some poets are not actors and well
because there's a couple of different places we could put it
and we don't know which one we're going go ahead
and stick that on the line just like that. So, now we have our
premises represented in the diagram itself and now we need to look
at our conclusion which says so some poets are not sculptors
and we have to see if that's represented in the diagram.
And because there's no areas that are nulled out, there's no areas
we filled in indicating a null area, then we can
conclude that this argument is invalid because the conclusion
is not represented in the argument itself.
So this is an invalid argument. OK!
So, we used our Venn diagrams here to show that the arguments
one argument is valid and one an argument is invalid
simply by representing the content of the premises
in the diagram itself and then seeing if that diagram represents
the content of the conclusion. In one case it did here
and then in the second case it did not. So one argument is valid
and one arg is invalid. And that's how you can use a Venn diagram
to test arguments for validity.