All right, we've been looking at how to construct logical
arguments.
We've looked at statements and propositions.
We've been looking at argument form,
the concept of validity and invalidity.
We've looked at simple statements, and
compound statements, and symbols, replacing those simple
and compound statements with their symbolic representation.
And the final tool that I wanna present to you is looking
at operators.
We wanna look at how operators work to combine
simple statements into compound statements.
And these operators are going to be used in constructing
arguments in your premises in your conclusion.
I'm gonna give you four.
There are others but
I'm gonna give four main operators that you can use to
construct most arguments as you need to do that, okay?
So let's look at the first operator.
This operator's called the negation, all right?
It has a symbol and you can find this on most keyboards.
The tilde symbol is the operator for negation.
It looks exactly like that.
I don't know if you can see that,
you'll have to zoom in [LAUGH] on your screen there and
the negation.
All the negation does is changes the truth value of
the proposition that follows the negation symbol, all right?
So the way we would symbolize a negation is using the tilde
with the symbol for that proposition, all right?
So let's say that A stands for Ann is home.
The tilde in front of it means,
it is not the case that Ann is home, all right.
And that's how we would phrase this.
That's all the negation does is it flips the truth
value in our argument.
We would write it this way symbolically or
we would write it out that way.
We could also say not, it is not the case that Ann is home,
or not a is the other way that you would word this.
Now it's really important, the way I have it structured here,
the way I have it worded is actually is quite important
when you're constructing arguments in logic.
We could say Ann is not home, correct?
This would have exactly the same meaning, right?
If Ann is home is true, and we wanted to reverse that and
say that, it's not the case that Ann is home or
reverse the truth value we can say that Ann is not home.
But the way that I have it written here it is to say,
it is not the case that Ann is home.
Why did I write it that way?
Well, we wanna keep our simple sentence preserved,
we wanna keep Ann is home as a simple sentence
the way that it is without adding a new word to it.
Ann is home is our simple statement, if you remember
the lesson on simple statements earlier in the course.
We wanna keep that simple statement preserved.
And we negate it by simply saying, it is not the case that.
Right, and that's gonna be very important when we're
constructing logical arguments because if you start changing
the sentences, if you start changing the simple sentences.
You're gonna lose track of what simple sentences you're
working with.
So always stated as not a or it is not the case that and
then your simple sentence.
Ann is home, Bob is home,
the grass is green whatever it is, right?
Try to keep your simple sentences preserved, so
the negation symbol will be structured exactly like that.
All right so, that's the first
symbol that we're gonna be concerned with, the negation.
The second one is called the conjunction,
the conjunction symbol.
And this is the and operator.
In logic, you can use an ampersand or a dot.
In some older logic textbooks, you'll see an ampersand used.
Modern textbooks tend to use the little dot symbol.
If you're a computer programmer, again you're gonna see some of
these symbols starting to show up in formal logic, ones that
you already are used to using in computer programming.
They operate exactly the same way, right?
So in a conjunction, I'll go back
to the bottom here the under the example, Ann is home.
A simple statement and we join it to another simple statement,
Bob is home.
We can symbolize that as A & B or A.B and we're simply
joining two simple statements by using that and operator.
This is called a conjunction.
Ann is home and Bob is home,
is called a conjunction, a compound statement.
And each simple
statement in the conjunction is called a conjunct.
So I'm gonna say, Ann is home is a conjunct.
Bob is home is a conjunct.
In the conjunction, Ann is home and Bob is home.
Right, so when you're referring to parts of a conjunction,
you're gonna refer to those parts as conjunct.
When you're referring to the simple statements,
each simple statements is a conjunct.
By the way, you can have multiple simple statements
conjoined using the symbols here, right?
You could say, Ann is home and Bob is home, and Kyle is out,
and John is swimming.
Now you've got a conjunction with four conjuncts and
each will have it's own truth value and
those will work together to give the entire conjunction
a single truth value of true or false, right?
So that's the second operator that you're going to be using.
Conjunction, first one was negation,
now let's go to our third one.
This is the disjunction operator.
This is the or operator in our tool kit,
so the or operator uses the v on your keyboard or
if you're writing it out, you just write it out like a v,
it's called a wedge in logic.
And it's constructed very similarly to the conjunction,
only the way that the truth value works is gonna be
different.
So here we have Ann is home or Bob is home.
Each will have it's own truth value.
It creates a compound sentence,
a compound statement, joined by that conjunction.
Sorry, joined by that disjunction symbol and
then, the whole thing is called a disjunction.
As in conjunction, each part of the disjunction
has a specific name called the disjunct.
So Ann is home.
Simple statement,
that's a disjunct in the disjunction compound sentence.
And Bob is home is also a disjunct.
And we can refer to each of those parts
as a disjunct when we're talking through the argument.
Notice that we can combine disjunction and conjunction.
We can say Ann is home or Bob is home and
Kyle is swimming, right?
Now, we've combined the conjunction with
the disjunction.
We can also throw in negation in there if we wanted to.
We could say Ann is home or Bob is home and Kyle is swimming,
but it is not the case that Susie is riding her bike, right?
So we can bring all of these operators together to
create more complex,
compound statements and each of these has its truth value.
Now I want to just take a moment to look at how truth value works
in each of these scenarios.
So let's took at conjunction again.
Suppose I said, Ann is home is true and
Bob is home is true, what is the truth value, do you think of
the entire compound statement, the conjunction as a whole?
Well, if both conjuncts are true,
doesn't it seem the entire conjunction would be true.
If we're gonna say Ann is home and Bob is home and
Ann is home is true and Bob is home is true,
the whole thing would be true, right?
Because both simple statements are true.
Now let's change Bob is home to false.
Ann is home and Bob is home but Bob is home is actually
false, what do you think the truth value of the entire
conjunction would be.
Intuitively, doesn't it seem it would be false because now we're
saying that these statements since one of them is false,
the whole thing has to be false.
So in that condition, the entire conjunction would have
a truth value of false because one of the conjuncts is false.
We can do the same thing with disjunction, right?
Ann is home or Bob is home.
Let's suppose both are true,
it would seem that the entire disjunction is true.
Now let's change Bob is home to false.
Ann is home or Bob is home.
What are your intuitions tell you?
Actually in a disjunction, if either disjunct is true,
then the entire disjunction is true still, right.
So in conjunction, it made the whole conjunction false.
In disjunction, we can have one of the disjuncts as false and
still the whole disjunction is true, right.
Cuz think about that intuitively.
Ann is home or Bob is home.
Bob is home is false.
Ann is home is true, the disjunction is still true.
Now, if we changed both to false, Ann is home is false, and
Bob is home is false, then the whole disjunction becomes false,
right, that we have an intuition that that's a false statement.
Right, so that's how truth value relates to our symbols, and
our operators in constructing logical arguments.
So we have negation, we have conjunction, we have disjunction
and I'm going to give you one more called the conditional.
This is a very important construct in logic and
you'll use it pretty heavily when you're creating arguments.
Under the conditional, you'll use the arrow or the horseshoe.
You can use either, again, modern textbooks generally
go with the arrow symbol for the conditional.
They're called horseshoe [LAUGH] and arrow,
obviously under the symbol name.
The construction is down here at the bottom,
if you look under the example.
If Ann is home then, Bob is home.
That's how we write a conditional.
The way that is symbolized is you put the first symbol
sentence before the operator.
So here we have A horseshoe B or A arrow B.
A is the first simple statement, B is the second.
And the B follows what would be essentially the then statement
if we were writing it out in English, okay.
The conjunction and the disjunction,
each part of the conditional has a specific label,
a name that logicians have given it. okay.
The part that follows the if or
the part that comes before the symbol is called the antecedent.
So that would be the A or Ann is home in our example here.
That's called the antecedent.
The simple statement that follows the horseshoe,
follows the symbol or
follows the then in English, is called the consequent.
Right, the antecedent and the consequent.
Right, so here Bob is home then function is in the consequent.
Ann is home, function as the antecedent.
And it's always written that way, okay?
Now, notice too that the simple statement does not include
the if, the if is a part of the symbol itself,
the operator itself.
So if I were to ask you,
what is the antecedent of the example down here below?
You would say,
the antecedent is, Ann is home, not if Ann is home.
You leave the if and the then off the simple statements.
The consequent of this statement here,
this conditional is Bob is home not then Bob is home, all right?
The if and the then are a part of the operator,
they don't get included in the simple statements, all right?
Now again, you can add other operators here.
And say if Ann is home then Bob is home and Kyle is swimming,
right, you can group those together to use the symbols and
the operators in conjunction with each other.
All right, so those are four operators.
You can use these operators to build compound statements
that then you can use in your logical arguments.
As we get further into the course, your gonna see how these
operators are used to build arguments.