We've been looking at how to construct good arguments.
We've looked at statements and propositions.
We've looked at truth value.
Now we're looking at argument form,
how to put arguments together.
In a previous lesson, we looked at the concept of validity and
invalidity.
A valid argument is an argument that is in the proper form.
I tried to illustrate how you can look at an argument and
tell whether the argument works just by looking at the form
of the argument.
What I wanna do now is show you how you can use symbolization
to determine validity,
how you can use symbolization to determine validity.
Symbolization is a concept that most people have been using
since they were in their early schooling.
We use it a lot in mathematics, where we replace numerals
with symbols so that we can better understand a structure.
And we can replace those symbols with other numerals, so
that we can have other formulas or we
can create new formulas by just plugging in different numbers.
We do it in mathematics all the time.
Logic has the same concept.
We can replace simple sentences and obviously,
compound sentences based on those simple sentences
by replacing those sentences, those statements with symbols.
And when we symbolize an argument,
we can actually see the structure a lot better.
It's easier to see the structure cuz we are not distracted
by the truth value of those statements that we
are looking at and then we can also tell validity.
We can also tell whether an argument is valid or
invalid just based on that structure, which
we're gonna be able to determine by looking at it symbolically.
Let's take an argument here and we want to determine
whether this is a valid structure or not.
Remember I said validity only has to do with form,
only has to do with the structure of the argument, and
not with the truth value of the premises.
We're gonna look at this argument,
all humans are irrational.
All rational things are conscious, or
you can say all rational things are conscious things.
Therefore, all humans are conscious.
This argument has a very specific logical structure and
we're gonna be able to tell that structure
simply by the way that the argument is put together.
We can look at that structure by looking at its form.
Here is the same argument in symbolic form.
We are going to replace human with H, rational with R, and
conscious with C and now we have
the argument structure much more clearly here.
All H are R, all R are C, therefore, all H are C.
Now what's important about this structure is this is a valid
logical form, and it doesn't matter what you plug into H,
R and C, it will always be valid.
Now, you can say, how can you tell if it's valid if you don't
know what the letters mean?
That's the exact point.
Validity only has to do with the structure,
it has nothing to do with the meaning or
the truth value of those statements that we're gonna
replace those variables with, those symbols with.
Symbols are valuable in that they can help us understand
the structure of an argument, whether the argument is valid or
invalid.
Obviously, as you're learning these things,
you'll have to learn the proper forms,
you'll have to learn the proper structure.
I'll give you some later on but for right now,
all we're concerned with is looking at the symbolic form and
then being able to tell whether that form is valid or invalid.
By the way, you probably intuitively can tell whether or
not the conclusion follows from the premises in the way that
this argument is formed.
You have an intuition whether the argument is valid because
you can tell that the conclusion does follow from the premises.
But there are structures that logicians have come up with
that you can memorize so
you can tell whether an argument is in the right form.