All right, we've been looking at constructing logical arguments.
In previous lessons, we looked at two different argument forms,
deductive arguments and inductive arguments.
What I wanna do now is start to give you some very specific
deductive argument forms.
So these are, again, only going to apply to deductive arguments,
and they are valid argument forms.
You can use these basic forms, plug in various terms and
create deductive arguments from them, all right?
So we're gonna continue on looking at argument forms, but
we're gonna focus now on looking at very specific
deductive argument forms that you can use
to construct arguments, all right?
So let's remember that deductive arguments,
we would call syllogisms.
Syllogisms have exactly two premises and one conclusion.
And the syllogisms, again, are rules that given the truth of
the premises, the conclusion necessarily follows.
And this is gonna be true for
every deductive argument form that we look at.
All right, I'm gonna give you a symbolic representation.
I'll give you an example.
I'll give you the Latin name for each of these forms.
And then you can use these, not only to construct arguments but
as you're doing any kind of reading, both in literature,
newspaper, anything.
Anybody that wants to make an argument,
you can start to look at the arguments they're making and
see if you can find the symbolic representation,
the form of those arguments that you're reading about, okay?
So the first argument we've see already in a previous lesson,
it's called modus ponens, literally means the mode of
putting, the modus ponens argument, all right?
The form of the argument looks like this,
actually this is the symbolic representation
that's verbalized in an English sentence.
We say if p then q.
And here's why we call it the mode of putting,
we're gonna put forth the antecedent of the conditional in
the first premise.
We're asserting it, we're claiming it's true.
All right, so we're gonna assert the antecedent here and
then that allows us to conclude the consequent.
All right, here's an example.
If Jerry grows a mustache, then George grows one.
Jerry does grow a mustache, again, asserting that antecedent
in the first conditional, first premise, we can then conclude
therefore George will grow a mustache, all right?
And then here is the symbolic form of that argument,
p arrow q.
Assert p conclude q, the modus ponens argument.
And remember, you can insert any value, any simple or compound
statement for p or q and the structure is still valid, right?
And obviously you wanna use true premises there, so
that you can conclude something that's also true.
But this is the modus ponens form, it's always valid,
and it's a deductive form of argumentation, modus ponens.
Let's look at the next one.
This is called the modus tollens or the mode of taking.
The mode of taking, the modus tollens argument.
Again, another valid argument form.
This one says if p then q,
conditional in the first premise we're gonna negate or
take away, that's why it's called the mode of taking.
We're gonna negate the consequent in the second
premise, not q, therefore we can conclude with logical necessity,
therefore not p, therefore not p.
If p then q, not q therefore not p.
Notice that it's different from the modus ponens,
in that in the modus ponens we're asserting the antecedent
and concluding the consequent.
Here we're negating the consequent and
asserting the antecedent.
All right, here's an example,
if you are in college then you are exhausted.
It's not the case that you're exhausted.
Therefore, it is not the case that you're in college.
Now you might say that there's something, what does that mean,
how come we can we say that it's not the case that you're in
college based on the case that you're not exhausted?
Because the first premise tells us that it's necessarily true
that if you're in college then you must be exhausted.
Since you're not exhausted,
it's impossible that you're in college, okay?
That's what the form of the argument,
that's what a deductive argument allows us to do, right.
And here's the symbolic form.
We say p arrow q, ~q therefore ~p,
that's the form of the argument.
You can plug any value, compound or simple statements for p or
q, still have a valid argument form and
construct a valid logical argument.
Whether the argument is sound of course is gonna be dependent
upon whether or not your premises are true, all right?
Now, I'm gonna give you some real-world
examples of modus tollens at work.
All right, you can see how, in literature,
you can actually pull these argument forms out when you're
reading something in a book or a newspaper or whatever.
Here's a couple of examples of a modus tollens argument
in literature and in a scientific publication.
First one is from Sherlock Holmes, all right?
Here's what Holmes says, a dog was kept in the stalls, and
yet, though someone had been in and
fetched out a horse, he had not barked.
Obviously the visitor was someone whom the dog knew well.
That is the modus tollens argument,
it's the mode of taking.
You can actually pull out the premises here and
stick it in that logical structure, in that form, and
see how it is a modus tollens.
In fact, if you wanna pause your video, try to do that.
Try to pull out the premises of Holmes' argument and
put it in a modus tollens form from the previous slide.
See if you can do that.
Here's another example.
If the universe were infinitely old, there would be no hydrogen
left in it since hydrogen is steadily converted into helium
throughout the universe and this conversion is a one-way process.
But in fact the universe consists almost
entirely of hydrogen.
It is not the case that, even though it looks like a positive
statement, Hoyle is actually reversing the truth value
of the consequent in the first premise.
Thus the universe must have had a definite beginning according
to Hoyle, right?
Very interesting argument that is a modus tollens argument.
Again, if you wanted to pause the video,
see if you can put the argument
into modus tollens form in the format that we looked at before.
But these are two examples of modus tollens, the mode of
taking argument in literature and in a scientific publication.
There's another type of modus tollens that we can make,
another type of argument and I wanna look at that as well.
Have you ever had a conversation with someone, and said okay, for
the sake of argument I'm gonna assume you're right.
Let's see what happens,
let's see what happens if I assume you're right.
That's a modus tollens type of argument and
it's called a reductio ad absurdum, that's the Latin name.
Literally means a reduction to the absurd,
a reductio ad absurdum.
But it's a type of motus tollens at the end of the day,
all right?
So let's suppose you wanna prove proposition p is true,
you assume its negation,
you assume that not p is true or that p is false, okay?
Remember your goal is to prove p,
but you're gonna start by assuming that p is false.
From that assumption, you derive another proposition, and
that proposition has to be false because it's absurd, okay?
So if not p is true, this other thing turns out to be also true.
But that other thing, that q,
is false, because it's absurd, therefore p must be true.
In other words it's impossible that not p is true
because it involves a contradiction or an absurdity.
That's a reductio ad absurdum argument, and
it is a type of modus tollens.
Now, if this is a little confusing,
let me give you an example to show you how this actually works
in the real world.
Let's suppose that you wanna prove that the earth is round.
You start by assuming it's a negation.
So you say, suppose the earth is flat.
If the earth is flat, it has edges and
it would be possible to fall off the edge.
In such a case, people and animals
regularly would be falling off the edge of the earth.
But that's a ridiculous think to believe, because people and
animals don't actually fall off the earth, it's an absurdity.
So assuming the opposite of the thing you wanna prove,
that the earth is round, assuming that the earth is flat,
we end up with an absurdity that animals and
people are constantly falling off the earth.
That's just not true.
Therefore, it seems clear that the earth is not flat or
the earth is round.
That's our original proposition that we wanna prove to be true.
So this is essentially a modus tollens argument
in the reductio ad absurdum form.
And anytime you say to a friend or
someone else that you are talking with, a colleague.
Anytime you say, okay, for the sake of argument let's assume
you're true, your conclusion is true, you're using a reductio ad
absurdum argument which is a form of modus tollens.
So that's a very interesting way that we can use that same type
of argumentation form in a little bit of a different
format.
All right, the third one I wanna give you is called
the hypothetical syllogism.
And you can see from the name probably that we're gonna be
working with conditionals here.
All right, the form of the argument looks like this.
If p then q, if q then r, therefore if p then r.
So we're taking the consequent of the first conditional and
making it the antecedent of the second conditional, and
introducing a new consequent.
And then in the conclusion,
we take the antecedent of the first conditional and
associate that with the consequent of the second
conditional in a new conditional in the conclusion, all right?
So here's an example,
if you're a Monty Python fan you'll recognize this.
If she's as light as a duck then she's as light as wood.
If she's as light as wood, then she will float in water.
Therefore, if she's as light as a duck,
then she will float in water.
And again, if you look at this intuitively,
you can see how this works, right?
By making these associations between antecedents and
consequents we can actually come up with that third conditional
in the conclusion, and you can see how all that works together.
And here's our symbolic form, if p arrow q, q arrow r,
conclusion therefore p arrow r.
And that's our hypothetical syllogism.
All right, so now we have three.
We have our modus ponens, we have our modus tollens, we saw
a couple of different forms of that, the reductio ad absurdum.
And now we've got a third called the hypothetical syllogism.
And we're gonna end with one final one called the disjunctive
syllogism, the disjunctive syllogism.
If you remember from our previous lesson,
we looked at the disjunctive symbol, the disjunction symbol.
Now we're gonna look at that symbol used in a syllogism.
The form is p or q for the first premise, and the second premise
we negate one of the disjuncts, it doesn't matter which one.
But whatever disjunct we negate,
that then allows us to assert as true the other disjunct, okay?
So p or q not p, therefore, q or
we could say in the second premise not q.
That would allow us in the conclusion to assert,
therefore p, right?
Example, either The Beatles are playing tonight or
The Rolling Stones are playing.
It is not the case that The Beatles are playing, so it must
be true then that The Rolling Stones are playing, all right?
Or we can say,
it is not the case that The Rolling Stones are playing,
therefore it must be true logical necessity, right.
The conclusion necessarily falls from the truth of the premises,
therefore it must be true that The Beatles are playing.
And here's our symbolic form.
We say p v p wedge q, ~p,
asserts as the conclusion q or ~q, asserts as the conclusion p.
So now we have added to your toolkit for
deductive syllogisms.
Again, you can take the symbolic version of these,
plug in any simple or compound statement
to any of these syllogisms and you have a valid argument.
If you have true premises for your arguments, for
your syllogisms,
you're gonna end up with a sound argument at the end.
And you can use these
syllogisms together to build complex arguments, and
we'll see how this is done as we move throughout the course.
Again, I wanna call your attention to the similarity
between what we're doing here in formal logic and
what you might do in a computer program.
If you've written in any modern computer language, you have
used these constructs, you've used conditional statements.
You've used conjunction statements, disjunctions,
you've used those in your computer programming
language to actually have a logical flow to your program.
And that's what we're doing with language,
that's what we're doing with concepts.
We're applying those logical flows to the way that we think
about the world, the way that we think about our ideas.
And it's very, very similar, right?
You're gonna use the same constructs in programming
as you're using in formal logic.
This is why learning formal logic can actually help you
become a better programmer, because you're gonna learn how
both of those things work together and work in synergy.
So as we move throughout the rest of the course,
we're gonna start to apply some of these concepts to what we do
in computer science.