In this video,
I'm going to show you how you can translate a standard logical
argument into a computer-based representation of that argument.
Again, what I wanna do here is lock in some of those concepts
that we've been talking about, where you can take essentially
the logical constructs that we've been working with and
apply them directly to the work that you do in computer science.
So I'm gonna use two programs to do that.
The first, you see up here on screen now is called Scratch.
It's developed by MIT.
It's a fairly complex application, but
it's very easy to use for anybody.
So it's a good training tool.
It's good visual representation of how the logical flow of
the program works.
And it's a great way to learn how to put programs together.
So if you're interested,
I put a link up to this application in the course.
And you can play with it on your own.
I'm not gonna show you how to use Scratch fully today,
I'm just gonna use it to illustrate the concepts.
And then we'll open up Visual Studio Code and I'll write some
JavaScript, and show you how to do the same thing we're doing in
Scratch, we'll do the same thing in JavaScript in a little bit.
So what you're looking at is the Scratch Canvas.
Scratch defaults to using this little cat glyph here,
this little cat character, and this character's gonna
help us as we work through this exercise.
What I've also done is put up a standard modus ponens argument,
two premises and
a conclusion, conditional obviously in the first premise.
We assert the antecedent of that premise, of premise one and
premise two, and then we conclude the consequent of
premise one at the end of the argument there, okay?
So what we're gonna do now is, I'm gonna represent
this modus ponens argument in the Scratch program.
And we'll see how all this works, okay?
So to get started, we have to create some variables,
which I've got started on.
So I've created two variables, x and y here.
And if you're not familiar with computer programing,
you can think of a variable as a container,
it's just gonna hold a value for us.
And those values are gonna be the statements that we
would use in the premise one in the conditional
of this argument over here on the left hand side, right?
So what I'm gonna do first then is actually set
the value of those variables using this little thing here,
this little tool.
This is the set tool, and I'm gonna set y to a value and
x to a value.
I'm gonna make y equal to Kelsey goes to school.
And you can see that's the equivalent of the consequent of
our conditional here in the left, in the modus ponens.
And then x is of course gonna be equal to John goes to school,
okay?
So now we got our two variables that we're setting through
this one puzzle piece.
The metaphor that they're using here is that of a puzzle, and
you put all the pieces together, and
then you can run the application.
Right, so now that we've got our variable set,
we actually need our conditional.
We're gonna construct premise one,
if you will, in the application.
So I wanna go to the control panel, the control tab and
drag the if then block over to the canvas.
And then we got to tell our if then block what to look for.
So essentially what we're gonna do now is say, if the variable
equals our antecedent of our conditional in the modus ponens.
So I need to grab the operator.
It's gonna be the equivalent operator, and
I'll drop that into this control.
And then what we're gonna say is if x is equal to the value,
John goes to school.
All right, so
this is the antecedent essentially of our conditional.
And we're saying if that's true,
then we're gonna do something else.
And that something else is that we're gonna have the cat
say something to us.
So where the cat's essentially gonna repeat back
the consequence of our argument,
of our conditional in our first premise.
So if x equals John goes to school, then say the consequent,
and we'll have him say the consequent for
five seconds, all right?
We'll plug that into our set statements there.
And now we have our conditional set up.
So if John goes to school, then Kelsey does.
If x equals John goes to school, which essentially means,
if x is equal to the value of that, if that's true,
then repeat back the consequent, Kelsey goes to school, right?
Now we need one more thing,
we need an event to kick off the process.
So we're gonna essentially say when the go button,
the flag is the go button, when the go button is clicked,
run this program, set the two values, and
then see if the condition matches.
If it is, then repeat back the consequent.
So let's go ahead and do that.
So you can see our little cat over here on the left said,
Kelsey goes to school, because the condition was met.
And therefore, essentially what we're doing is we're saying
premise two is true.
x does equal John goes to school.
Therefore, we can then repeat back the consequent,
Kelsey goes to school.
Now to illustrate this further, let's go and
change this last value to work.
So what this is essentially does is changes the truth value of
the antecedent, John goes to school,
to false in this conditional here, in the program itself.
So now if you click the go button,
you'll see the cat doesn't say anything.
That's because the condition wasn't met,
so it's not gonna repeat back that statement.
So this is just a nice visual representation of
logical flow in a program.
And what I wanna illustrate here is that we can represent
the modus ponens argument very nicely and
very easily in logical flow in a computer program.
And this program, Scratch, allows us to illustrate that.
And you can even play around with this, and
build your own applications, using a lot of the constructs
that we've already studied in the project.
All right, I wanna switch gears a little bit, and go from this
visual tool to actually looking at a code editor.
And we'll look at some JavaScript code.
This is Visual Studio Code, is the name of the program, and
it's a software development editor,
a code editor that we can use to write software.
And it's not important that you understand
either Visual Studio Code or
JavaScript, that's not the point of this.
It's just merely to illustrate how we can translate
arguments like the modus ponens that we've been looking at
to computer code, to see how the two are related.
So I've got the code editor open here, and
I have a very simple website.
I've got an index.html.
And in the body of that, I'm loading this logicStatements.js
file, which is this file here.
And this program, this script does something very simple,
right?
So we're gonna take a quick look at this and see how this goes.
Now, like in the Scratch editor, I have two variables,
I got an x and a y.
I've set y to Kelsey goes to school,
I've set x to John goes to school.
And then we have our conditional,
our if then essentially.
So the braces here represent the then.
This only executes if the if statement,
if the statement inside the parenthesis, if that is met,
if that condition is met.
And then we get this alert,
which essentially pops up a little message box.
And in this case will pop up, Kelsey goes to school, right?
So what this program is saying is,
if the value of x is equal to this phrase, John goes to
school, then show a message that says that Kelsey goes to school.
Okay, so let's run it and we'll see what it does here.
We run our web server.
It'll load the web server here, and then we should see a little
message pop up that says Kelsey goes to school.
So the condition was met, so we get our message.
That's all that's going on here, right?
Let's go back to code, and I'll go ahead and
stop the web server.
Now this is essentially a conditional,
just like we have in our modus ponens argument.
We can also add other compound statements.
So let me go ahead and add a new variable, we'll call this z, and
we'll make this equals to Bob goes to work.
So let's go ahead and add a conjunction.
So I'm gonna say and include it in our conditional,
and if z is equal to Bob goes to work,
then we're gonna show Kelsey goes to school.
So now we have a conjunction in our conditional statement.
And we saw a conjunction, obviously
we can use a conjunction in our logical arguments as well.
So let's go ahead and run this and see what happens.
And again, because both conditions are met,
we should be able to see a little alert again, and
that says Kelsey goes to school.
Now let's go ahead and change our program and
see what happens.
We'll actually change the phrasing of this second phrase.
We'll say Bob goes to the gym.
And we should no longer see our message, our alert.
Because remember, the way a conditional works
is that both conjuncts have to be true in order for
the conjunction as a whole to be true.
So the if statement will essentially fail,
the condition will not be met.
So let's go ahead and start that and see what this looks like.
Notice we get our local host running.
We have our web server running,
I just have a test message in here to show that it's running.
But we don't get our message, the alert never popped up,
because the condition was not met, all right?
So it works the same way.
Let's go back now and do a disjunction,
just to test our concept here.
So we'll go ahead and change this to OR.
And, in JavaScript, the pipe symbol is used for the OR.
So now this says if John goes to school is true, OR
Bob goes to the gym is true, then pop up our alert.
Now remember in a disjunction, either disjunct can be true for
the disjunction to be true.
So because x does equal the value that we're looking for,
even though z doesn't, we still should see our alert.
So let's go ahead and run this, and we'll see how that works.
Start up our web server and then I will switch over to
the browser and we'll see our alert, Kelsey goes to school.
All right, because one of the discjuncts is true, so
the whole disjunction, the disjunction as a whole is true.
All right, so this is just a quick illustration to show
how you can take the logical constructs that we're
dealing with in formal logic, and
translate them to computer programs.
And as you learn how to think this way,
as you learn how to apply these concepts, you're gonna be much
better at writing programs when you get to that point.