In previous lessons we were looking at argument form.
Argument form is the structure of a logical argument
in which we place premises and
conclusions that are made up of statements and propositions.
What we're gonna do in this lesson,
and in subsequent lessons,
is dive a little bit deeper into specific argument forms.
Specifically we're gonna look at deductive arguments and
inductive arguments and how you construct these.
We talked a little bit about validity in a previous lesson.
We're gonna go a little bit more deeper into those concepts.
So, just to remind you,
we've already talked about propositions and
as we worked through the structure of arguments,
as we worked through the toolkit,
remember that it's propositions that are true or false.
If you need a reminder on this,
I would encourage you to go back to a previous lesson and
then just get a quick review on what propositions are.
But in our taxonomy, in our overall structure,
in our toolkit, remember that propositions are true and
false in logic, and that's going to be very important as we
work on constructing these arguments.
Now what I wanna do is talk about deductive syllogism.
I introduced the term syllogism in a previous lesson.
A syllogism is just an argument form,
a structure of an argument.
Syllogisms have two premises and that's followed by a conclusion.
And we're gonna look at the form of argument called
deductive arguments.
Deductive arguments, simply put, are arguments where
if the premises are true, assuming the premises are true,
the conclusion must follow with logical necessity.
Or, to put differently, if the premises are true,
it's impossible that the conclusion is false.
That's what a deductive argument means.
So when you're looking at deductive arguments,
we're gonna look at validity in just a moment,
but when you're looking at deductive arguments,
you're gonna look at the form and you're gonna always assume,
in determining whether or not the argument is valid,
if the premises are true does the conclusion follow?
Now, notice you don't have to know whether
the premises are true
in order to determine whether the argument has a valid form.
You're just gonna ask yourself if they were true,
is it possible that the conclusion's false?
I say here that deductive arguments are the strongest type
of argument because it's impossible to for
the conclusion to be false given true premises.
Now, let's go back and revisit this notion of validity again.
If you'll recall from an earlier lesson,
validity only talks about the structure.
It talks about the relationship between the premises of
an argument and the conclusion of the argument.
It has nothing to do with whether or
not the premises are true or false.
So a deductive argument is constructed in such a way that,
again, if the premises are true, it is not possible for
the conclusion to be false.
That's the definition of a deductive argument.
It's not possible that the conclusion is false.
As I said earlier, validity only applies to deductive arguments.
Validity only applies to deductive arguments.
So we can only tell whether the conclusion is necessary given
true premises if the argument is in deductive form.
So validity, again, has to do with the form of the argument
not with the truth value of the premises.
Let's look at a couple of arguments here.
Suppose I make the claim, all shrews are nocturnal,
premise one.
Premise two, all shrews are insectivores.
The conclusion therefore,
at least some insectivores are nocturnal.
This is a valid argument form.
Now suppose you don't know what shrews are, or you don't know
the meaning of nocturnal, it doesn't really matter does it?
Because we can tell that this is a valid form
by looking at the structure.
We can say if it's true,
we don't know cuz we don't know the meaning of the terms, but
if it is true that all shrews are nocturnal, and
if it is true that all shrews are insectivores, then it's
absolutely certain that at least some insectivores are nocturnal.
We don't have to know what nocturnal and
insectivores or shrews are to know that
the conclusion follows with logical necessity.
So that is a valid deductive argument and
it's in a valid form.
As we learned earlier we can symbolize all of this.
We can put symbols in place of these actual terms.
So we can replace shrews with S, nocturnal with N,
insectivores with I.
And we can get our same argument structure, All S are N,
All S are I, therefore, at least some I are N.
This is a valid form.
And you can even see with just using symbols,
that if we assume the premises are true,
the conclusion must follow with logical necessity.
That's what a deductive argument does.
And we can determine that validity just based on
the structure.
So as you are looking at arguments,
as you are constructing them, as you're analyzing them, the first
step in looking at a deductive argument is to determine whether
or not the deductive argument is in valid form.
That's the first step.
It doesn't mean that you've done everything you need to do, but
you at least need to do that part.
If the argument is not in valid form, then you can stop.
The analysis is over, you can say it's now a bad argument.
You don't need to really do any further analysis because it's
not in the right form.
If it is in a valid form, then you're gonna want to go on
to the next step and take a look at
how the form actually relates to the truth value of the premises.
So valid form is where the argument
is in the proper structure.
And then an invalid argument,
an invalid form, is where the conclusion
does not necessarily follow from the truth of the premises.
Put another way, even if you assume the premises are true,
if its possible that the conclusion is false,
then the argument is invalid.
So let's look at this argument.
All in symbolic form,
we're not gonna put any terms in here just now.
Let's suppose we said all a are b, all a are c, therefore,
all b are c.
This is an invalid form because it could be true that
both of the premises are true but
it's also possible that the conclusion is false.
We cannot derive this conclusion from those premises.
It's possible for
the conclusion to be false, even given true premises.
If you're following along, you'll notice that there was one
minor change between this argument and
the argument we just looked at.
What is that change?
Well, we changed in the conclusion the sum to all and
that makes the argument invalid.
Just by changing that one word it makes the argument
invalid because this conclusion
does not follow with logical necessity from those premises.
Let's illustrate it by looking at it with actual terms in it.
All crayons are colored.
All crayons are pigmented.
Therefore, all colored things and pigmented things.
All right that is an invalid argument.
Now you might be saying but, wait Paul, hold on a second.
That conclusion is true.
Yes, it is, right?
Just assuming we're not gonna quibble with language,
all colored things are pigmented things.
So how come this is an invalid argument?
The reason it's invalid is because we cannot get this
conclusion from the premises I've given you.
From the premises all crayons are colored and
all crayons are pigmented, we cannot derive the conclusion
all colors things are pigmented things,
even though that conclusion is true.
We don't get it from the premises.
In order for
an argument to work the premises have to give us reason
to believe the conclusion is true and that's not true here.
It's still possible,
given our premises, that that conclusion is false.
Therefore, it's an invalid form.
So validity has to do with the structure of the argument.
Based on the possible truth of the premises,
it's impossible that the conclusion is false.
If it is possible that conclusion is false
it's invalid.
If it's impossible the conclusion is false,
then it's valid.
And that's what validity has to do with in terms of
deductive arguments.