Hi and welcome to this module on critical thinking.
You've been studying different forms of logical analysis.
We've given you some information on how you construct statements
and put arguments together.
This module really is about application.
So now that you have all these tools, what do you do with them?
And critical thinking really is the discipline
of applying logical analysis to the world.
Looking at arguments people are making, arguments that you want
to develop and then focusing those arguments in a very
specific way so that you can convince people of something.
Critical thinking is a little bit broader than logic itself.
Critical thinking involves an attitude as well as a set of
analytic tools that you can use and we really
call it a discipline and you want to think of it as a way of
being in the world, a way of thinking about the world.
So to me, critical thinking is the important
practical application of logic.
So in this module, you're going to see less of that kind of
mathematical syllogistic approach to logic, and more of
how you apply it, how you think about actual world problems.
So in this module, or in this video, what I'd like to do
is talk through an example of a person that tried to apply this
methodology to the way that he thought about the world,
and we're gonna look at this example as a way of kind of
a radical example.
It's an extreme example but
it's a way of being a critical thinker and
applying these skills that we've been looking at.
Right so what is critical thinking as a discipline?
Well, one way to word this or one way to define it is to say
that it's the discipline that allows us to shape and
refine and exercise our thoughts.
Exercise the faculties or the capacity,
the capabilities of our mind to think more clearly about
the subjects that we're discussing, right?
And we can apply this to any subject, right?
We can be a critical thinker about any subject.
When we think of the term critical,
it sounds like it's a negative term,
we tend to think of critical as being critical of somebody and
that tends to have a negative connotation.
But really critical thinking is just about being hyper-aware of
what's going on, of what people are claiming, of what you're
trying to claim, and doing that analysis in depth.
Just being aware of what you're saying, and
what you're hearing, and being able to tear those ideas apart
in a more refined way, okay?
So, I used the example here,
develop the skills to argue without being argumentative.
Without just disagreeing with everything because you feel like
disagreeing with everything.
Arguing for a point, because there's a good
goal that you have in mind, a virtuous goal, is different than
just disagreeing with everything for the sake of disagreement.
We want to develop that discipline.
How do you argue without being overly argumentative?
How do you examine ideas and adopt all sides of an idea so
you can test it for its truth.
I have a really good quote here from Aristotle.
It's one of my favorites.
It's a mark of an educated mind,
to be able to entertain a thought without holding it.
How many of us can do that really well.
We can actually adopt the other side.
Think about your political stands.
Right, we all tend to have a critical view point.
Can you fully adopt the other side is if you held it
without really accepting it as true?
That's the year marks of a critical thinker,
being able to see the other side fully and
then say I actually disagree and here's why.
Okay?
Not just disagreeing with sound bytes or
something that you think the other side is holding.
It's actually adopting that other side's position fully.
Understanding why it's rational.
If it is rational and why it's reasonable and
then providing a disagreeing argument against that idea.
That's critical thinking.
That's what it means to embody the nature of
a critical thinker.
So in a lot of ways,
critical thinking we define it as an intellectual virtue.
An intellectual virtue.
So what is virtuous habit, a virtuous disposition?
It's those parts of your intellectual life
that just make you better at life in general, right.
It gives you a kind of excellence and again we use
the term here disposition and discipline very intentionally.
A disposition is something that starts to become natural
the more you do it.
If you have a disposition,
when you walk up to an ice cream stand for example,
if you have a disposition to choose vanilla over chocolate,
that's something that's kind of ingrained in you, right?
Like when you go to the ice cream stand,
you kind of have to think a lot of you don't wanna get vanilla.
Disposition is to always get vanilla ice cream or
chocolate or whatever it is.
Right?
It's the, it's your, a habit of mind.
It's a way that you respond to the world.
Now most of us have some dispositions which we wish we
didn't have, they're not virtuous, they're things that we
don't want to do naturally and so it takes a lot of work to
develop new dispositions, to develop new habits.
And if you approach arguments, if you approach your thought
life in a way that has some habits that you wanna change,
logic can actually help you change those dispositions and
develop new ones, okay?
So that's what intellectual virtue entails.
It's about developing these new dispositions, okay?
So using logic, using logical analysis
can help you become a critical thinker and then hopefully live
a better life because of it or have better success in life
because you've developed these skills, right.
So we're gonna talk about Descartes.
We're gonna talk about this thinker and
the way that he attempted to use critical thinking and
logic to evaluate truth, right?
That's really what critical thinking is all about,
is to get us closer to the truth, and
hopefully, the the more you're aligned with truth,
the more successful you're going to be.
So we're going to take these ideas,
these intellectual virtues, and I'm going to show you an example
of a thinker that attempted to apply these to his life and
with the goal of getting closer the truth.
Now that thinker is Rene Descartes
obviously a French Philosopher lived in Rome from
the late 1500s to the middle of 1600s.
A lot of people believe that Descartes changed Western
thought forever.
His methodology, his skeptical attitude really helped define
modern thought for most people in the West,
without even knowing, most of us don't even know about this.
You may have never heard of Descartes before but he had
a huge influence in the way that we think about the world.
So Descartes was raised like many of us.
He was raised in a very prescribed environment.
He was told a lot of things as a child.
He was given a lot of truths,
things that he just accepted as true, from family, parents,
priests, people, friends, people in the school, instructors.
He was told all of these things were true and he accepted them
as true but as he got older he started realizing that some
of the things that he was told weren't actually true.
There was a lot of facts that people taught him
that he learned were not facts at all.
They were just opinions, or if you looked at the same fact in
a different way, it had a completely different meaning and
this really started to bother Descartes.
Descartes was a little bit more sensitive,
maybe than most of us, a lot of us learned about things our
parents told us or our teachers told us.
We learned their false and we say,
okay, well, that's unfortunate, I've now learned the truth and
I'll move on.
Descartes was not that way, he was really bothered by
the fact that all of these things that he was learning, or
a lot of the things that he was learning were either untrue, or
could be viewed in a different way.
And so he really wanted to get to a place where
he could change that, he wanted to get to something a little bit
more solid, than the methodology that he was given as a child.
Okay, so he set out to doubt everything,
that was his big insight, I guess you can call.
He really set out to doubt everything he was taught and
that methodology really changed the way that he approached
the world and changed philosophy as we know it.
Right, so what motivated the method?
Well, he, again, was exposed to a lot of falsities.
He wanted to change that.
And he realized that the problem was with the structure of his
knowledge.
It was with the structure of his knowledge.
The individual facts being false rather than true
were problematic.
But he realized that the method that brought
about those falsehoods was faulty, right?
And that's what really, really struck him, is if he were taught
truth by his church, by his teachers, by his parents, and
that methodology brought about the wrong result,
we really need to look at the methodology.
Now this is a really good example of
critical thinking, right?
Descartes was raised a certain way.
He believed certain things based on how he was raised, and
the things that he was taught.
And he said, you know what?
This doesn't seem to be working.
There's a problem here.
And so critically,
he said I'm gonna adopt a different viewpoint.
I'm gonna take a completely different viewpoint on this.
I'm gonna set aside everything that I was taught as a child and
as a young adult, and I'm going to evaluate it.
I'm gonna look at it critically, okay?
So he was then looking for a better foundation.
He wanted to look for a better methodology.
So in his early adulthood, he took some time off and
he hid himself away to this little cabin in a mountain.
I think it was called The Stove.
It was essentially just a one room
building with a large heater in it, a large stove in it.
And he sat there and
he thought through how he was gonna solve this problem.
And the way that he did this was to expose everything that he
believed to this radical doubt methodology, okay.
So we call this the Cartesian method, and
that's what it has become known as in philosophy.
All right, so he was after certainty.
Now most philosophers think that certainty is a goal that
we cannot reach.
But Descartes, in his time in life and
where he was in his intellectual development, believed that
certainty was possible and so that was his goal was.
He wants to get rid of anything that he could doubt, and so
he's after certainty.
And again, he may have just done this as a method,
he may not have wanted to apply this in his life moving forward.
But for this time in his life,
he said this is what I'm gonna do.
I'm gonna go after certainty.
And so in order to get to certainty, I'm gonna look at all
my beliefs, all the categories of the things that I believe,
and I'm gonna subject them to doubt.
Can I doubt them?
All right, but here's a nice little quote.
He says reason now persuades me that I should withhold
my assent,
no less carefully from things which are not plainly certain.
There is his goal of certainty and
indubitable than I would to what is patently false.
All right, so he's gonna be critical of the things that he
holds as true, to see if they can be doubted,
just as he would to those things that he knows are false.
He's gonna doubt everything.
Al right, so that's the approach he took to his philosophy.
So he's in this cabin, he's heating things up
with his stove, he's thinking about the world.
He's thinking about his philosophy and
he starts to tear down everything.
Now obviously, he's got a huge problem because you can't
go through every single belief you have.
It would take years, if you can do it at all.
So you can't write down everything, I believe x,
I believe y, I believe z, and ask can I doubt it?
So what he decided to do is go after categories of beliefs,
all right, he's gonna go after the categories of things.
And say is the categorical area of this belief,
is that a solid foundation for truth and certainty, right?
So he starts out with things that he believes
by way of the senses.
That seems like a pretty solid area, right?
So he looks at all the things
that he believes through the senses.
I believe I see a red object, actually in the cabin he talks
about, he has a candle on the table and the candle's burning.
He's looking at something beyond the candle.
And he's like,
I see all of these objects through my visual sensation,
I feel the heat of the stove, I can hear the birds chirping.
Those seem pretty solid.
But can I be deceived?
Is it possible to doubt them?
Well, it only takes just a couple a minutes of thinking and
you say I absolutely can doubt them, right.
My senses deceive me all the time.
As he was looking at the candle,
the candle flame was letting off heat, and
the object behind the heat from the candle had a different view.
It was actually waving cuz of the heat,
than it had if he was looking at it from the side, right?
It didn't have that weird sensation.
So his senses were actually providing him with inaccurate
information about the world.
And he said, I can absolutely doubt my senses.
And people get to see it all the time.
You hear something that doesn't, or you interpret what you hear
as something that doesn't actually exist, right?
There's something outside the house, or
something inside the house, whatever, okay.
So he said that's an easy category to dismiss.
I can doubt everything in my senses.
What about beliefs formed by reason, logic, mathematics?
Those have to be solid, right, those have to be beyond doubt.
1 plus 1 equals 2 all the time.
There's no situation where it actually ever does not
equal two, so that seems like a really solid
place to go in terms of finding truth.
As he thought about this, for many pages in his journal,
he says, I think I've got it.
I think I've found the foundation.
Mathematics has got to be it.
There's no way that I can come up with a counterexample
to these mathematical principles that I've learned.
And then he stumbled upon something.
He said,
I actually can be deceived by things that I learn from reason.
How is that possible?
He said what if I'm being deceived by what he termed as
an evil demon?
What if there's this malevolent demon out there and
he is tricking me?
And he invented this whole system of mathematics,
this whole system of logic, to trick me and
think that it's absolutely true.
Provide no way around it, no way of finding falsehood,
but the whole system is completely made up.
And the real world doesn't operate that way at all.
If you've ever seen the movie The Matrix,
that movie kind of plays on this idea, right, that Cartesian
being duped like Descartes thought he probably was duped or
possibly was duped, right?
Our whole mental life could be a fabrication by an evil demon or
a mad scientist or whatever.
And so there's really no way to disprove it.
If the evil demon, the math scientist is deceiving me,
I have no way of disproving that that demon is deceiving me,
that I'm being tricked.
Cuz you can never get outside of that trickery
to learn that you're being tricked.
So he ended up having to dismiss mathematics.
He ended up having dismissed the fundamental laws of logic,
he said reason is not indubitable.
I can certainly doubt reason, and
the evil demon will approach, the evil demon construct,
if you will, is the way that he said that that's possible.
So now he's struggling, right?
I mean, if you can't trust your senses,
you can't trust mathematics, you can't trust logic.
He obviously knows that he can't trust all the facts that he was
given by parents and teachers, right?
Those are certainly open to doubt, cuz he's found
that a lot of those are wrong, or incorrect, or untrue.
Now he's stuck, where do you go from here?
There is really no foundation, there is really no other area,
there is no other category that you can run to where you could
have these indubitable ideas, these ideas behind doubt.
Well, he did stumble upon something as you probably knew I
was going to tell you.
He actually found what he would consider pay dirt.
He found a rock solid foundation that not even the evil demon
could trick him on.
And that foundation is that he was thinking.
He said as I'm going through this exercise, I have to find
the one thing that I can build my whole system upon Not even
the evil demon can trick me on, and that's that he was doubting.
So he actually put this to the test.
Playing the role of a critical thinker, he said,
I know that I'm thinking, I seem to be doubting,
I'm going through this process, could I doubt that I'm doubting?
That just seems like a reasonable question for
a critical thinker to ask.
Is it possible to doubt that I'm doubting?
And he said, in order for
me to be doubting, I have to be thinking.
And to doubt that I'm a thinking thing would be a contradiction.
You can't doubt that you're a thinking thing because then
you're thinking in order to doubt.
So as he thought more about this he said,
that's impossible to fake.
Even if there is an evil demon tricking me about everything
else, I still have to be a thinking thing
in order to be tricked by the evil demon.
So the one thing that is beyond doubt,
that is beyond critical analysis,
that cannot be proven false, is that I'm a thinking thing.
I am a thing that thinks.
And that's where Descartes came up with his famous phrase,
[FOREIGN], I think, therefore I am.
Now this does not mean that Descartes is somehow
thinking himself into existence, it's not a claim of being,
it's not a claim of existence, it's a claim of knowledge.
Another way to say this is,
I think, therefore I know that I am.
I think therefore I can be certain that I'm a thinking
thing, that I exist.
It's impossible to doubt that I am a thinking existing thing.
And Descartes saw this phrase,
saw this idea, as a foundation for all of knowledge.
And he built up a system of knowledge just using this very
seemingly modest idea, I'm a thinking thing, I cannot doubt
it, therefore there has to be something that exists,
there has to be something real.
Now, a lot of people disagree with the next move Descartes
made and how we built up this system from this phrase.
But the point of this lecture, the point of this lesson,
is that Descartes applied a critical methodology,
an analytic methodology as a critical thinker.
And I'm using this to show how you can use that methodology to
subject even your most foundational beliefs to analysis
and to come up with a way of getting around doubts and
falsehoods.
So he was willing to do this,
he was willing to expose his beliefs, everything he believed,
even the foundation of his beliefs, to critical thought to
analyze them, and by doing that, he actually ended up changing
western though, hopefully for the better in the long run.
So even if you don't agree with Descartes' approach,
you don't think that he actually discovered anything interesting,
the point of this lesson is about the methodology.
It's about taking your cherished beliefs,
taking the things you've been taught all your life, and
exposing them to the light of doubt.
To asking yourself, is this really true?
Is what I'm hearing on television actually the case?
Is what this politician is saying, even if you like
the politician, is that person actually giving me what is true?
Or do I need to think about it more?
This is what critical thinking is all about.
And in the the upcoming lessons in this module, we're
gonna walk you through some of the tools that you can use to be
a better critical thinker.
Taking the logical analysis that we've done in the first few
modules, and then applying them to problems in the real world.