>> Hi and welcome back.
I've been talking with Dr. Paul Herrick,
the author of the textbook that we've been
using in this course, Think With Socrates.
In the last video, we talked
a little bit about logical structure,
deductive reasoning,
validity and the relationship
between content and structure.
And we're giving you
this content now prior
to you getting into the lesson so you
can be prepared for the stuff that you're
going to be learning in the next couple of modules.
So what you might do is, as we
walk through the next set of slides,
as you're working through the lessons, if you get stuck,
come back and review this because I think
once you start getting into the material,
a lot of what we're going to talk about
here is going to make a lot of sense.
But what we want to do now is walk you through
some examples of deductive reasoning,
where students tend to
look at arguments that we're going to show you
and they get the- they evaluate them in the wrong way.
And Dr. Herrick's going to talk
a little bit about why that happens,
and how you can actually work through looking at
these arguments and kind of land on the right answers.
So, some of the stuff that you're going to see in here,
you will see on assessments.
So it's going to be worth your while to take
some time and make sure you understand this,
so that when you get to the assessments,
you can do a better job of
evaluating how you need to answer those questions.
So why don't we jump in we've got
a couple of slides here.
The slides are put together by Dr. Herrick
earlier and he's going to talk you through
some of these examples. So what's going on here?
>> Okay, so the slides that we're about to look at,
I chose because I think they show how
the study of logic can improve your reasoning.
>> Yes.
>> So, when students first look at an argument like this,
before they've studied logic,
their first guess is that the reasoning looks correct.
And it does on the surface appear to be correct.
"No birds are fish" and "No cats are birds", well,
it's true that "No cats are fish"
and it just looks correct to students at first.
It actually is an invalid argument
but it's not obvious so
we have to apply some principles of logic.
Aristotle actually developed a system of
logic that was very mathematical in nature,
and by using that system of logic,
he could actually show that this was invalid.
But this is not a valid argument,
meaning, the premises by themselves.
The information content of their premises all by itself,
does not conclusively establish the conclusion.
>> But these facts seem correct.
"No birds", it's true that no birds.
It is true that "No cats are birds."
>> It's true.
>> So why is this invalid?
It doesn't- may not make sense.
>> Yeah. So this is an example of an argument
that has true premises and a true conclusion.
And yet, it's not correct reasoning, it's not valid.
So let's think about it. When we say
that no birds are fish,
we're telling you that there are
no birds in the fish category.
But we're not telling you that there's
no- we're not telling
you that there are no cats in the fish category.
We're not saying anything about
cats in this very first premise.
>> Correct.
>> Okay, now,
the second premise says there are no cats in
the bird category but that
doesn't tell us anything about the fish category,
if you think about it.
>> So the terms aren't relating to each
other properly in
the premises, is that what you're saying?
>> Correct. They're not related
to- just because there's no birds that
are fish and there's no cats that are birds,
it does not follow.
It's not conclusively proven that no cats are fish.
So this is an example of an invalid argument.
>> So the point is that even though
these are stating true facts,
they are not related to each
other in the right way to draw this conclusion.
It doesn't make these facts
false doesn't make the statements false.
It just means that you can't get to
this statement by believing these two are true.
And again, we're going to work through
this process and the rest of the lessons in
these modules and I'll try to
show you why that's the case,
and we'll use material from your book
to kind of illustrate this.
But we're trying to show you is
that when you first read this,
if you saw this on a test,
you might say yes, that's a valid argument.
While it's structurally invalid even
though the facts that are being stated are true.
>> Now, I'll give an example to show.
Paul you said something very important,
its structure- it's structurally invalid.
Validity and invalidity are due
to the form of an argument.
The structure, not to the content or not to what
the arguments are about which we
talked about in the previous video.
>> Yeah.
>> So let me give you a parallel argument.
This argument is going to have the same structure,
the same form, and you're going to
see that it's clearly not good reasoning.
So, should I erase this?
>> Yeah, you can go ahead and erase that.
>> Okay, so when I started teaching,
we used chalk and blackboards.
So let's look at this parallel argument.
"No Microsoft employees-" I'm going to
make some room here, "-collect stamps. "
"No stamp collectors are artists."
"So, necessarily, no Microsoft employees-"
do Microsoft employees mind being called, MS employees?
>> Yes, that's totally fine. That's appropriate.
>> Microsoft Employees are artists.
Now, if you examine this,
this argument has the same
logical structure as this argument.
Except we've substituted Microsoft employees.
Well, I'm sorry, we've substituted
Microsoft employees for cats.
And we substituted stamp collectors
for birds and so forth.
Otherwise, the abstract structure is the same.
In other words, the logical form is the same.
Now, obviously the premises
do not establish the conclusion with certainty.
>> Right.
>> It's possible the conclusion is true,
but the premises don't prove it.
>> Right.
>> "No stamp collectors or artists."
Suppose that's true.
And suppose "No Microsoft
employees are stamp collectors."
That would not prove that
no Microsoft employees are artists.
>> Right, even though
all three statements could be true-.
>> Could be true.
>> You can't get to the conclusion
from this two statements.
>> Yes. And in terms of information theory,
the information content of the premises by
itself doesn't include
the information content to the conclusion.
>> Correct.
>> So this isn't- both of these arguments are
invalid because they instantiate,
as you will learn, an invalid form.
Anyway, the point I was making is,
before students have studied logic,
they'll look at an argument like
this and it looks valid to them
until they learn some logic and think
about it more critically and they
realize that's not correct reasoning.
>> Right. Can I get to that conclusion from the premise.
Again, we will look at all these terms,
look at these concepts and how you can arrive at
the right conclusion using the proper reasoning,
as we move throughout the course.
Let's look at another example.
>> Okay.
>> If I can make that happen.
Let's see, there we go. Okay, so this
is a similar situation but-.
>> Similar.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. So again,
the form of the argument is the problem.
It's not the content, it's the form.
The form is, "Some A are B,"
where A and B are categories of
things or names of categories of things.
Well, here's what I'm going to do.
I'm going to rearrange these letters,
some A are B.
And then, some B are C. And the form concludes.
So and therefore meaning the same thing.
So some A areC.
Now students before they've studied logic,
will look at this and it looks okay.
And explain Paul why it's not okay.
>> Again, for the same reason that we
saw in the last argument.
While these statements can be true.
>> Probably aren't true.
>> You cannot use the truth of these statements
to arrive at the truth of this statement.
So if you just look at the truth of the statement,
you might say, yeah, that seems like
a good argument. That's a valid argument.
It's a valid form.
You might not say that until you studied logic.
But, you would look at this and say,
I would think this is okay.
I would give it a check mark. Looks okay.
>> On the surface.
>> Correct.
But if in an argument what you're trying to do is
arrive at the truth of this statement
by believing the truth of these true two statements,
and you can't do that with this form.
>> Yeah. And now, even if these are true,
even if that's true,
and that's true, that by itself does not prove.
>> Correct.
>> That this must be true.
>> And that's worth an argument.
>> Which is what it necessarily means.
>> That's exactly right.
>> That doesn't prove this must be true.
>> Now, we would encourage you
to pause the video and look at this argument
and see if you can see
intuitively before you've learned the principles,
why you cannot arrive at
the necessary truth of
this statement by believing those are true.
Just look at it and you'll be able to see that
the conclusion does not
follow from one end to which other premises.
>> May I suggest a counter example?
>> Sure.
>> Okay. So logicians call
an argument a counterexample to an argument if
it shows that the target argument
is improper or illogical.
Here's a counterexample.
Suppose I say,
some programmers, is it okay if I pick on programmers?
>> Yeah. We're used to get picked on.
>> Some programmers are magicians
>> I think most
of the programmers in the audience would
say all programmers are magicians.
>> Well actually, it's magic what they do because
most people would find it magical.
>> Yeah, that's true.
>> Okay. Some programmers are magicians,
some magicians collect stamps.
Did you know that stamp collecting is a worldwide hobby?
>> I did not know that.
>> It is worldwide.
>> Wow.
>> Yeah. Okay. Some programmers are magicians,
some magicians collect stamps,
and then the conclusion would be what?
Some programmers collect stamps.
Now, I don't know
if there are programmers who collect stamps,
but these two premises would not prove it.
>> Correct.
>> Even if it's true that
some magicians collect stamps and
some programmers are magicians,
the problem is that this premise
doesn't tell us that the programmers who are
magicians are among the magicians who collect stamps.
Because some magicians collect stamps,
it doesn't tell us they all do.
So I don't know if the programmers who are
magicians belong to the group of
magicians who are programmers
or who are outside that group.
So this reasoning does not connect.
>> Yes. And you'll see a valid form of reasoning.
A reasoning where that does work in just a moment,
in some of the other examples.
But clearly in these examples,
you cannot get to that final statement as
a necessary conclusion based on the premises.
>> And so in Logic.
>> And you'll learn the principles
of this as we move through the lesson.
>> Yeah, it's a principle distinct.
Within logic we call this a fallacy,
meaning a mistaken reasoning.
>> Correct.
>> And again, this I think if you study logic,
you spot mistakes and
reasoning more easily, more readily.
Because you're more tuned to
the structure of an argument rather than its content.
>> Which is the point of studying logic.
>> Yeah, I think if you look just at the content,
it can mislead you.
Because looking just at the content,
you can say all that sounds fine.
But when you think about the abstract structure,
you say wait a minute, there's a problem here.
>> Yes, correct.
>> This doesn't prove this.
>> Right. Exactly. Here's another example.
>> So, all vegetarians are artists,
all programmers are vegetarians,
so all programmers are artists.
>> Valid or invalid?
>> So, is it valid or invalid?
>> So the question is, can you conclude this is
an absolute necessity if
you believe that these two statements are true?
>> So if you think about it,
this is a valid argument.
You have to think it through.
But if you'll learn
the Venn diagram technique that
can let you visually see that this is valid.
If all programmers are vegetarians, everyone of them,
and every vegetarian is an artist,
then it necessarily follows with
complete certainty that every programmer is an artist.
This is an example of a valid argument.
>> That's correct.
>> Now, it's interesting
the premises are probably not true.
And it's still valid.
So this bothers students.
>> Let's talk through that for just a moment.
What is going on here?
If you have false premises
and you have a valid argument, how do the two relate?
>> Well, this issue,
how can an argument be valid and have
false premises bothers all logic students.
And it takes a while to get over it.
It's a hump. Valid, I have to stress this in logic class.
Valid does not mean true.
In everyday life we
often use the word valid to mean true.
When you say something,
I say you're making a valid point,
and I just mean your statement's true.
In logic, valid doesn't mean true.
What valid means is,
if the premises are true, there's the premises.
If the premises are true,
the conclusion must be true.
If it were true that all programmers are vegetarians,
and if it were true that all vegetarians are artists,
given those two hypothetical facts,
this would be true.
That's what valid means.
>> Yep.
>> But the premises don't have to be
true for an argument to be valid.
This is in fact,
one of the beauties of deductive reasoning,
is that we can reason from one premise to another,
from one idea to another without
worrying about whether our starting point is true or not,
and then logic can tell us
whether our reasoning is correct.
>>Yes.
>> Whether our premises are true is a separate task.
>> And we'll separate those in the course.
We'll talk through the structure part of making
an argument and the content part of
making an argument as two separate things.
What we cal truth, value, and validity.
>> Right.
>> And we've been using terms premises
and conclusions. You'll learn about those.
Premises are just the reasons that you
offer for something else to be true.
If you believe the reasons,
you should conclude that the final statement is true.
>> And I might add a philosophical point, Paul.
>> Sure, sure, sure.
>> The ultimate goal of
reasoning is to get at the truth of the matter.
>> Yeah, that's right.
>> At the truth of some matter.
That's ultimately why we reason.
And so, if an argument is valid,
and in addition, it has all true premises.
Well, I should say if a deductive argument
>> Yes.
>> Is valid and it has all true premises,
we call that Argument Sound.
So, Soundness, for Deductive Arguments,
is what we're ultimately after.
>> That's correct.
>> We're after arguments that
have true premises and their reasoning,
their internal reasoning is valid.
And so, Sound brings in truth.
>> Right. So, what you're going to learn in the course is
to separate those at the beginning,
so that you can construct better arguments.
And then, you bring them back at
the end to produce
sound arguments which is really your goal.
>> And this can help you in everyday life.
>> For sure.
>> Because sometimes we reason with
each other and someone's reasoning with us,
and we know they're starting with some false premises.
But, we also know their reasoning isn't correct.
And so, what we can do is we can do, like you said,
we can divide our job into two parts.
Part one is we talk about their reasoning.
>> Yes, correct.
>> And we try to
show them that their reasoning goes wrong.
Part two is when we ask, "Okay.
But now, your premises?
There's a problem here.
One of your premises isn't true."
And so, we can look at the truth of
the premises in one operation,
we can look at the validity of the reasoning in another.
And then, when those two go together,
you have a complete analysis.
>> Great. Alright, let's look at another argument.
>> Okay.
So, this is another deductive argument.
What makes it an argument is the word "Therefore'".
What makes it deductive is the word "Necessarily".
So, this is an argument because we
have premises offered for a conclusion.
This is deductive because
the word "Necessarily" indicates
that the claim is that if the premises are true,
the conclusion must be true.
>> That's right.
>> So it's a deductive argument
and this argument is not valid.
But most students before they've studied Logic,
look at it and it looks correct.
They look at it and it seems correct.
But if you analyze it and think about it,
it's actually not good reasoning.
It's not valid reasoning.
So, do you want to explain why or should I?
>> Well, since you're our guest,
I think you should explain because they're
going to hear plenty from me in
the course and the rest of the courses.
>> Okay. I have to do the work. So suppose if
Malia goes swimming then Jose goes swimming.
And I'll interpret that to mean,
every time Malia swims, Jose swims.
Does that premise alone now,
just that premise alone tell
us that every time Jose swims, Malia swims?
>> No.
>> It does not. Does it?
>> It does not.
>> It tells us every time she swims, he swims.
>> Correct.
>> But does that premise leave open
the possibility that he swims alone sometimes?
>> Yes.
>> So it does. So, just because when she swims,
he swims, it does not logically
follow that when she does not swim,
he does not swim.
He might swim every day
and she might swim every other day.
In which case, if she swims,
he's swimming with her.
If she swims every day at 9:00 am and he does,
but on the days when she doesn't swim,
he might swim anyway.
>> Yes.
>> Now, the second premise simply
adds that Malia will not swim today.
So, given just the two premises,
the conclusion isn't proven.
>> Right.
>> We are not guaranteed that Jose will not swim.
Maybe he will anyway -.
>> Yes.
>> Without her. So, this looks valid.
It looks correct, on the surface.
It's an example of a fallacy that can
mislead people if they haven't studied logic.
>> Right. Now, I want the students to take a look at this.
You might pause the video and study this.
And how would you change the premises and
the conclusion so that it does seem as if,
the conclusion wouldn't necessarily follow the premises?
>> That's a good exercise.
>> So, you may not have the skills just yet,
if you haven't gone through the course
material yet, to do that.
But this is something that you may want to revisit later.
Try this as an exercise.
Look at this invalid form and see if you
can change it into
a valid form and you'll see a valid form just a moment.
>> And the change is very small.
>> Correct. It's a very minor change,
but see if you can do it.
And then, once you can get to that point,
you'll start to see the difference between
valid and invalid in terms of the structure.
Let's go to the next argument.
>> Okay.
>> Now, this looks very similar.
It looks like almost the same argument.
>> Yeah.
>> But some things changed.
>> Flip back to.
>> Yeah.
>> So, look at the difference.
They do look very similar.
So, this is an argument
that many students when they first look at it,
think it looks invalid,
but it actually turns out to be valid.
>> And there's complicated reasons
for why in terms of logic,
which we'll talk about later, but let's
talk through the surface reasoning here.
>> Alright. Well, I mean, most people,
they look at it and they say, "That looks fine."
I mean, they say that something's
fishy with this argument.
It doesn't look right. They think it's invalid.
But when you think about it,
the first premise says,
If Malia goes swimming then Jose goes swimming.
So, every time she swims, he swims.
No exceptions.
That's what it says.
He's not going to swim today.
The second premise adds,
"Jose's not going to swim today".
Well then, if that's all the information we know,
that's all we need to know,
to know that Malia will not swim today.
Because if she did swim today,
well, let me back up.
>> Sure.
>> If she swims, he swims automatically.
Knowing that he's not going to swim today,
she's not going to swim today,
because if she did swim today,
he would swim today,
and he's not swimming,
so she's not swimming.
That's how I'd like to think of it.
>> Sure. Yeah.
>> Yeah. Knowing the premises alone,
we can be assured the conclusion is true.
Because if she did swim, he would.
He's not, then she's not.
So, it's valid although it's misleading.
>> It does. It can be very confusing
when you look at this and you can say, "Well,
that seems like it's going the wrong way.
It's doing the wrong thing." But when you look at it,
it's actually a valid argument.
>> Yeah.
>> It's not Sound as Paul tried
to explain earlier or we don't know if it's Sound.
>> We don't know if it's Sound,
might be, But it's clearly valid.
>> But we can clearly say that it's valid.
>> In virtue of an abstract structure and in logic,
you'll learn that we represent that structure,
if P then Q, not Q,
so not P. So, in logic,
we take an argument that has
a content and we translate it into
an abstract structure using symbols.
And then, we study the symbols
and there are ways of actually
showing in almost a mathematical way
that any argument that follows
this pattern will be valid.
>> That's right. So, what that means is you can plug
any value into P and Q and it would still be valid.
You can even put nonsense.
You could say if foo then bar.
Not foo, therefore, not bar.
Sorry, not bar, therefore, not foo.
Yeah, that would still
be valid even though the terms are nonsense.
They don't refer to anything, they don't mean anything.
It's still a valid form and if that bothers you,
work your way through the lessons and you'll hopefully
see the value of doing that, right?
It doesn't matter what terms you put in for validity
but when you get to Soundness then obviously,
you have to be working with real content.
>> Yes. And what shows us the problem is
when we look at it at the level of
form rather than context.
>> Yes.
>> Then we see the problem.
>> That's right. Here's another one.
>> In this one,
I chose as an example of an argument that
many people don't think is valid and yet it is again,
that it's often students think is not
valid and yet it is clearly valid.
>> This is a valid argument.
>> So, we have to think it through.
A common response to this argument is, okay.
If it's raining the roof is wet.
It's raining and they will say,
"But the roof might not be wet and so it's not valid."
In other words, they say,
the premises don't prove the conclusion with certainty.
And then, I often will say, "Why?
What's the problem here?"
And they'll say, "Well,
if it's raining the roof is wet."
I'll grant that and it's raining.
Yes, I'll grant that but then they say,
here's the house, they say,
"What if there's a big tarp over the roof?
To prevent the roof from getting wet."
They say, "What if that's the case,
then the roof won't be wet?"
And so then, they conclude from
this idea that that's an invalid argument.
And so, this is again,
it's an example that I'm using to
show where logic can improve our reasoning.
If you think about it,
if someone had a tarp over
the roof that kept the roof dry,
then what would that mean?
>> This premise is not true.
>> It would mean that the first premise is not true.
Now, to call this valid is simply to say that
if the premises are true,
if they're true, then the conclusion must be true.
So, it's all based on "If", "Then".
If the premises are true,
there is no tarp over the roof.
>> That's correct because
the first premise is telling us,
if it's raining, it must be the case that the roof is wet.
It's not possible for not to be wet.
>> Yeah.
>> Right? That's what that first premise is telling us.
So that's why when we assert that it's actually raining,
we know the roof has to be wet with
certainty because that's what our first premise tells us.
Now, if there's a tarp, then we would
never make that first claim.
We would never claim if it's raining the roof is wet,
because there might be a tarp right?.
But we're looking mainly at the structure, right?
The structure is the
>> Yeah. The structure makes it valid, not the content.
The rain, the roof.
>> That's right.
For the same reason that we saw in the last argument.
Alright. Now, I want to spend just a couple,
I think we have two more slides left.
I want to spend a little bit of
time on Inductive Arguments.
And the reason for this is a lot of students I've found
in the last two quarters that I've
taught in this online course,
a lot of students seem to struggle
with this format of argument.
So, it's a really good format
because it does help you actually
practice the process of
induction and thinking about
strength and all the rest of it.
But I've noticed that
students really struggle with thinking through this.
So first of all, quickly explain the difference
between Inductive and Deductive Arguments.
What are we talking about here?
>> Okay. So again, logicians distinguish
between Deductive Arguments,
which attempt to show their
conclusion must be true with certainty.
And Inductive Arguments, which aim a little lower,
they only try to show that the conclusion
is probable but not certain.
Probability is a concept from everyday life.
When Paul and I leave the studio,
I'll head to my car,
and my car is probably going to be where I parked it.
But, of course, I'm not certain it will be there.
It's all probability.
I think it's a very high probability.
>> Yeah, sure.
>> So, most things in life
revolve around probability estimates.
But an inductive argument attempts
to show that its conclusion is probable
>> And that probability is a range, right?
It can be a low probability or high probability.
>> Yeah. For the sake of our discussion,
we can say point five and above,
but less than one.
So, more than 50 percent
probable but less than 100 percent certain,
we'll call that probability.
So, now we have an argument,
it's an inductive argument because of
the presence of the word "probably."
We interviewed 10 randomly selected adults
from the kingdom of Ruritania,
an imaginary land, and we found that all 10 play soccer.
We conclude that probably
all adult Ruritanians play soccer.
Probably. And so, that argument has,
well, it depends on how big the kingdom is.
Let's say the kingdom of Ruritania only has 200 people.
It's a very small kingdom.
I would call that a pretty strong argument because
>> Is the sample size.
>> The premise is true, I think that
makes it somewhat probable,
that above 50 percent,
that all adults play soccer.
That's a fairly strong argument.
> So hopefully, again,
pause the video, look at
the argument if you're not seeing it.
And see if you can see why that probability is.
>> They're randomly selected.
>> Yes, randomly selected.
>> They all play Soccer.
>> And it's not specifically calling out men or women,
it's just sampling of all the adults, Right?.
>> So now, we can think about our response.
We'll make some elementary changes.
So, let's change the conclusion to,
"most adults, Ruritanians play soccer."
So, previously we said they all do,
probably they all do.
Now, let's say, probably most do.
>> Now, in my course when students see this,
they believe that the strength of the argument goes
down because we're using
the term "most," which is weaker.
"All" is a strong statement,
"most" is a weak statement,
so the conclusion that students tend to draw is,
Okay, that's a weaker argument,
the strength of the overall probability is
weaker because we're using a weaker term.
Instead of having that all inclusive term,
we have a less inclusive term.
>> Very good.
In fact the logical truth is exactly the reverse.
>> That's correct, the strength goes up.
>> So, it's a logical and optical illusion,
but when we say,
most probably play soccer,
that conclusion has a higher probability
than the one that says,
all probably play soccer.
And the reason for that is that,
when we draw an inductive conclusion, we're making claim.
And the more narrowly we draw the claim,
the more precise our claim,
the more chances there are that the claim is false.
And the more broadly we draw the claim,
the more chances we have that the claim comes true.
So, to go back here,
if even one adult Ruritanian doesn't play soccer,
just one, then our
conclusion that all adult Ruritanians
play soccer, is false.
>> That's right.
>> But now in this case,
if one adult Ruritanian doesn't play soccer,
it's still true that most of them do, so,
we have more chance that this is true,
based on the evidence then that this is true.
>> So, which is then there is more chance that
the second conclusion is true than this one,
and that more chance means that the argument is stronger.
>> Stronger.
>> It's a stronger inductive argument.
Even though it might seem intuitively opposite, right?
You see a weaker phrase,
a weaker term, and you automatically
think that the argument is
weaker but that's not how it works.
The weaker term actually makes the argument stronger.
And that's also true to at
least changing to at least half. Now, you're reducing.
>> I'm making a weaker claim,
and a more general claim.
And this is even more highly probable
that 51 percent play soccer.
That's even more probable on the evidence.
>> Yes.
>> Than the first prep. The worst conclusion.
>> Right. So, it's very important that
as you're working through these arguments,
that you think very carefully
about what the arguments are claiming,
and think of strength as the probability,
the degree of strength as the probability
that the conclusion is true.
>> Based on the premise.
>> Based on the truth of the premise.
>> Now,
>> What are you doing here?
>> Also now, we have the reverse orientation.
So, now we're going to add a premise to the argument.
The 10 adults, they wore beards,
no other Ruritanians wore beards.
So the 10 adults that we interviewed,
we're going to add that they all wore beards,
whereas no one else wore beards.
Does that make the argument stronger or weaker?
>> I don't think it has any impact on the argument.
The wearing of beards does not seem to have any impact.
>> Well, this is where people will
disagree because it is somewhat subjective here.
It seems to me that weakens the argument for this reason.
We've got us a sample of 10 randomly selected adults,
and we're making an inference about
all the adults in Ruritania.
So, this premise tells us that
those adults in our sample are
a little different from the rest of the population.
>> So it's only half the population
because they're all men, is that what you are telling?
>> Well, no. All we're assuming,
oh, because women don't have beards.
I didn't think of that. I didn't
>> So, walk through your reasoning.
>> Okay. So, my reasoning is that,
when we add this premise,
we're now adding the additional information that
our sample is different.
>> Because of this. This is very.
>> None of the other Ruritanians wore beards.
>> Got it. I see.
>> So, our sample is a little
bit oddball from the rest of the population,
which weakens our confidence that what
we learned about the sample is true
of the rest of the population.
>> Sure.
>> It just weakens the argument.
>> Yes. Now, if we didn't include this,
it may not have any impact because we've included
>> Yeah, yeah. That's right.
>> Because we've included that
>> Because they're the only ones wearing beards,
it suggests that there's something unique about them.
Which means that, our inference from them to the rest of
the population is a little more
suspect than it was before we knew this.
>> Got it.
>> Okay. So, that shows you
want your sample to be random,
and you want it to be diverse,
you want it to be representative.
If there is some reason to think the sample is
special or not random,
that casts doubt on your conclusion and makes it weaker.
>> Now, this is a great example and
our conversation is a good example of
how determining the strength
of inductive arguments can be tricky,
and we acknowledge this in the course.
The examples that we try to provide in
the course which largely come out of your textbook,
are a little bit simpler.
So, we're not going to do tricky things
like only men wear beards,
therefore we're only interviewing men.
We don't want you make those inductive leaps,
but you can see that trying to
find the strength can be tricky.
So, our recommendation is that you slow down,
you make sure that you go through that material multiple
times if you're not getting it, and just practice.
Walk through the exercises,
we have a number of samples in the coursework
that are exactly like this format.
We add information and then you get to practice to see
whether the conclusion is more or less probable.
But take your time and work through those examples.
If you rush through this stuff,
particularly as you're getting used to it and you're
learning, you're going to make mistakes.
So, the way that you avoid
those mistakes is to slow down.
>> Well, I would add, if I may.
>> Sure.
>> It's tricky and it's also a little bit subjective.
We don't have a precise measure
of probability in a case like this.
>> Correct.
>> We would need to know more.
Under certain very special conditions
that require a lot more information
and many more assumptions,
in inductive logic we can actually calculate
mathematically the exact probability of that conclusion.
But we can only use mathematics
and calculate probabilities with precision,
when there's a lot more information and
there's a lot of really specific information,
and we have to bring in a whole bunch of assumptions.
But, cases like this that are close to ordinary life,
the judgment of probability is a little bit subjective,
although probably 90 percent of all people would agree
that this argument makes it somewhat probable.
Most people would agree
within a range or a certain number of points.
But this shows that the study of logic can help
you see patterns of reasoning differently,
see strengths and weaknesses you didn't see before.
>> Totally agree, and I think this is very helpful.
So, we're giving you
this material at the beginning of your study,
so that as you go into
the topics on inductive and deductive reasoning,
you'll start to know what to look for.
And so, there are some terms here that
you may not be familiar with,
but you will become familiar
with them and you'll learn how to
use them and apply them as you work through the material.
So, Dr. Herrick, thank you so much
for spending some time with us.
>> Thank you, Paul.
>> Really good to have a conversation
and take advantage of your expertise.
Your book has been fantastic addition to the course,
and it's really great to have this conversation.
>> I appreciate your using it,
and thank you for your compliments too.
>> Thank you, and thanks for watching.
>> Thank you.
>> I hope you enjoy the next two modules.