So we've been looking at how to construct arguments,
we've looked at statements which are grammatical,
linguistic declarations of truth.
We've looked at propositions which are the actual thing that
is true or false, and statements symbolize those propositions.
And now we wanna look at truth value.
I said then in an earlier lesson,
that logic is all about getting to the truth of a statement or
a claim, and so we wanna look at what truth value
is now in constructing arguments, right?
So when we're talking about propositions,
which is the meaning behind any declarative statement we make,
those propositions can either be true or false in logic,
all right?
So when we're creating a logical argument,
any statement is going to be or
any proposition is either going to be true or false.
It can only be one or the other.
It can't be neither and it can't be both.
So what do you do when you don't know what the truth value is of
a statement in logic?
Well, you always assume it's true and
see whether the argument works, okay?
And then, obviously the goal is gonna be to try to find out
whether your premises actually are true.
All right, so Seattle is located in New York.
That is a statement of truth.
If you know where Seattle is located you're gonna know
that that's a false statement.
So, we would give it a value of false or F.
Ice is frozen.
Again, not parsing terms here, we're just gonna say ice is
frozen is a declarative statement that is
by definition true.
Ice is frozen water, okay?
Now again, suppose you didn't know whether
ice is frozen, right?
It doesn't really matter in logic cuz what you can do is
assume that it's true.
Plug it into your argument, and you'll see how this works later,
plug it into your argument and
see if the actual argument goes through, okay?
So this what we're talking about when we're talking about truth
value, whether the statement,
the declarative statement is true or false.
These are obviously simple statements as we learned in
an earlier lesson and each is gonna have a truth value, right?
Now, what I'd like to do is quickly summarize
what we've covered so far.
So we talked about statements as linguistic or grammatical.
They're written or spoken,
that's all we mean by linguistic.
Propositions are not linguistic, they are the things that
are being symbolized by the sentences.
Statements then are the symbol,
the propositions are the thing that actually have meaning.
And then propositions themselves can be true or false, statements
cannot be true or false because they're just the symbols for
the things that are, all right?
So the big takeaway is, remember that statements express
propositions and propositions are true or false.
So, those are basic tools for constructing logical arguments.
We're gonna write statements that symbolize the meaning as
best as we possibly can, and
then we're gonna assign them a truth value.
And as we get further into the lessons, you're gonna see how
all of this works together to create logical arguments.