Hopefully from the previous video,
you have now understood the value of incorporating history
in making better predictions in the future.
In this section, we will walk you through how that
history can be incorporated in the framework of recurrence.
So let's see, you have an input which goes into your model.
And this input could be as simple as the temperature
of the given day.
However, we have convinced ourselves here that adding some
extra input from the past can really
help us make better predictions.
For instance, the output of the solar panel from a previous day.
Or any of the previous day temperatures, etc, etc.
So that's why you see this vector on top of the notation,
which means the input can be a set of numbers.
And corresponding to that,
you would have a n dimensional array here.
Now I'm gonna point out to the dimensionality of the array over
and over as we go along, because it's key to understand the data
that you are gonna use to build these recurrent networks and
how the dimensionality of the data interplays with
the predictions you're gonna make.
Now what's the output gonna look like?
So the output in our case was the output of a single day for
that solar panel.
So it was a single output, say, w out, and
that corresponds to the wattage.
Now it could be that we are gonna be outputting the wattage
of the solar panel for multiple days in future so w out + 1..
Say, 5 days or so, you could do that.
So y can also be a vector,
in this case y is a c dimensional array.
Now, what is missing?
We have incorporated multiple features and
we figured out a way to predict multiple things into the future.
I hope you remember in the previous video,
we talked about history.
How can we incorporate history into our modeling framework?
Let's see.
So what we do in neural networks is that we have this thing
called the internal state, which is an m dimensional array.
This is also known as the history.
For every time we make a prediction why,
we also admit a history.
Obviously in the first round, the history is zero,
there is no history.
But subsequently you will have an ocean of history
that feeds into the next stage of your model.
So here we'll take the history from t is equal to 1.
Take the next set of inputs, and emit the corresponding outputs.
And additionally we'll also emit the updated history.
So note, the history keeps getting updated
as we go from one time point to the other, okay?
Now the inputs could be an array of numeric values from different
sensors like you have seen here.
It could be an image.
Pixels in an array, here we would map
the image pixels to a compact representation, say n values.
And you know the ways to do that given the convolution models
that you have built, and from words in text.
So you haven't quite done this yet, by the end of next module,
you would know how to do this.
But I'm just giving you a heads up and a teaser that we can
represent words as numeric vectors, and using something
called embedding that you'll learn in the next module.
So this is how our recurrent network is gonna look like.
You'll have an input, you'll have an output.
And you'll have an internal state or
history which will keep updating at every stage of recursion.
So that recursion at each stage implies there's a notion of
time, and you'll hear the time steps and
recursion being used interchangeably.
And here is a visual of what the input vector would look like.
These could be different entities all encoded
in a numeric array and you can have multiple outputs.
c dimension, this is gonna be n dimension, and
h is gonna be m dimensions.