A common work flow for using Jupyter Notebooks for
coding is to use Edit, Run and Save.
Some really common operations we're gonna use in our Jupyter notebooks
are edit, run, and save.
So to edit a cell, and I'm talking about a code cell here,
you can see this is a markdown cell.
Remember up here, and a code cell, if I highlight, is there.
To edit, all I have to do is highlight in there, and
you see my blinking cursor.
So I already had x = 2, let's go ahead and add to that.
I'm gonna say that y is equal to x + 5,
and then I will look at how to run this.
And so if I run this cell, there's a couple ways I can do that.
First let's go to the menu and see Cell > Run Cells.
And that has just run the cell.
And what it does is put the value 2 in memory for
x, and the value of 2 + 5, because that's x + 5 in the for y in memory.
And we don't see anything, so let's run it again so
we can see something.
So I'm just gonna put y there, and
all that's gonna do is say echo the value of y to the screen below here.
So let's go ahead and run that again, but
I'm not gonna hit Cell > Run Cells this time.
What I'm gonna do is just click into the cell, the code cell, and
hit the Ctrl button, Ctrl+Enter.
And then we see that I have the value of 7 there.
I can edit again by highlighting it in there, and
I can add more to the equation.
So I'm gonna add 3 more to the value of y.
So I'm gonna expect 10 to come out.
And I can hit Ctrl+Enter again to run it, or I can hit Shift+Enter.
What Shift+Enter will do is move to the next cell, and
if there's no cell below it will create a new cell.
So we see that the cell was run because the value changed from
7 to 10, and then I have a new cell.
And all new cells always default to a code cell, and
our notebooks are still Python 3.
Now to save my work,
there is a Save button right there that will save that.
It says Save and have a checkpoint so that next time,
when I open this notebook, it will still have
the edited text that I put in right there and the new cell.
So we learned how to edit just by typing within the box.
All you need is the focus there to run using the menu, or
we can use Ctrl+Enter, or we can use Shift+Enter, which
we'll probably use the most because it will move us to the next cell.
And then we can start working on the next cell and
keep running them in order.
And then to save we can push the Save button.