Do you know what an elif statement is?
Elif in Python is an else if statement and
it allows us to test for multiple conditions.
Elif in this example will allow us to check for four different cases.
Whether the weather is sunny, rainy, snowy, or
if we put in another entry that we don't understand.
Let's look at the example in the very
simplest case with just the if statement.
If the weather, this input that we got right here,
is equal to sunny, then we're gonna print wear a t-shirt.
If we wanna check for rainy, else would not work for us,
cuz it could also be snowy entered, or some invalid input.
So we use the elif statement.
This first elif checks if it's raining.
The second elif checks if its snowy.
Then finally we get to our else statement,
where its none of the three cases we checked for and
we just say we don't understand the message.
Let's run the code.
I'll try sunny first.
It says to wear a t-shirt, so we went through this path.
Let's run it again.
It's snowy, we went through this path.
This was not true, if statement.
The elif statement was not true, rainy.
The elif statement for snowy was true, and we printed our message.
So we can control the flow through many paths using elif.
The other example's very similar.
It just uses the elif statement to see if we're guessing a number
properly.
So we put in a secret number, and then we tell
the individuals to guess 1, 2, or 3.
If its not a digit, then we say, they need to put in a digit.
So this case checks if it's a letter or some other non digit.
If they guess 1, we tell them they guessed too low.
If they guess the secret number, we tell them that it's right.
If they guess 3, we tell them too high.
And otherwise, we say it's not a valid guess in the range.
Let's run the code.
If we enter a typed, Three in letters,
we should get the message that it's a invalid guess.
And we do.
And that means this statement here executed.
It checked if it's a digit, and because if is.digit was false,
then that executes it matched.
.isdigit()== False;.
Yes, then run this code.
Let's try another test.
Here we gotta to run the third elif statement.
Using the elif statement, we can check for multiple conditions.