Lets talk about integers.
Integers are a data type.
They are a type of information that is numbers and
we use these just like we do in normal mathematics.
So the counting numbers, positive or negative, zero included,
and let's contrast those to the strings we just learned about.
Strings are characters which include the A through Z characters and
digits zero through nine.
But the difference is a string is just a representation of a picture
of that number.
It's the representation of the shape of the number three,
versus the actual integer number three as something that we can do
mathematical operations with.
And so the difference between the two is quotes and not quotes.
So we see that the string
number representation here, this would be the same as -123, but
it's a negative character and then the 1 and 2 and 3 digit characters.
And so we can echo that to the screen and we see the -123.
And a integer has no quotes, and we can echo that as well.
And notice that the quotes do not echo in the integer right there.
In the print statement, we have a little bit different
behavior for strings and for number integers.
So let's go ahead and print that and we see it prints without the quotes
because that's the behavior of the print statement.
The print statement is also able to decipher numbers,
and in this case an integer number, 2017.
And it can echo it as well.
It can also echo a negative number.
The difference here is the quotes.
This makes it a string.
So I can add a letter in with that because it's a string.
If I put a letter into here, it no longer makes sense to Python and
it causes an error.
Integers are the counting numbers, both positive and negative,
and include zero.
If you put them in quotes, that'd be a string.
So we don't use strings with our integers.
Just put on the number, no quotes.