We're going to walk through the requirements for
the Required Coding Activity for
Module 3 and we're going to do a cheese ordering program.
And so there are the required keywords if,
elif, else, print, input, and float.
If any of these are excluded from your program solution,
you will not get credit.
So make sure that we are covering each of these items.
Let's look at edX page.
And we see there are requirements, right here,
that we just talked about and we also show
some of the requirements and code running.
We also have that on
our Jupiter notebook and in this case I'm going
to run some sample code that I've
pre-loaded and just show you how the program should work.
So, we have the requirements to enter
in some values that are above 100,
below .25,
and somewhere in between and so that
we can give different types of messages.
So you put in your order value.
So here I'll put in something bigger than 100.
So we'll just go a little bit bigger 101 and you can
also do that with decimal places,
because we are going to convert
this string input into a float and then it gives us
a message that "101.9 is
more than is currently
available in stock" so they can fulfill that order,
we'll run it again and then we'll
put in something below .25 so I go
.01 and we see
that is .01 is below the minimum order amount.
So let's order something in between .25 and 100.
So I'll just say,
55.3 and then it gives us a cost and so that cost has
to convert that amount into
a float value and multiply it by a fixed count per unit.
So we're going to have to by 55.5 times our requirement.
So in our module let's make sure that we're
testing our input within if, and elif,
and then else statement
that we are printing some results,
that we're gathering the input that we used,
and we're converting that input into float values.