Here are the references we have used for this course.
We start with a great book by Goodfellow, Bengio, and
Courville titled Deep Learning.
Standford CS231N course also has a wealth of information
that has been very relevant in preparing this course.
And finally, the tutorials on neural networks by Geoff Hinton.
I'd like to acknowledge, Chris Basoglu and
Cha Zhang, Microsoft for their support and
improvement throughout the development of the course.
I'd like to extend my thanks to Surya Pathak,
Professor at the University of Washington for
helping out the pedagogical approach to teaching and
changes to the content to reflect those.
Jonathan Sanito, who is Content Developer at Microsoft for
his assistance with graphics, and later on in the course
you'll see especially in the convolutional networks.
Nikos Karampatziakis, my colleague, for help with
the tutorials associated with text classification.