Before we go too far down the lane, understanding what
convolution operations specifically does, let's take
a moment and understand the image data format.
We have been dealing with the MNIST data, in the previous
modules we have been flattening it out into array
And here I hopefully have convinced you that,
that is not really ideal because we lose the correlations
between the pixels that exist here, when we flatten it out.
So we would be treating from hereon, this image
As a matrix with one channel.
Because this is a grayscale image,
it has only shades of gray and, With parameters,
weight and height, in this case, these are both 28.
So, they are 28 x 28 pixels, and each pixel has 1 integer value.
Another set of images that you'll often encounter, and
this is more likely to be the case,
where you'll see natural scene images.
And here, your matrix dimensions are gonna be the same weight and
height, so this is the weight, and that's gonna be the height.
But, there are three channels.
The red, green, and blue channels.
How do these channels come together to form this nice
beautiful image of the fire truck.
Let's take a look at it.
Here is a moniker for the three channels.
Here you can see, this is the red channel, and
the red parts of the fire truck are now bright,
very bright here, okay?
And green parts, which are predominantly
the grass area, is very bright here.
And here, the sky, which is largely blue,
is very, very bright.
So these three channels come together to form this image.