We saw how starts with can help us, find
a search of the first character and a
string. But sometimes we want to search
in the middle of the string and so the
Boolean_in_keyword is very useful in
this regard. So below, I have a string
called menu and I just entered a number
of things that might be in a menu in that
string and then I just can print and to  the result here of to see, If pizza is
in menu and so, what this will do with
the in keyword is, Pizza it's gonna be the
search string and they're gonna run
it through this entire list to see if it
gets a match and So the way that our
work is at each letter, it will just
check if there is a P and then when it's
there it will see the second letter and soon and that doesn't work then we'll
move on to it gets to the start again
with another piece.
So we can run this and it says False, but
I see that right here there's pizza in
the menu but it wasn't found so the
problem in this case is that, I need to
have pizza be lowercase and so, I can run
it with a lowercase p and then I see
that it's true and so this is really a
great part of Python here is this the
way that it works to just use this word
and it seems very natural to look for
something like this because, I named my
variable menu and my search term was
quite straightforward, I could just run
this really easily and I couldn't use a
variable in this case as well. So let's
look over here at another version of
pizza. In this case, I put lower and lower
and this is really a best practice that
you should look for in any  of you search, if you don't care
about case sensitivity, then it's a good
practice to make lower used in both
sides and we can see how that makes
search run a lot faster .
The "in" keyword is very effective in searching within
strings and so the best practice we use
with that is when case sensitivity is
not important , we can use a dot lower
and use that string method to make both the
search string and search target a
lowercase . And that will lead to really
effective searching.