Now that you are familiar with the LSTM blocks, how they can
improve with longer sequences and dealing with a larger amount
of history, let's come back to our time-series problem,
which has a much simpler representation of the data.
We want to take away the complexities associated with
data for the learning purposes using this time series data.
We'll come back and bring back more different type of data
representation later on in the course, in the model six.
But for now, we're going to focus working with the time
series data, which is relatively simple numeric inputs.
But understand how we can incorporate recurrence and
LSTMs in building a network and
predicting the output of our solar panel based
on the recorded inputs over a span of time.
So our input here is 14 data points represented in this
pink window here, and these are our sequences.
And our output is gonna be a future value, one output value
of what the solar panel output would be at a future time.
Now that you have a notion of time, and
the corresponding inputs in the form of a sequence,
we can generate a recurrent time series with the LSTM units and
then only project the last one to the dense.
Because we have one value to project and we take all the,
in this case, in this illustration,
ten time stamps to predict a future value of Y.
It's very easy to do in the toolkit that we are gonna use
for the tutorial.
You can see that the first layer here defines the recurrence or
the repetition of the LSTM units.
Then, we pick the last cell and pass it through the dense layer.
And in this case the output is going to be just one value.
And Z is going to be the output of the solar panel that we
are going to be using as a part of the exercises and
tutorial in this module.