Let's begin with understanding what
the MNIST database provides with regards to handwritten digits.
So on the left here, you see these
are the images of different digits written by hand.
You can see that the same image,
like the digit 3 is written in three different ways here.
And we want to detect
what those digits are in a machine readable format, so
this is an application called optical character recognition.
And this application was originally used to
recognize handwritten post codes.
So the data set has handwritten digits of 0 to 9,
and there are 60,000 training images.
Needless to say, there are multiple repetitions of
the same digits like you see here, 3, 3, 3.
There might be however many 0s and so on and so
forth for all the represented digits from 0 to 9.
And then, there are 10,000 test images, and
each image here represents an array of 28 by 28 numbers and
in image terminology they are called 28 by 28 pixels.