You've heard me talk about activation functions many times,
and every time I bring up sigmoid, so you might be
wondering like beyond sigmoid is there something?
What are these activation functions?
When do I use it?
What are the traits, tradeoffs maybe associated with these
different activation functions?
So, let's take a moment and
learn the concept of activation function.
In the next several slides you will see
the different options you may have when building your models.
So, activation functions, also known as non-linearities,
take a single number and map it to a different value.
So for example, your friend and
much too familiar sigmoid activation function maps values,
any numerical value, to a 0,1 range.
Some of the popular activation functions yes, sigmoid again,
then we have hyperbolic tangent also known as tan.h value,
this is a very popular one it's called the rectified liner unit
and then there's an advancement over value leaky value and
parametric value.
There are few others that I'll allude to you as we go along
in the video.
Let's take a closer look at the different activation
functions you have.
Let's start with our friend sigmoid and
understand what its characteristics are.
So we have Our function is very simple
And the output of this function becomes
the input to my activation function.
So say we have a value of 0 here at the output,
which is the input to the activation function,
the value of the sigmoid would be 0.5.
Now if we have a different value,
say something like 3 or
something, so it'll go here and
it would give me a value of, say 0.9.
Historically, this activation function has been very,
very popular and because it mimics the brain-firing pattern.
Recently, it's popularity is dipping, and
largely due to saturation and vanishing gradients.
What does this mean?
Let's take a deeper look.
So the either end of the tails here,
like once your input crosses a certain value, say 4 or
5, the output of your activation function is gonna
be close to 1, As shown here.
And say you had initial model wx + b where for
certain choice of weights and biases, your value was say 8.
So the output would be, say very close to 1.
And now with the different set of weights which got updated
during training, you would get say a value of 5.
And the output of the activation unit would be close to 1.
So which means that,
if you were gonna take the difference between these two,
the change between the updates of w to w' between that
iterations of your training set, you would see that the slope or
the change is gonna be very, very negligible.
Which means that for that particular
update during the training step, the net new learning for
the network is very, very low if anything else.
Besides this phenomenon of vanishing gradient or
saturation, the output
of sigmoid function is non-zero centered.
What it means is that for
input value of 0, the output is 0.5.
It's more of an inconvenience and less severe than saturation.