Working with strings and string variables
we've accomplished a lot.
Still we're a little bit limited, so let's look at adding input
and so we're going to use the input statement.
So, right here, I have the input statement, as the second line
and I'm going to assign small int a new variable to the input.
And before that we have a message, which is telling the user,
enter a small int or integer.
So, let's see how that works.
So now, it asks me to enter small int.
And so now, I can put a small integer in there,
and I think 3 is pretty small. So I enter that in
and now I've populated this variable
small int with 3, and so, I'm going to go ahead
and print the output
and if I go to the cell below,
I also have access to the small int variable
because in a Jupyter notebook,
any variable, any object, that is created
in a cell, once it's created, it's available to all the cells.
So now I can go ahead and run this cell and it says
the small int is 3. So that works.
So, let's go ahead and try it again.
I'll put in a different number 5, and so now
I've re-populated the small integer variable
and I see 5 below there.
So, working with input, we can populate variables with strings
and use them in our programs.