Congratulations, you have made through module one and two, and
now into module three.
This is gonna be our first deep learned model.
One of the simplest ones, but yet very, very powerful.
And it's used in a large number of contexts.
So even though it's very, very simple it's very foundational,
you'll use it for many of your applications and
find it very useful.
More importantly, the concepts that you will learn here
are going to be applicable in subsequent modules.
So pay attention to the different concepts that
are gonna get introduced in this session.
Additionally, I would like you to start building the notion of
the layers of neurons in the brain.
Keep that in mind in order to have higher level of cognition
that, us, human being do, we need to bring that into
the machines and deep learned models enable us to do that.
With that, let me walk you through what to expect
in this module.
In this module, we'll have the same application which is
the optical character recognition using MNIST data.
We want to use the same dataset so that you get
really comfortable in using MNIST data with the task of
recognizing the digits and focus on building different modules,
which comprises of different deep learning models.
In this module, we'll do a recap of logistic regression,
and then we'll go into multi-layer perception.
The concepts that you'll learn here are gonna be activation
functions.
These are key to make the deep learning models work well.
And then, finally, we'll walk you through the train, test and
predict workflow using multi-layer perceptrons.