So machine learning is a branch of computer science
where you build models from data.
So these models are mathematical models and
can learn from and make predictions on data.
There are different subfields of machine learning such as
supervised learning, unsupervised learning, and
semi-supervised learning.
So in supervised learning,
you have data points and a label associated with it.
For instance, the red dots and the blue dots.
The red and blue are the labels, the dots represent data points.
You learn a model, a mathematical model,
in such a way that when you have unforeseen data, such as these
dots that don't have any red or blue tags associated with it,
you'll be able to map these data points to either red or blue.
That's supervised learning.
In unsupervised learning, you start with data that don't
have any labels associated with it, in this case.
There's no color label associated such as red and blue.
What you learn here are inherent structures within the data.
So for instance, you will see a red cluster here and
you can see that there might be another cluster here.
Semi-supervised learning is somewhere in between,
where you have some of the data points that are labeled.
You use these labeled information and make predictions
on these unlabeled datasets.
The key thing is that the number of labels that you see in these
datasets are far fewer than the unlabeled data points.
In this course, we are gonna be focusing on supervised learning.
In supervised learning, one starts with data and
a corresponding label.
So the input would have data and
corresponding label.
This data, label pair is used to learn a model and
is referred to as the training data.
This dataset is referred to as the training data.
A classical example is classification of emails.
Here, the data is the content in the email and
the label is whether it's spam or not spam.
You learn a model using this data, such that at
a later time when a new email comes into the mailbox,
you can run the contents of the email through the model and
label it as either spam or not spam.
In this case, the presence or absence of certain
keywords in the email are referred to as features.
So the words in the email can be referred to as features.
These features help build effective classifier with
a reasonably good performance, such as
the majority of the non-spam emails get classified correctly.
This particular task in machine learning is refered to
as classification task.
Another example where machine learning can also be effective
is in prediction of house prices in a neighborhood.
So here these are the individual houses in a neighborhood and
the corresponding prices.
So the data here are the different features associated
with the house, be it the number of bedrooms, the square footage
of the house, the neighborhood, where it is located, etc.
And the label here is a price, what is the price of the house?
Now as you can imagine this price may be influenced by
several different aspects not only just with the house
features, but
also other features around the house in the neighborhood.
So you'll combine these features and build another model such
that, when you have unlabeled data point, in this case a house
for which we want to estimate the price of it based on all
the features that are available for that particular house.
Say what is the size of the house?
What is the number of bedrooms, the neighborhood that it is in?
And you come up with the real number.
Note, this is not a category, this is a real number.
So this task is also known as regression.
We assume in this course that you are familiar with some of
the basics associated with classification and regression.
We'll do a brief recap of machine learning basics, but
there's an underlying assumption that you are familiar with some
of these terminologies.