Many of you who are not familiar with text processing,
may be wondering how we can convert the text tokens, be
it in the input or in the output labels, into a numerical format.
In a previous module you have seen that when we had the MNIST
data, we had taken the digit 3 and represented it
in a one-hot encoding which means that the fourth element
with the index starting from 0 would represent digit 3.
We had ten digits, 0 to 9, so the length of the encoding or
the one-hot encoded vector was ten.
Similarly, in case of each word,
the One-hot representation is a vector with 943 elements.
So for the token boston, which is the 266th element in
the vocabulary of the words that make up the ATIS data set, we
will make that 266th element to be 1, rest of it all will be 0.
And the length of this vector would have 943 elements.
Similarly, for
each label we would have a one-hot representation.
And it would be a vector with 129 elements.