Casting input is a common task.
Input always is a string and so it's important sometimes that we are able
to change it into a float, or an integer, or back to a string.
>> Casting is when we force a type upon an object.
We're gonna look at three different types of casts.
Int, forces something to become an integer,
str is a string cast, and then float.
Let's look at this example where we have two weights.
One is a string, and the second one is an integer.
When we add numbers, they can be floats and integers but not strings.
In this case, if we run the code, we get the familiar TypeError that we
saw earlier when we did string concatenation and
try to add an integer to a string.
It's the same error, here, we'll need weight1, the string,
to become an integer.
Cast it by typing the keyword int in front of the object and
place it in parenthesis.
Now, 60 changes from digits that are string to numbers.
And we add and get our result 230.
In this example, we're going to calculate
the graduation age of a student.
First, let's get some input.
Age of the new student.
Input is always a string.
So I'm going to take that string input and
add it to 3.75 to calculate the graduation age.
But I'll need the age of the new student to be a float value,
so in order to cast that to a float in parenthesis, I'm putting
the string that I want to cast and preceeding it by the keyword float.
This allows me to add the input together.
Now the numbers will add up.
So we see this grad_age is the 16.55, it's a float.
For my graduation message, I want to string concatenation and
add this age upon graduation will be plus the 16.55.
In order to avoid the type error,
I'm going to change grad_age into a string.
In order to print it, I'll just create a print statement.
We can avoid the type error by casting to int, string, and float.