Now let's start taking steps that would
eventually help us build our first deep hero network.
We start again with our MNIST image,
that is flattened into an array and
is provided as an input into the model.
Now notice, in our logistic regression we directly
mapped these inputs into the corresponding
10 digits, 0,1 all the way till 9.
Here in deep networks, we will
put intermediate layers which enable us to
introduce interactions between the input features.
In other words, what is the interaction between this pixel
and another pixels somewhere else or
this one against a boundary pixel?
So what we do is, we do not directly map
the inputs into the corresponding 10 digits.
What we would do is we will initially
create another layer and in
this case we put say 400 nodes and this is a hyperparameter.
In other case in your model you will get to choose
how many nodes you want to build in the intermediate layers.
This is our first intermediate layer.
If you do not understand what intermediate means, just wait
for the subsequent videos it'll become clear, but the first
thing in this building a deep network is to generate different
features that are built on top of the inputs that you give.
So in this case, think about you take the input
pixels here in your image and map it into 400 features.
Now the output here would have a parameterization
of 400 activation units.
Here you know that these are called activations, and
different kinds of activation functions can be built in.
One of them you are already familiar is called sigmoid.
We'll do a quick review of other options shortly.
In this case since we are using 400 as my
intermediate feature representation,
we will instead of 10 we'll have 400,
Vectors each of length 784 in my W matrix.
What would be the dimension of b?
Take a moment, think about it.
If you followed the material in the course so far you would
agree with that this would have the same dimension as the number
of division unit outputs that we choose to have,
In this case it's 400.
We call this the dense layer.
It is represented in subsequent, Videos and
the lecture set as this unit.
Here we have the input number of units that come into
the model as shown here.
And the output units which is 400 in this case.
And the activation function we used in the past was sigmoid,
but there're other options that I'll talk about in the next
video.
We'll also represent sometimes the dense layer in a more
compact way using this notation.