OK! To create our model let's first
review the big picture of what we're doing here?
We're taking each record of
784 pixels that's our input to our model.
The active part of our model is going to be
consisting of ten nodes each of them
fully connected to the inputs
each with their own set of weights.
So we'll end up with ten by 784 weights.
And then we'll have a bias for each of the nodes also over here
ten bias values. And the output of that
will then be used in a softmax
and cross-entropy for a loss function
we'll explain that when we get to it.
Let's scroll down here a little also up.
We have this notion of an input variable
that we'll be using and that's where we
can bind data to the model
after we built the model. So the first thing we do
is we say we're going to create an input variable
whose shape is input dim which is 784.
And we're going to call that input
that's so we're actually put in our features.
And next input variable is
shaped or sized as num output classes which is 10.
And that's going to be associated with our labeled data
and then here's our model creation
it's pretty small because this is a really simple model.
Essentially, what we're doing is this
kind of boilerplate code here
where we say let's use default options
and we're going to initialize our weights
with this function called glorot uniform,
a uniform distribution of values, random values.
And then we're going to create layer called dense
which means it's a fully called connected layer.
The number of nodes in it is going to be
the number of output classes which is 10.
And then our activation function is none
that's because we're going to take care
of the softmax kind of activation inside the loss function.
And we're passing it our input
features here. And then we return
the network that we've created, the model we've created is r.
Here, we're going to actually call that,
create model passing in our input binding
for features called input
and we'll do a divide of 255 right up front
which will see normalize our input data because our
input data is grayscale pixel values
between 0 and 255. So by dividing by 255
we'll end up with normalized values between 0 and 1
which help our training work better.
So next step is creating our loss function
this will be used to guide our optimizer
as we adjust weights and we're going to use cross entropy with softmax
which we've discussed in the lecture
it's-- it's a good loss function
when you're doing with categorical data.
The input to this is Z which is
the output of our model and label
which is our binding for our label data.
And for our metric for evaluation
we're going to use something called classification error
which is just returns a 1 if the
labels are the same and a 0 if they're different.
And we'll store that again we pass in Z and label
and we'll store that in label error.
So now we have our loss in our error function
we can actually create a trainer.
So let's work backwards here
this is the trainer we want to create
CNTK dot trainer is the function to do it.
We pass in Z we pass in our loss
and our label error which we already have.
And then we pass in-- in the list
because you could have multiple learners.
We pass in our learner and that's created just above here
for that we're using CNTK dot sgd
or Stochastic gradient descent.
We give it our model Z and then dot parameters
that returns the parameters of our model
because it's going to have to adjust those
And it's going to use a learning rate schedule
that we've defined right up above here.
And we created that with the standard
learning rate schedule from CNTK.
We gave it a learning rate of 0.2
and then we said the style of learning
is going to be minibatch. Alright!
We've got a model, we've got a trainer.
Here, we're going to define a couple of helper functions.
This first one is called moving average
and this is going to be used to
plot some data that we gather during training.
Essentially, what it does is this
little messy kind of expression here
is doing a sliding window average of five.
So every five elements it
creates a new average that slides over,
and creates a new average on that.
So that's just going to smooth out our data for plotting
then over here we have print training progress
we pass in a trainer minibatch number,
the frequency with which we want to print
and verbose flag set to one.
And we say, hey if the minibatch mod frequency is zero
that means, it's time to print. We will--
take off the trainer object
a field called previous minibatch loss average
and previous minibatch evaluation average,
will store those in two variables here.
And if it's verbose to set which is by default,
we will print out this information minibatch
the number, the loss value, the four digits
and the error value with a two decimal digits.
And then there are those parameters
and then finally we'll return
all three of those values.
Now we're ready to run the trainer,
so, the first thing we're going to do is set some parameters the minibatch size
is going to be 64. The number of samples per sweep that's 1 walk
through all of our data is going to be 60,000.
The number of sweeps to train with is 10.
So that means we're going to go through all of our data ten times for a
a total of 600,000 samples and the number of minibatches to train,
we can calculate as a number of samples per sweep
times the number of sweeps divided by the minibatch size. Ok,
so now we've come to the actual minibatch loop, so we create our reader
start and reader train, we give it our training file name
we say True because we're training we give it the input dimension 784.
The number of output classes 10, now we create an input map,
this maps between our input variables is called label and input
and the data in the stream that will be passing called the streams.label
and streams.features, this is coming from our reader.
We're going to set our progress output to 500 that mean every 500 minibatches
will print the progress, we're going to set up a variable called plotdata,
that's going to be holding it says batchsize,
but it's really the minibatch number and then the loss value
and the error value for that minibatch
and then here's the--- the actual actual loop right here.
So we set up a range to go from 0 to the number of minibatches to train minus 1,
we call on the reader object, reader train, we call next minibatch,
we give it a minibatch size and our input map.
So that will actually get us the next, since minibatch size is 64
it'll give us our next 64 records of training data and labels.
And then we call trainer.train minibatch passing the data.
So this is where our weights actually get adjusted based on
the current predictions that it makes with the current set of weights.
Then we'll call print training progress
and we'll pass it the needed parameters
and that will print every 500 minibatches
and it will also return these three values
that we're going to need to store in plotdata.
So that we can plot them later
and here you can see from the previous run,
we have minibatch going from 0, 500,000 all the way to 9000.
The law starts at 2.2 and goes lower and higher in some places
and then back downed again seems to be converging
and like wise the error starts pretty high at 80%
goes down, goes up to 12, down to 4 up to 9 back down to 3.
So it looks like it's converging to be great, if we could see this plotted
so that's the next section of code. This uses Matplotlib
to do the actual plotting, first though we're going to take our plotdata
and we're going to run it through our moving average helper function
that'll smooth out our data. So we start with plotdata loss,
we store it in something called plotdata average loss
and we take our plotdata error and we stored in plotdata avgerror.
Now we import matplotlib.pyplot as we're going to call that plt
and this will create a figure that we can plot into
this is a one of two plots and we'll start with the first one
and we're going to plot the plotdata batchsize,
which is the minibatch number against,
so this will be in the X and the Y would be the average loss
and that's what we see here. And so this is loss and we can see it, converging down.
We also only set the X label the Y label on the title.
Let me show it then we go to the second plot and we do a similar thing
or here we're back we're plotting the Minibatch number against,
the average error and we set the labels and we set the title and we show it
and so we can see that here.
All right so it looks like both our loss and our error are converging
and let's see how that model now holds up against test data.
So to evaluate it on test data we're going to have another
Minibatch loop like we did before it's going to look very similar only
things we used to say train are now going to say test.
So we have a reader underscore test the creating reader
from test underscore file and this time this parameter for training is false
and these two are the same. We're going to have a test input map
that associates our input variable label
with our streams.labels and our input variable called input
with our stream stream.features.
We set some parameters this time we're using
any batchsize of 512 and that's okay.
Because this is just test data we can actually run through as many
records at a time as we want as long as they can all fit into memory, 512
should be no problem at all. The number of samples is going to be 10,000
that's how many samples we have in our test set
and the number of Minibatches to test
we're going to say is the number of samples divided by the Minibatch size
and so far we're going to accumulate an average test result first a total
and then we'll divide it by the number of entries.
So it's going to start at 0 here's our for loop again,
this time we're controlling it by the number of Minibatches to test.
Here's our reader test getting the next batch of data,
next Minibatch passing the size and the map.
Then once we have the data we can call trainer.test this time last time
it was just want to point this out this
difference last time it was trainer.train Minibatch.
So that actually does weight adjustment this call trainer.test Minibatch
only does evaluation and it gives us back an error, evaluation error
that's our metric and we're going to just accumulate that and test result
and then at the end here.
We'll say divide it by the number of Minibatches to test,
that gives us an average we multiply it by a hundred to get a percentage
and we print that out average test error and it with two decimal places
and that's shown here 7.4 percent.
So that's not bad for logistic regression really the simplest
kind of model you can imagine,where we're in
single-digit error ballpark that's pretty good.
So now we're going to do a little prediction
this kind of simulates a deployment environment.
We want to take some data and predict just what the values are. So,
we're going to extend our models with one node,
we're going to actually put a soft max output now on z,
which is the previous last node of the model and it's
now going to give us a new output called out.