deep learning let's take a step and
understand what you can expect later in the course.
So we'll cover the deep learning basics in six modules.
In Module 1, you'll have a flavor of the different concepts
getting introduced in the form of different application where
deep learning is being used, and a high level modeling work
flow that we will be using throughout the later modules.
In Module 2, we will cover logistic regression with
an application in optical character recognition.
We will use the optical character recognition
application in module three and four as well.
In Module 3, we will use Multi-layer perceptron
base models for the task.
And in Module 4, we will use convolution network for
the same optical character recognition task.
In Module 5, we will introduce time-series
modeling using deep networks.
In Module 6, we will going to text modeling,
we'll specifically use long-short term memory
recurrence units for text classification.
The course will have 5 hands-on lab, and 5 quizzes.
These are required for certification.
We will use Python Jupyter notebooks for your hands-on lab.
Upon completion, the students will be having enough knowledge
to build their own deep learning, end to end workflow,
combining the concepts, and the algorithms,
that will be introduced in this course.
You'll be specifically be able to build these models and
combining the end to end workflow that will get
introduced, you should be able solve practical problems in AI
with large amount of data involved.
So who are the audience for this course?
We aim this course for Data Scientists and
Engineers who are getting introduced to deep learning,
who have some background in machine learning,
and want to try out what deep learning can or
cannot provide in their application domains.
So this course is more of a practical hands on approach.
We also target technical managers who are interested and
involved in development in AI based technologies.
The third audience are the machine learning scientists
who are looking to build deep models, and
the focus is gonna be on agility and ease.
This is very, very important because as you can imagine,
with large amount of data involved, it is
important that you are able to scale your models efficiently.
So let's talk a little bit about the instructors.
I am Sayan Pathak I'm a principal machine learning
scientist at Microsoft.
I've built several machine learning applications in my past
in healthcare domain funded by NIH.
I have published in neuroinformatics during my
tenure at the Allen Institute for Brain Science.
I have a diverse range of interests starting from
computer vision, healthcare, informatics
applied to social networks as well as online advertisements.
I have academic affiliations with the University of
Washington and at the Indian Institute of Technology.
I'm also an instructor at the Ai school at Microsoft.
And my co-instructor, Roland Fernandez,
he's a researcher at Microsoft.
He's also an Ai school instructor.
His interested are in reinforcement learning,
autonomous multitask learning, and Computer Human Interaction.
He has worked in areas of Natural User Interface, activity
based computing, and a large number of programmer tools,
operating systems, and databases.
Let's talk a little bit about programming environment.
We'll be using Microsoft Cognitive Toolkit (CNTK).
We will be using different environments for
this course that meets your need.
Any one of them is appropriate for
you to successfully complete this course.
The first one that is recommended is that you install
the toolkit locally on a machine that you have.
You can also use pre-installed notebooks in
the Azure Notebooks.
Note these are gonna be CPU only.
So for those of you who want to leverage the powers
of deep learning, we do recommend using GPU.
But for the course, you can use CPU machines only and
successfully complete the course.
Additionally, we do provide access to Azure Data Science
Virtual Machines, where you can sign up with a trial account.
More details will be provided to you in the form of course notes,
samples, and in the supplementary material that
comes along with this course.