String comparisons will resolve to true and false and therefore we can
use them in an if statement to control the flow of our code.
In our first example, we have a string called msg and
that contains Save the notebook.
And we want to check if that message string
is equal to this string literal Save the notebook.
If that resolves to true,
we're going to print the message as expected.
If it resolves to false, then we'll go to our else statement.
Print the message was not as expected.
Let's run the code.
So the message was not as expected, so
that means this must have resolved to not true or false.
And we see that's because the capitalization of the two strings
is different.
A more elegant way to write this code would be to test
our message against a prediction.
So both of these can use variables.
And we're going to ignore the case.
So here we're going to put both sides of this comparison to lower.
Regardless of what are entered for
the message and the prediction the case will be ignored.
And so the same as before,
we will print message as expected if the statement resolves to true.
And if doesn't, we'll go to our else.
If this is not true, and do message not as expected.
And this time, the message is as expected because we ignore the case.
In this example, we're gonna input a name, a last name and
check if it is alphabetically less than or equal to c.
If you remember from our ASCII discussions before that capital C
ends up being smaller than lowercase c, it's just the way ASCII works.
So in order to do the check,
we have to make sure the name is entered to lower.
To do this check cuz otherwise a Z uppercase
would be less than c and we would not be able to do this check.
So we're gonna check against those and
if this resolves to true we're gonna print Welcome to the a, b, c line.
If the statement resolves to false,
then we're going to tell the people sorry, this is only for a, b, c.
So let's go ahead and run that code.
And they ask us to enter the last name,
we'll put in Babic and it says Welcome the the a, b, c line.
We could run that again.
And we could put in Derosa.
We've seen using string comparisons with our if statements,
we can control the flow of our programs.