This is introduction of Python, unit one.
I am your instructor, Eric Camplin, a Content Developer at Microsoft.
I&#39;m excited to present this course designed for
those who are new to programming, to ease into learning Python.
The student will cover basic programming concepts and
do exercises that can be completed online using the Jupyter Notebook
development environment hosted on Microsoft Azure.
Unit one focuses on Python Language Basics.
Student would be able to develop and run programs in Jupyter Notebooks
that utilize concepts as data types, variables, user input,
they&#39;ll build functions, use operators and conditional statements.
We&#39;ll build while loops and increment variables, and
we&#39;ll delve into troubleshooting errors.
All key foundations to further learning in computer science.
Each concept introduced has a video, and examples, and
student coding task, and followed by additional programming practice.
With the modules, there are multiple sections that have knowledge checks
and end of module coding assignments.
At the end, there is a final coding project.
For those pursuing the verified certificate,
70% credit is required for passing.
Welcome to the course.