Welcome to module four.
This is probably one of the key modules where you learn
a lot about Convolution models,
there are also called Convolution Neural Nets, CNN's, Conv Nets.
Convolution Neural Nets have been
bringing a huge amount of
revolutionary changes in the domain of deep learning.
It's been used for image tagging,
face recognition, different kinds of object tracking will look into
these different applications. However, in this module you will learn
variety of basic concepts that will enable you to build
very advanced models with practical applications.
So in this module we will continue to use
the optical character recognition application as our
foundational problem set to get your hands dirty with building
Convolution models, we will use the MNIST data set.
You will do a brief recap of
what Multi-Layer Perceptrons are
from our previous module? Then we'll talk about
Convolution Networks and then you will
see some popular deep Convolutional Networks.
The concepts that will be
introduced in this model are Convolution
and pooling and then finally you'll see
we'll walk you through the entire
Workflow of train-test-predict as usual
where we piece together this concepts
and the network architecture to solve
the problem of OCR using MNIST data.
And hopefully at the end of the module
you'll see that we are able to get
better performance out of it, after all that's one of the motivation to build
this modules which enable you to recognize
data with spatial coherence or spatial information to do it with very
high accuracy almost are better than even human abilities
to perform these tasks.