We've talked about the data types for string and integer,
now let's add in float and the type function so
that we can programmably understand what type we're working with.
So, the decimal in this literal number here,
3.14, makes this a float data type.
It's a floating decimal point and so any number with a decimal,
it could have just all decimal is a float
versus the counting numbers are gonna be the integer types.
Now, what I did here is I put those into the type function and
it returns the type of the variable.
Right here, it is just echoing it to the screen and
we could also just print that as well.
When we print it, we get a little bit more information and
it says it's a class int right there and if I add a decimal,
then I get class float.
The type also will work for strings as we show below here.
And it can also display in a variable, so
if we assign student- "Colette" in here.
We should throw it's a string, but we can change that to the number
again, student number, in quotes, it's gonna be a string.
Without quotes, It's a integer.
Even if it's the name it's gonna be a string again.
So we learned about a new type,
the float, which is floating decimal point.
And that's any number with a decimal within it, a fractional number.
We also learned that the type function can help us return the type
of a different variable or a literal type.