Even though the problem said that we're gonna deal
with MNIST images are grey scale, most of the applications
that you will deal with in the case of convolution networks
I'm gonna be probably natural scene images.
In other words they would have the red, green and
blue channels.
So let's understand what convolution operation means
when you have natural scene images in the context of RGB
color channels.
So you start with this image,
which has three components, the red, green, blue channels
represented by the number of channels information here 3.
And the width and the height of course.
In the past video, we have seen that we have used
a single 3 by 3 matrix or a patch or a kernel or a filter.
These are all synonymous and did a doc product
with the underline pixels which are treated as features.
And then of course we cannot forget our bias.
In this case, we're gonna do
the same thing except my W matrix
is gonna be having 3 channels.
One matrix for each channel.
And then the width and the height.
Our filter is gonna match the corresponding image batch
underneath it, and
it's gonna have the dimensions that I just explained.
And we'll call this the filter_width and
the filter_height.
Now the next thing we need to do, with respect to convolution,
is to slide this filter to its adjacent position where
we're gonna repeat the dot product operation.
So let's do that, and
you can see that the patch has moved to a different location.
And the other thing if you paid attention,
the patch did not move to this particular location.
Let me choose a different color pen.
So it didn't move to this location but
instead move to this location.
So this movement is called a stride.
And in this case, since we skipped one value here and
landed up two steps away from this location,
our value of our stride is 2.
This is a parameter in your network
that you can play around with as you build your models.
Now, the usual thing we'll do and
it can be seen in this animation here where you will see that
the patch gets moved around and that filters get composed.
In this case we have our blue filter,
we have the orange filter then we have the green filter and
then we have the purple filter.
You can have any number of filters over there and
that's a parameter for
you to define as a part of the network you will see that.
And then finally, The output of
your function here gets routed to an activation function.
Okay and this is gonna be represented by our moniker for
convolution, which has the filter height and width,
the number of filters, the strides, padding.
This is something I haven't introduced to you yet..
But it will become clearer in the next few videos where I'm
gonna talk about padding.
In activation you have seen a lot of these and
you can play around those activation functions as
you build your network.
How's the cord gonna look like?
The cord is gonna be very similar to this cartoon that we
have here which has the filter shape and
you have the number of filters which is 8.
The strides which you already know in this case we had strides
of 2 and these are two values because,
One is along the width, and the other is along the height.
So let's say this is for the width dimension, this is for
the height dimension, this is again for
the width dimension this is for the height dimension, okay?
In this case we have set the pad to be true, but
it can be false as well and what it means, we will shortly learn.
And then the activation unit that we have used here is called
relu okay.
Now what does this operation mean numerically?
You can follow this rendition of this convolution operation
done in three dimensions with the three channels,
red, green and blue.
The values of this filter is multiplied with
the corresponding value in the input data,
and then you sum all of them up.
When you sum all of them up and
then add your bias, you should get a corresponding value here.
You may take a moment and review the content of this page to
convince yourself that indeed these values are getting
computed the way that I have just described.