Hello and welcome to the part 2 of the lab for module two,
Logistic Regression with the MNIST data.
I'm going to open that now from
CNTK 103 B. Okay, in the first notebook we
just reviewed, we downloaded the data
and formatted it to a local file in the CTF format
and this notebook we're actually going to read that data
and use it to train our model.
So, let's start with-- let's review
the two types of Logistic Regression.
So there's a Binary Logistic Regression and a Multi-class form.
In the binary form, we have a
single node which takes the weighted sum of the inputs
and runs that through a sigmoid function to squash the value
between 0 and 1 and treat city value
output from 0 to 0.5 is the first class prediction and anything above
0.5 as the second class prediction.
In Multi-class Linear Regression which is the form we're going to use
in this notebook, we have a
separate node for each output class that we're trying to predict.
And each node has its own set of weights
and takes the weighted sum of all the inputs
and we run collectively, we run all three
outputs into softmax such that we get out probabilities for each
selected class and the output with the largest probability is
the prediction for the associated class.
Alright, our code starts out with again bringing in some libraries
that we're going to be using.
Matplotlib, numpy, sys, os and then here we see CNTK
being brought in and we're going to refer to that as a capital C.
And again, we're using our matplotlib inline to say any plots we create
we want them to be in the output pane, not as a floating window
just to make them easier to manage.
Here's a little section and we can
ignore but what this does is, it switches the CNTK system to use
either CPU or GPU depending on
environmental setting. But this is just used for internal CNTK testing.
Alright! In our initialization section
we call np random seed,
setting that to zero, this will ensure that
because there's some fixed number here
that we're going to get a consistent set of
sequence of random numbers.
And we have two variables here,
one is input dimension and number of classes. Input dimension is going to be
our 28 by 28 pixels for each record
which is 784 values and we're trying to
predict the digits 0 through 9,
so that's a total of 10 classes that we going to output or predictions for
and here's a reminder of what our data is looking like
in the CTF format, each record will start with a vertical bar and labels
and then be followed by the 1-hot encoding of that label
and followed by features
and then the 784 values from 0 to 255
that make up the pixel Grayscale values.
So this code block here is going to
create our reader object that will use in our training
and it's job is just going to be to read the
next set of data 32 or 64
however many-- many batch, whatever many batch size we use,
it'll read that many records.
So we sort of start here label stream, we can see
we're defining in a stream, it's field, is going to be called labels
that's the vertical bar and the word it's going to look for
and it's going to have a ten values
from num label classes.
The features-- feature stream will be defined using the
features keyword with vertical bar in front of it.
And it's going to have 784 values.
Then we put both these streams together
and this CTFDeserializer.
And finally we wrap all that with a MinibatchSource.
And the MinibatchSource is our actual
reader object that we can use in our training loop.
And then some parameters here
as taking the Deserializer
and then it's saying that, using the name parameter randomize
and it sets it to true if it's training or false if it's not training
because we don't have any
reason to randomize if we're doing that just evaluation.
Randomization is really used
for during training. And our max sweeps
is going to be infinity, we're not going to
put a maximum on here, if we're doing training,
otherwise if we're doing
testing we're just going to say go through the data and maximum of one time.
Down here, we're trying to figure out
where our data is? We're trying to figure out the data directory.
Essentially, we first look in the examples directory
and if we don't find it there, we look in the--
the data in this directory and when we're
finally done, essentially we actually
loop through these two sets of directories and we try them both.
And when we find the file,
we say data found is true when we break out.
So if we didn't-- if we didn't find the file
we say ok, raise an exception.
Otherwise we print where the data is and you can see the last time I run this
it says Data directory is data MNIST.
So now we've got our directory, we've got our reader to use.
Now, we're going to create our model.