Python uses the backslash as and escape sequence.
This allows Python to display quotes,
backslashes, tabs and new lines.
>> Our formating character examples all start with a backslash.
Let's start with the Newline Carriage Return formatting
character, \n.
This creates a new line in the middle of a string.
So, Hello World is followed by a new line and I am formatting print.
The Tab character, \t Creates a tab in the middle of a string.
Here, I have two tabs to help create a header.
Let's run the code.
We see the two tabs, and
then another between the name and the age.
To display quotes, I use a backslash, and
then either a double or single quote.
In this example, I want to show a display of quotations around
the text without putting the single quotes around them.
Where this becomes more useful is when I have a long string, and
I want both a single quote, or an apostrophe, and double quotes.
The backslash quote, in either single or double,
will display the characters.
Here is my apostrophe or single quote and the double quotes.
Sometimes, we just want to show the backslash character.
Use two backslashes.
Double backslash results in a backslash being printed.
We can use formatting characters that all start with the escape
sequence backslash to help format our output.