>> Let's walk through Module 2: Required Coding.
And, we're going to build a fish store function.
And it has some requirements for the code as do
all of the required coding activities.
So we're going to have to use
specific keywords in order to get credit.
So in this one it says you're going to have
to define and use
a function that has parameters in return.
So that means we're going to use the def keyword,
that our function is going to take two arguments:
It's going to be the fish name and the fish price.
And that, it's going to return a string
that has a message about the fish name and price.
We're going to use input to get strings
that we'll use as the arguments for our function,
and we're going to print
the return value that comes back from the function.
So we'll have to do all of those things.
Let's look at the edX course page
and you can see they have those requirements there.
And that, we will have to go and
submit that when we're done with our submission tab.
And we should do our coding in the Jupyter Notebook,
or if you want to use another solution you can do that.
We're going to do at the Jupyter Notebook,
and I have preloaded a solution,
and I'm just going to run that code here,
and it ask me to enter a fish name.
I'm just going to say tuna.
And then, the price of the fish, I'll say 11.97.
And, we see I get this nicely formatted message back.
Fish type is tuna that costs
11.97 and that's what your code should do as well.
Now, let's go back to edX and paste in our code solution,
and we know that from our module 1 that
this is of primitive solution for submitting code,
and that it will not show you the user,
the indentation of the code and that's okay.
So it just kind of looks like that.
And then, when we submit it,
we can see, you get two attempts, I've used one.
So if you've missed it you've probably
missed one of the requirements,
such as a keyword like return.
So, go ahead, and work on that solution,
and submit your code.
But, don't forget that we're going
to have to use each of the keywords,
def return, input, and print.