Now that you are quite familiar with the convolution operations,
let's put together a pure convolutional network.
We start with our MNIST image of digit 3.
This is a greyscale image, so we specify the input
with the dimensions of 1, 28, 28.
And we're gonna use a filter size of 5 by 5,
and we're gonna learn eight filters.
We'll keep a stride of two.
We'll set padding equals true.
And we'll use activation equals value.
At the end of this operation, when the image is processed,
you will get eight 14 times 14 images.
And then that becomes the input to the next layer.
And in this layer, we're gonna keep the filter sizes the same,
but the number of output filters we're gonna increase to 16.
We'll keep rest of the parameters the same.
This is the trend that you will notice, that,
in convolutional network, that as you go build the layers,
you tend to squeeze the image, the image sizes themselves will
start getting smaller but the number of filters
that you'll learn keeps getting deeper and deeper.
So this is a key aspect of convolutional network
where you keep squeezing the image.
In this case we have only a 28 by 28 image,
so you can only do it so much.
But if you have a larger image, you can do a whole lot of things
by playing around with these parameters.
So the end of the second convolutional layer here,
we have seven by seven and 16 of these here.
So we would flatten that out at this stage into array, and
map these values into output layer of 10 vectors.
We need to get into this vector size of 10,
because ultimate goal for us in this case is to characterize
each of the images that are coming in as input
to the corresponding digits from zero to nine.
And, indeed once you ride this network and
you run to a set of images you'll, for the m nest data,
you will see that the output comes like a vector
of 10 numbers with the largest number
being the value corresponding to the digit three.
And this is what the code for
that particular network would look like.
Here you can see it's a one-to-one
correspondence between this diagram.
Here the convolutional layer, this is the second convolutional
layer, and then there's this dense layer.
And with this type of network, when you run it through, you
will see the error rate for the MNIST data goes down to 1.56.
Significant jump from LR.
If you've done the homework, the assignment for the feed
forward network, you will see that this is an improvement
over the multi-layer perceptron based network that we had.
And we'll see how we can further reduce this error rate in
the next several videos.