A simple function can be created with the def keyword,
function name, followed by parentheses and a semicolon.
So here we have two simple functions.
And this first one, say hi, we're going to use
the keyword def which tells Python we are defining a function and
then we have the function name.
It just has to start with a letter.
We use the standard of lower case and underscore separating words,
that is not required, just our standard, and then parenthesis and
a colon, and that is your function definition right there.
And then you put code underneath, and
we'll put many different types of pieces of code in our functions, but
right now we're just gonna stick with some simple print statements.
The indentation is four spaces.
I can then end the function by ending the indentation.
So anywhere where either the cell just ends, or
if I put something else in the cell.
And in this case, I'm going to call the function.
And because this indentation has ended,
the function only goes to this point here.
So to call the function, I use the function name and parenthesis, and
then I'm just gonna use this keyboard shortcut Shift+Enter.
And it runs the function which prints these two lines, Hello there,
goodbye.
And then I can look at another example where I can call a function
from another cell.
And in this one, three_3_function, it just prints the number 33.
I use a def statement to tell Python it's a function.
I put a function name, and then I put my parenthesis and colon.
And I add my function definition again, four spaces and
then function code.
I need to run the function before I can call it though.
Why do I run it?
Because that puts it in memory.
Now, this cell can call the function because it's in memory,
and I just use the function name followed by parenthesis,
and it prints 33.
So those are simple functions,
we'll write many more functions in this course.