One-hot representation can be considered as a kind of
embedding which means you take an entity, in this case,
it was the word token and you map it into a new micro vector.
So, one-hot encoding is a Numerical representation of text
in this case, as shown here.
You have an array of 943 elements
represented as the input.
Word Embedding is another kind of encoding where specific
techniques are developed to map words or
phrases to vector of real numbers.
Note in One-hot encoding, we had either zero or one.
All the elements for zero except the one word that was present
and it's corresponding index in the vocabulary.
In the case of Word Embeddings, we will map words or
phrases to vector of real numbers.
This maps the one-hot encoded vector to a lower
dimensional space.
Instead of having a whole vector with a single number
representing that particular word,
it would compress the encoding.
So instead of having 943 elements,
it would have a much shorter representation and
those representation would have real numbers.
One example of word embedding is linear embedding.
What we do here is, with some transformation that takes
this one-hot encoding, we can compress it and represent it in
let's say, 150 element vector instead of the 943 ones.
And this could be a variable that you can tune for
however long or short you may want.
What does it do?
We first take the vector and
multiply a matrix with this one-hot encoded vector.
The vector is of size 1 X 943 times 943 elements.
And the matrix has a size of the number of elements that you want
to compress it to, times the one-hot encoding vector length.
And this matrix can be learned as a part of your network.
You could initialize it with a random number and
you can then learn this compact representation
which would transfer your one-hot encoded input into
a more dense embedding.
Or, you can use some popular embedding techniques,
such as Glove, or Word2Vec.
These are more advanced techniques, that are widely
available for use and people have code available of
these locations where you can pre-generate these embeddings.
Depending on you vocabulary and use them into your network
either directly here, or you could initialize your We matrix,
with the embedding from Glove or Word2vec, and
then subsequently refine them as you train your network.