A variable is just a container.
It's a name storage location that holds an object.
You might have used variables in math and
you think of x equals five or other equations that have variables.
It's similar in Python.
With Python, we use variables so that we can re-use code and
we can assign different values to the variable.
So in Python, we use very simple names.
As we show here, for
a student_name that would be a good example of a variable.
It's descriptive, we use lower case and
we connect it with an underscore.
Variables can also be assigned strings
not just numbers like in math.
And if we run that cell, we don't get an echo but
what we've done is we've assigned this storage location,
which has a student name
with a string of the student's name, that's in quotes.
Then we can call back on that variable and
we see that it will echo below.
We can also print the literal string as we did in earlier assignments.
But through using a variable I can automate that.
And I can have a different student name going through this print
statement each time,
where other code can change the value of student name.
So, what would that look like?
Well we call that variable reassignment.
And we see the example below, the first time that print ran,
it had the student name of Joana.
Then, we reassigned the variable with Colette, and
when we print it again, Colette prints.
>> If we go back up to the top, we can rerun the cell and
reinitialize the variable.
And then we can check the further value now in student_name.
Now it is Joana and we can see that if I re-run this previous cell and
then rerun the student_name again, it will change back to Colette.
>> So, a variable is a name storage address that we can use in our code,
just the same we do as a literal string or number or
other objects we'll see later.
A variable means change as well, so remember we can
reuse that variable within our code and make it more efficient.