So I've been alluding to you that parameter
in the convolution operation where we say padding is equal to
true or false.
We get to understand here what that means.
So let's start here.
You can see the image of the red, green, and
the blue image that we have.
And around it we have laid out an array of zeroes.
Whenever we do that, that operation is called padding.
So this set of zeroes that we have added here and here,
we call it zero padding.
And what implication does it have?
What operation does it entail?
So here is an example of what happens when you do no padding.
As you'll notice,
the kernel here cannot step outside the bounds of the image.
Can only have effectively four locations that
can be mapped for that corresponding kernel and
this image shape with no padding.
Now if you add the zeroes, you have a little bit of better
control of shape of what the output might look like.
In other words, in the previous case without padding,
with no padding, our image became a lot smaller
when we did the convolution operation.
But in this case with padding,
where we have added a set of zeroes around the boundaries,
you can see that the input image here in orange
is the same as the output image in green in terms of the size.
Obviously the values are gonna be different based on whatever
the convolution operation from that particular kernel with
respect to the image pixels lying underneath it means.
So this is with Stride 1, which means that for every image, You
would just slide to the adjacent value here, by one step.
Now you can do that with more number of steps, and
that will be the Stride parameter.
So in this case, the stride is set to 2, and when you do that
with a larger stride, your image automatically shrinks.
Please take a moment to look through these
animations to convince yourself that that indeed is the case.
The number of positions where this kernel can move
with a stride of 2 would be these smaller number of
pixels in the output compared to the input image here.
Now, with these padding operations,
our convolution operation for
the entire image is animated here.
Again, there's a good reference of the Stanford GitHub site
that you can refer.
But do take a moment to convince yourself that indeed these
animations are reflective of your understanding of
the convolution operations that we have described in this video.