Congratulation, so
you have built your first text classification model end to end.
Let's see what other models may be possible
with these technologies.
This is one of the very popular ones.
You may have heard about machine translation.
This is where you'll give the input a certain sequence.
The model would process that sequence and
emit an output, say, in a completely different language.
And that is how you would represent it in terms
of network.
Each of these words,
hello how are you in English is pass to a recurrent unit.
It composes history as you all know.
This can be also called vectors.
And once you do that, in response to a beginning of
sentence token it would emit, hello.
You can then take that hello and fill it as input
to the next recurrent unit, then it would say, wie.
You take the wie into the next recurrent unit and
it would emit geht as your with the end of sequence.
Sounds a bit magical, try out one of the tutorials that we
have on our GitHub site, really, really works.
And you should be able to have a lot of fun.
Note that the number of input here and the number of output,
they are not the same, so there are some tricks you have to
apply to get that machinery going.
We haven't discussed that in this particular set of lectures.
In the more advanced lectures in the future,
we will walk you through those details.
Another area of sequence generation you may have run into
is automatic caption generation.
So here is person flying a kite.
You can encode this image into a numeric code vector.
You know that, you are seeing convolution networks, so
you should be able to generate encoding of this
image into a set of numerical entities.
Which you then feed into a recurring block which would then
generate text like a person on the beach flying a kite.
So this would be an instance of having one input and
generates many outputs.
Here are some of the examples that you can find,
where, this is a person flying a kite on the beach.
This is a train.
And the fact that this is a black-and-white photo can be
recognized by these types of models.
There's a person skiing down the slope.
And there's a bunch of giraffes standing next to each other.
All of these are texts that are generated
from these images by a model like this.
Details can be found out in this particular
literature that you will have at the bottom of the screen.
And this concludes our Module 6.