The string format methods are really
useful for display alterations,
so putting something all upper or all lower title case.
Another very useful way to
use the string methods is on user input.
Here we have two things going on,
first of all we're going to use a
variable favorite color, fav_color and input as we've seen before and then so
we're going to apply this lower command
to actually alter what's going to go
into the variable. And so this is a choice this is formatting on input.
So right at the input statement you just
use the dot lower to invoke the method
because input will return a string and so you can use the dot lower on a string,
so this really is a string right here.
After input returns whatever we put in
there, so let's try running that. So I can
put in my favorite color and I can use
green and then it prints the favorite
color green and notice my capitalization
is removed because I use the lower and I
could use that with upper as well. And I could use blue and we see that I have
all caps in that answer.
So when do I want to use the
String_Formatting and input  I can use it when
I'm doing the input or I can just get my input stored in a variable and then
I can just alter the variable string in
print statements and in other places and where that could be an advantage is
perhaps later I wanted to see what the
format that was originally used in the string.
So let's go ahead and run that.
so I can go yellow and I can see there
that it prints it all caps, although if I just print it without any
string modification and then I see that
yellow is displayed right there. So
working with the strings input and then
deciding whether I want to modify it
right when I come in and the string is
entered and that's a case where I never
want to change it later or I can modify
it in place in a print statement or in other uses.