Let's walk through the final required coding activity.
As with the other activities,
there are required keywords that if these are
not included in your submitted code,
your answer will be marked incorrect.
So we are going to build our adding report.
We're going to build functions so we
have the def keyword.
We're going to loop until we
get a proper type of input using while statement.
We'll do some comparisons with if, elif,
and then we'll also use the else keyword.
We will be casting some inputs to int to be
integers and we will be testing if input is an integer.
Also we'll be printing output to
the user and of course we'll need to get user input.
Let's take a look at the edX page for
this activity and we have
our familiar assignment requirements
that we just went over.
Please review those.
And there are additional requirements in
telling you how the program works.
Let's take a quick look at
this diagram where it shows we start in this area
here and jump into a while true loop,
so that's what this here means and that you continue
off to the input
and find out if it's a quit or if it's a digit.
If it's a digit,
we're going to add it to
a total and if it's
not we're going to see if they said quit,
otherwise we're going to say this
is invalid input and it takes us
all the way back to the true,
so we keep this is that loop right there where we
keep input going until we
get a valid input which is either something
that starts with q or a digit.
So in our Jupiter notebook I've preloaded this with
function code and so
we can run it and see what it looks like.
And it asks us to choose
a report type A or T and we could put
in an invalid response
and then we see that it continues to ask us,
so I'll put A for all items and
then it asks us to either enter a integer or to quit.
So I'll enter an integer and another and then I'll quit.
And then we can see our report which
shows there's two items added with a total of six.
We can run the report again with just the total mode.
And again we can enter a number of integers.
We can do this time some invalid input
or invalid because it's
not all digits, it's not integers.
And so we can only put in
integer values and then we can quit and get our total.
So when we enter T it just gives
us our total when we enter A it's
going to show all of the values that we
entered and it will give us a total as well.
So be sure we use all of these keywords.
Good luck on your final project.