Boolean String Methods such as isalpha or
isnum can be used to control our flow of code in an if statement.
We can use any Boolean String Method in an if statement because they all
resolve to either true or false.
In our example, we get input for the title of a book and
save that in favorite_book.
Then we use the istitle method
to see if it's a title case where every word is capitalized.
If that result is true, then we'll print nice capitalization.
If not true, we'll go to the else statement and
we'll give them a tip to capitalize each word.
We run the code and I'll put in a title.
It says nice capitalization because I put in each word capitalized.
If I'll just put in something without capitalization,
it gives me the tip.
So this resolve do not true.
In the next example, we want to enter a positive integer and
then we run the check, is it a digit.
This is a good check because if we're looking for a number input,
then if someone puts in something that's not a number or
the positive digit we want,
Then we see that a text string is not an integer.
We can also run more than one if statement at a time.
After this first if statement runs,
I can run a second one to check if it's a alphabetical character.
And if it is, we can tell people that that's a word and
that we're looking for a number input.
So I can try again.
And that it says number is not a positive integer,
number is more like a word.
So we can use our Boolean string test to evaluate if statements and
control the flow of our code.