We have all the components to train
our Multi-layer Perceptron Network.
We are going to us the same train validate
test predict workflow that you have seen before.
The only difference here is the
model itself. In the previous module the
model was logistic regression.
Here it's a Multi-layer Perceptron model.
So let's see the Train workflow remains exactly the same
except we are going to replace
this part with the Multi-layer Perceptron model.
So I want to spend time
explaining the loss function how it
evolves over the iterations. The suffice to
say that during this stage we are
finding new sets of parameters which
yield lower and lower loss value.
Subsequently in the validation workflow
we select the final model based on a
different data set called the validation data set
such that the loss is the least
on the validation data set.
So let's start with the same database
the MNIST database. Here we are going to
use the training data set again. Pretty
much nothing changes here we sample a
mini batch of size 128 these are the
number of images that we are drawing from this
MNIST database and the corresponding
labels which are One-hot encoded. Now this
is where things are different right. The model here
is the Multi-layer Perceptron model that
we have seen during the lectures.
The first dense layer produces 400 outputs,
the second one has 200 outputs
and the final one emits an array of 10 numbers
representing the ten digits that
we are trying to classify. We are using
activation function relu here in the hidden layers.
Since we are going to use soft max
we do not use an activation function,
we just have it as a pass through in the final output layer.
So there are six sets of parameters, three weights and three biases
our loss function is cross_entropy_with_softmax
which takes the output of the model
and the labels from our training set.
Optionally we also use the
classification error() function to figure out
how well our classifier is doing
against the ground truth or the label
set and then using the trainer object
which takes the model, the loss, the error
and learner functions we train our model
like repeatedly calling Trainer.train_minibatch
with the data and the labels provided to the function as an input.
The learners can be any one of them such as sgd, adagrad et cetera that
we have introduced to you in the last lecture.
Following the selection of the
final model we want to test what its
performance is going to be on data set
that hasn't been used for training.
So using the final model, we sample data sets
from the test database and using
the final model we generate predictions
and calculate the error. Let's see how
the test workflow loads out here.
We do not want to sample from the training data set.
We sample from the test data set,
we sample the input data or the
features in this case what we call and the corresponding labels .
Note in this case the model is frozen
that means the weights and the bias
values are fixed, they are not changing.
We called Trainer.test_mini-batch
repeatedly and evaluate the average error that
this model would produce.