Now that you are familiar with the
pre-processing steps that we have used
to convert the solar.csv data, raw data
from the IoT panel. Let's figure out
how we feed it into our models, we have
already said that we are going to look into the
data for only 14 time points per day
and we use a value of 20,000 to normalize
the input into zero to one range then we call the
generate_solar_data to read the
data from this solar.csv file.
Here's a small utility that would allow
us to sample data sets from these
data X and Y values, the input and the
corresponding label values that have
been read from the input data in that
size of 14 times 10 which is 140 you can
play around with that value and the data
looks exactly like we have discussed in
the previous video where there are
different individual readings for the
time point at which we are recording
from the solar panel and the
corresponding output which is the power
generated for that particular day
aggregated over the entire day so in
this case you can see that these are
different time instances for any
given day and these numbers are the
same because the total amount of current
generated for that particular day is the
same, but if you go and change these
indexes to something else which I would
encourage you to do so you can figure
out that these numbers change and so
does these numbers as well but at the
end of the day the values of X and the
corresponding Y's are what is needed for
us at that point the notion of time the
specific date doesn't make any
difference, the network learns how to
predict this Y's given any instances of the X's which is on sequence with
length of 8 to 14.
Here is our LSTM network setup, note that
we do not specify the maximum length as
a part of our model and we do not need
to pad our variable length sequences so
the sequences can be of length from 8 to
14 and we do not have to pad zeros or
any other values to our sequences that
are less than 14 that toolkit
automatically takes care of that, in this case
we will have the LSTM cells hidden
dimension or the internal state that we
have referred to a certain values. You
can play around with it in this case
coincidentally it happened so that 14
seems to be a pretty decent number you
can try out different numbers for the
hidden dimensions of the LSTM cells.
This figure should be quite familiar to
you where the individual data points are
input to the LSTM cells this is part of
the recurrence units
and we just sample the output from the
last LSTM cell and then we add a little
bit of a drop out to prevent overfitting
and then project the output to a single
value which corresponds to the
predicted output of the solar panel
based on the input values that we have
here, the network code is a direct
translation of what the figure you have seen before,
we have a set of recurrences with each
of the cells being LSTM's and their
internal state being hidden dimensions of 14.
We sample the data or we pick up
the data rather from the last cell, pass it to a dropout
and then project our predicted
value of the solar panel output here.
Once we have the model then we are going
to train this is again much too familiar
to you except for the fact in this case
instead of just C.input_variable you have a C.sequence.input_variable, this is
important because we are dealing with
sequence data, we get our model here
and the corresponding labels are also a set
of layer set of scalars for this
particular set of input values yep!
We set a learning rate, a fixed learning
rate in this case and each create a schedule learning rate
schedule in many applications you may
want to explore with different learning
rates and different learning rate
schedules. You can try these things out
in this tutorial if you want to. Our loss
function in this case is different from
what we have been using for them this
data because that task was from
classification in this case it's a
regression, so we use a squared error
where we minimize the difference between
the predicted solar panel output and the
observed output of the solar panel
and the same is used for the error
function then we can instantiate our
trainer object. Once the trainer object
is instantiated then you can run through
the entire data set and you can
train the parameters of the model by
calling trainer.train_minibatch
by feeding the corresponding minibatch
features and the corresponding labels.
This notebook is going to take a while
to run and once it's done in this case
you can see that the loss in general
reduces quite a bit, here is the plot of
how the training progresses over the
number of different iterations. And you
can then start plotting the mean square
error for the training validation and test data
here and finally you can visualize the predictions.
Here you can see that the
blue is the raw observations and the
orange one is the predictions and in general they are pretty close.
Even with 200 iterations is what we had
started-off let me quickly check, if it
was you have trained this one for 200 iterations.
Let me quickly check that, yes it is
indeed 200 passes that we have used but
if you were to use a much larger amount
of training which is set to 2,000 then
you will see this curves becoming even
closer to the observed values.
With that you are ready
to do the assignments associated with this lab.