We've learned how to combine strings
inside a print statements, using string addition with plus sign.
So, let's look at another way to do some
formatting with print and we can combine using commas.
So I'm going to just create a string variable here,
and enter the Name: Collette, I need to run that cell so that
that variable name gets populated with the string
and then I can go over here
and this is the familiar print statement we used before, we used
a string and then we just add in a variable,
that is a string and then we add a another string.
And I can run that cell.
Now, I got my "Hello Collette!" but,
this-- printing with, formatting with
commas is a different way to do this
and so, what I can do is, put a
comma between the different strings. And so,
I've done here.
"Hello to" be Collette again, "who is from our city".
And I can run that string,
and you can see here that concatenates
all of the strings inside this print statement
in between the commas,
it just puts a space in between there and that's a default behavior.
So, it says "Hello to", add in a space
"Collette" added in a space whose from our city.
So we can print format with commas,
and concatenate strings very quickly
just by putting them next to each other,
using the comma for different string variables or literal strings.