Before we get into the modeling side of things,
let's understand what the data looks like.
As I mentioned in the current networks, modeling and
model capacity is important to better understand what it
takes to encapsulate the knowledge that comes from
combining inputs with the corresponding history.
It's also important to recognize what the data is and what
the format would look like and how to feed it into the model.
So let's take a closer look at the ATIS data.
This data comes from human computer queries from
Air Travel Information Services.
There are 943 unique words,
we'll also refer to that as the vocabulary.
So when I said show flight from Burbank to Seattle on a day,
each of those words would be word in this vocabulary.
So there are 943 of those.
And the corresponding labels such as the other from city
to city, add date, would be considered as labels.
There are 26 intent tags in the data set.
We will not be using that in this tutorial,
we'll just be using the first two as the input, and
this is the corresponding label for the output.
Now, let's take a look at what one of that sentence might
look like.
We always start with this tag called beginning of sentence.
And then the real query,
which is the please give me the flights from Boston to
Pittsburgh on Thursday of next week, end of sentence.
This token beginning of sentence is the 178th
word in the vocabulary, and that is lit up, so
we indicate it in this format.
This is the format in which the data will be represented for
the tutorials and the exercises that you're gonna do.
And this belongs to the 19th sequence,
that means this sentence that you have
is the 19th sentence from the ATIS data set that have used.
And corresponding to that word, there's a label.
You can see most of them are labeled as others.
Which means, I don't really care about it,
it is some other token.
And in each case, we have the corresponding index,
similar to the Word Index where that token is present.
So here, Boston becomes B-fromloc.city_name and
Pittsburg becomes B-to loc.city_name.
Thursday is depart_date.day_name and next week
is depart_date.date_relative time frame the label.
So you can have any labels that you would want to associate with
this tags.
So it's not necessary that you'll only have these.
So for instance if you wanted to say that I want to tag all
prepositions, so
you could have on as like preposition token for say.
But in this case we are interested in tagging text or
words in a sentence that have connotation with air traffic,
travel information services, and
these are the tokens that are provided in the data set.
So again, the sequence 19 indicates the sentence is
the 19th sentence in the data set.
Word Index, whatever number, ###:1 indicates the position
of the corresponding word in the vocabulary,
there are total of 943 words.
And corresponding to those words, this number which is
###:1, again indicates one of these numbers here which
would be the location or the index of that particular
labelled in the label set of vocabulary if you might say.
And the corresponding tag in the tag index which would be a total
of 129 tags here.