OK! Now we're going to train a
single predict with a single mini batch of data.
So, we will create a reader, pass in our test file
and false again because
we're no longer training and our two--
input parameters as before, and our set mini batch size to 25.
We'll create a map and then we're going to call
the reader, next mini batch to get our 25 samples using the map
and then we'll get out our data, directly as an array.
So, we'll take our data sub-label and our
data sub input and put them into
a variable called image label and image data,
and then here we're going to use
entry case eval function, but that lets us
do is take any node in our computational graph, and evaluate it
at that point. So, if you remember from up here, we created
a softmax function on the end of our model.
So, by call out--, that's called out. So by calling outside eval,
we'll get out the softmax probabilities
for these 25 images,
and what we're going to do here is,
we're going to iterate from 1 to range of the len of the image data.
So I'll be 25 and so it'll go 0 to 24, we'll get out
all samples here and we'll evaluate each of them one at a time,
and we'll stick all the probabilities into an array called
predicted label probability.
Then we're going to go through and find the Arg max,
that is the index, whose entry is highest
in our predicted label as well as our image label
that was given to us as
in the test data set and we're going to
compare those, will first print out the
two of them labeled and predicted,
and we'll print out the whole array of 25 here,
and so the top label here-- the top row
is the actual labels and the bottom rows
are our predictions. So let's see how
we did. 6, 7, this list entry is wrong,
this entry is wrong, right, right, right, right, right, wrong, OK.
So it's a mixture of right/wrong.
Let's try and visualize one of the images
and its label, so we'll pick sample number 5,
and we will use matplotlib, to image show to plot that
from my image data sample number,
reshape is 28 by 28 again and use a gray map,
and then we'll print out a
the actual predicted label from a gt label sample number,
and it's actually coming from prediction sample number,
and long behold it looks like a 9
and we predicted an 8. So, that's OK.
That we know our model isn't perfect yet,
but that's sort of a way of checking and making sure that things work
like we expect they would at the detail level
and that's also an example of--
the kind of code we would need to do predictions in a deployed model.
OK, so that's it for our coverage of the notebook.
It's time for you now to go to the notebook
yourself, open it up, run it, try changing some things,
try printing out some values,
intermediate values and make sure
you understand what's going on and I also suggest that
you try some of the
suggested exercises listed at the bottom
or maybe there's some throughout the notebook.
Thanks!