Welcome to Module Six.
This is the last module of this series.
We are gonna walk you through a text classification task
using recurrence and LSDMs being the recurrent units.
In this module, we are gonna talk about Text classification
with the ATIS data.
We'll talk a little bit more about the ATIS data
specifically, we're doing the module.
You already are familiar with recurrence last term cells, so
we will build a model using that.
We'll talk about different recurrent
networks towards the end.
And we'll introduce you to a concept of embedding,
which will help us process the text data that you will start
seeing in this module.
And then finally, as always, Train-Test, and Predict Workflow
will help us put together the application end to end.