So now you know that, if we continue to
connect all the image pixels even using
this patching scheme which takes into
account the neighbourhood adjacency
of the pixels. We end up having a huge
number of parameters in our network.
So what I mean by that here, let's go back a little bit
and see as we scan through the image,
each time we are learning a new set of weights.
And that leads to a huge explosion in the number of
parameters that we need to estimate.
Convolution Networks is somewhat key
to understanding how we can build deep networks.
What we will do here is again do the scanning except for the fact that
the Kernel weights that are being learned get updated
every time we run the kernel through the entire image.
In other words in a Convolutional layer, a single set of weights
is being shared by all output nodes within the current filter.
So consequently the values that get
updated are only these three times, three values of the same weight matrix
and the bias ofcourse. So with that for a filter shape of 3x3
we have to learn only ten parameters.
Now what we can do is try to train as many filters as possible.
Now you would imagine that if I trained
another filter, how would it be different
from this filter. But remember during the
initialization phase of our convolution operation
this is applicable to the
dense network as well. But in Convolution even more so
that you would have multiple filters each of them would be
initialized to a different value. OK.
So you would have the first kernel
that would have learned something about
maybe the brightness of the image.
Then you would have the second kernel, the orange one
which would have learned something about
maybe the contrast of the edges.
And so and so forth you will build
n filters. The total number of parameters
for this filter set with n filters would
be 9 times n plus n, a much smaller number.
So in case of a 3x3 filter with 5 layers
this would have 10 parameters,
you would get about 500 parameters. OK.
With larger images the number of parameters
doesn't increase anymore. So instead of
39 million you would get something like
a thousand parameters. What does it let us do?
It allows us to handle larger images
trying larger filters, this allows us
to learn more different kinds of
spatial correlations, a relationship between the pixels within the patch.
The patch is larger, we can learn more number of filters.
So these can detect different
kinds of relationship between the
different patches and also
deeper architecture with may be as high as 150
odd layers. So what are these layers learning?
Let's talk about the some of the first few layers
we call the primitive features, they learn the edges.
You can see that here it has learned
how to detect the edge in this direction
and this one has learned in that direction
so and so forth. OK.
If it was a color image you would have learned
some of the color features and the
deeper layers learn how to use these
primitive features and detect more
complex features like corners or combinations of
different patches and different localized features in the image itself.