In machine learning typically,
you would start with a bunch of features that is extracted
from the data and then you build models on top of it.
In supervised learning, you have labels associated with it also.
In real world application,
that extraction of features can become very, very challenging.
For instance, in the case of autonomous driving,
different conditions during the driving patterns people have,
the weather patterns, road conditions,
illuminations, local roads versus highways,
make the feature extraction part very, very challenging.
When machine learning is applied to health care, it is a very
attractive domain but features may not be easily discoverable.
In today's day and
age, it's not possible to live without web search engines.
And these web search engines are increasingly
becoming sophisticated and involve machine translation and
document comprehension.
Machine translation pops up in other places as well.
For instance, in Skype Translator when you are talking,
you can translate one language from the other.
Speech is an area where different intonations,
environment, noise, languages make feature detection very,
very challenging.
As children we all learn to build primitive constructs to
recognize voice, and slowly, higher level abstract
constructs help our brain understand language as we grow.
Many speech recognition engines mimic such complex abstraction
models in delivering the experience we have
in the form of different applications and devices.
Deep learning solves this problem of learning higher order
abstractions.
Increasingly, these types of models, because of the higher
level abstractions that they are able to build,
are becoming pervasive in our day-to-day living.
Deep learning enables building complex or
higher-level constructs, using simpler constructs.
Starting with the raw data, simple constructs,
to a range of higher order constructs or abstractions.
Deep learning is powered by deep neural networks,
also referred to as DNN.
We'll be learning how to build deep
neural networks in this course.
Deep learning embodies many of the constructs that
is inherently built into our biology, particularly the brain.
Deep neural networks may make several layers in the brain.
So starting with having multiple layers, such as here.
This is the cross section of a mouse brain.
I can see the different layers within the brain.
Similarly, deep neural nets have multiple layers.
Each layer learns a higher abstraction on the input
from the layer before it.
And many practical deep neural nets have
large number of parameters.
These type of deep networks, which have humongous number of
parameters, were previously difficult to build,
largely because of lack of large amount of data to train
these models, as well as the computing capabilities needed
to process that amount of data and build models out of it.
With recent advances in computer science, such cross computing
power and handling of large data is made feasible.
And with increasing number of devices generating data,
the amount of data is also becoming abundant,
helping us build really,
really complex models that mimic natural behaviors.
So that autonomous driving, document comprehension,
and speech recognition tasks are becoming more and more common.
Application domains for deep learning thus are in image and
video processing, speech processing, text.
And combining these three, Increasing
multi-modality and data coming from Internet of Things,
is becoming increasingly common.