Welcome to lab 5 which is corresponding to the module number 6
this is going to be the last lab for this entire curriculum.
And here in this lab we are going to
do a language understanding tasks. Which is classification of text.
The words in the text that come through a lot of applications,
that you might have, say want to have a set of queries
in which you want to recognize different entities
or you want to do part of speech tagging
or you may want to simply have some specific task in your hand.
In this case what we will use is a data set from Air Traffic Information Systems.
And in where we want to tag different entities such as
the location from where you are going to take a flight and the destination
the day at which you are going to take it and we want to be able
to automatically tag that information.
So that we can build interesting applications on top of it.
Now before I can go and walk you through this tutorial which I will do shortly.
What I would do also is to give you a brief recap
of the ATIS data set we are going to use it's going to be a recap of what you have
seen in the lecture set.
So that you become familiar in the context of the lab notebook
that we will be following.
So let's crunch forward. So just to recap from the last module where we
dealt with sequences. And in this case we are going to look into
tagging the different entities in Air Traffic Data here.
And we talked about in the lecture how we can
take a textual token convert it into a numerical embedding
pass it through a set of more modular components
which defines this recurrence block.
And then we will be able to get a classification out of it.
And the recurrence notion is captured here,
which you will see how it can be materialized in code.
And then we will once you unroll this recurrence
this is what it means.
So your input text would be say show Burbank to Seattle's flights tomorrow.
and the corresponding labels are going to be other from city,
other to city note that even though Burbank and Seattle are the city names
the fact that they are their position
in the sentence is somewhat different
defines the tags being From city and To city.
And then this being a date.
So keep this in mind that whenever we build this model which
you'll see in this shape.
Internally there is an unrolling of the loop that's going on here
which enables you to take positional information of these words
in the sentence and help us do the right classification
of these tags into their corresponding entities.
So the ATIS data again
has 943 unique words, we'll call this the vocabulary
corresponding to those words there are 129 unique tags,
these are called the labels. And there are in the data set if you look closely
there are also 26 intent tags,
which we are not using in this tutorial.
Let's take a quick look into the data example and in this data set
data snippet and related to components in the tutorial.
So this data snippet have a sentence
please give me the flight from Boston to Pittsburgh
on thursday of next week end of the sentence.
178 token of my vocabulary is beginning of sentence
and so and so forth in this whole segment here for instance the word from
is the 444 token in my vocabulary set
corresponding to each of these tokens there are world labels here
most of them are see here others but
some of them have entities associated with it and these are the
classification tags include that we this classifier is going to learn
and there are 129 of these tags, each of these tags as well as the words
are encoded in a one hot representation which you have already
familiar with if you have gone through the tutorial the
if you have gone through the video recordings.
So let's see what we want to do here we just like the MNIST data set
where the digit 3 was turned hot here
this is the fourth index so this is 0 1 2 3
in the case of words, what we do here
is we say the word is Boston and that's
the 266 element in my vocabulary I'll have a vector of 943 elements
and the 266th element here would be turned on.
And similarly for each label we'll have one-hot presentation of vector
with 129 elements in it. Just a quick recap of the Embedding
because it's a new concept that you will see appear
as a line of code in the CNT cape lectures in the lecture set
as well as in the tutorial here what we take is we take the token
and we get a numerical representation of
the text here which is the one-hot encoding which you are familiar with
and then we map these one-hot encoding into a more
compact lower dimensional space and this process is called word Embedding.
In this tutorial we are using a simple linear Embedding,
which projects this 943 dimensional vector into a
vector of length 150 this would be a parameter
that you will see appear in the tutorial and we will be using
this formulation for our embedding. In other words,
We will learn this W-e matrix in during the training process
Glove and word2Vec embedding are also very popular
we are not going to use it in this tutorial but you can surely play around
by substituting the embeddings
for the words in your vocabulary
with the Glove or word2Vec embeddings
and substitute it in the this W-e matrix
during the initialization period
or if you want to not learn this embedding,
you can directly take the Text token embed
get the embeddings from Glove and feed that directly
here into the Recurrent block. But we are not going to do that,
what we are going to do in this tutorial
to keep things simple is this whole process
where we take one-hot encoding will
learn the embedding's using a simple
linear embedding and then feed it into current block.
The model that we will have is very familiar to you
and it is taking the Text token converting into a compact
representation then we will pass it into an LSTM block
and output of the LSTM block will be processed project
using a dense layer and we will project it into the class labels.
So this would be a 129 size vector
and our model is going to be looking like this
where you will have the input being 943
dimensional one-hot encoding, output is 150.
The LSTM will take in this 150
encodings and the hidden state is a 300 dimensional vector
that will be processed in the dense layer
and we will emit the 129 classes that belongs to it.
For the 129 vectors corresponding to the what entities
in our label set that we want to classify.
Here is a brief summary of what the model is going to do, you can see that
we'll take the sentence and we will
unroll it internally this you will not see in the code,
because this unrolling is done internally
within the CNTk engine making this really really convenient, because
as you can see that if the length of that sentence changes
the amount of unrolling that you need to do will be also
changing. And you don't have to worry about it
when using this tool kit to be able to tag
the words to their individual Class Labels.
Now that you are quite familiar with the dataset,
how it's going to look like the model structure
it will be a piece of cake for us to walk through the tutorial
and get familiar with how to translate those pictorial views into code.
So let's start with first thing first we download the data here
and you can see that, we look for the train test
the vocabulary and the slots, these are the vocabulary words
and these are the label words. We will import
a few things NumPy, math and the CNTK library
this block is corresponding to some
internal testing that we do
and should not-- is not you don't need to fiddle around with it.
This is the structure that we have alluded to in the
slides before here you can see that S1 is the intent part
above which had 26 different intents and we are not using it we're just
going to use the S0 labels and the S2 labels.
So there the tokens, this one shows show flights from
burbank to st.Louis on Monday end of sentence and corresponding to
that there are labels, if you see st.Louis is one place
but there are split into two tokens. So you have
a label that signifies that when this beginning of that
to location city name and there is intermediate to location
city name. So this is  an additional tag which means
that with this engine that you are going to learn you can put any sentence
and as long as you have these tokens that are labeled with
whatever maybe the label you want you
would be able to classify them. I Don't believe that
this tutorial by lead reading all this
material, because I've already walked you through the
corresponding components in the slides.
But please take a look at it closely and get familiar with the
input data sequence syntax
and again here is the unrolled loop, that I was talking to you during the slides
preceding this video okay.
This is what our code is going to look like, it looks off fully simple
makes it really simple, we make it really simple how to interpret and create models.
So here the vocabulary size is 943 number of labels
was 129 this is unused again and a model dimensions here,
the input dimension going to the vocabulary size,the label dimensions
number of labels the embedding dim
dimension is 150 you can change it, You can play around with it
and see what impact it has in your classification results,
from the hidden_dim that,we use for the LSTM block is set to 300.
We create two containers, x standing for the input,Y stands for the labels
and create the model, this one we have
initialized with a default initial state
and then we create our model.
This is a sequential construct that you might be familiar
if those of you have used libraries like Kara's.
What it doing is taking the input
whatever you pass it through would you
at some point you would pass it to this model,
it will process it to the embedding
the output of the embedding would be concatenate would be
passed into the recurrence model.
And here you can see that we have recurrent blocks
with the each of the blocks being an LSTM
of the hidden dim and then you have
the final output layer,which is the dense layer, which projects the
internal states of the LSTM and into  number of labels
that you want to classify. So let's go through this and see
how we can take a peak into the model.
Here if you can see here, you create the  model z and in case note
that we haven't yet passed any input parameters
yet input shape or data it has no notion of this x ok!.
So we just call create model as shown here, and it creates that
function at this point it's a simple function and when we try to
look at the shape of the embedding.
It gives me -1 to 150  with this** all of these being initialized to 0
right, so sorry. Let's print the value of z component
the embedding component of z.
Let's print the embedding component of the z,
and here we print the shape of the embedding matrix.
You can see it's -1 and 150, -1 indicates that
this model doesn't know
what kind of input is going to get.
Because there is no notion of x here
in that and then we can also print
the classify layer which is the Dense layer here,
and print the bias values.
So in this case you can see that
there are going to be 129 of these
and you would be able to see that
all the bias cells have been initialized to 0.
Now, if I pass the input parameter x
which is defined here which is a container of length
or 943 defined by the vocabulary size
and then print the
shape of the embedding matrix
you can see that it becomes 943,150.
So what I'm showing here is there are different ways you can
inspect the model at different layers
and different stages so feel free to explore that.
Let's take a brief look at the data
and the data reading component of it so here
you will provide the data that the CNTK toolkit
accepts and you can read more about the CNTKTextFormatReader
there's a link here and it converts
a sentence like this into a format
that I talked about  here yep.
And to facilitate some of these processing you there's some built-in
convenience function that you can use
to convert a text to a CTF format.
And then once you have that let's define the reader
which will read the different streams in this case query
the unused intent and the labels
and with that we are ready to trainer model.
Without being equipped with the data
in the right format
and the model structure that you have,
learned in the video and seen it in the code
let's do the Train test and the predict workflow.