Welcome to the second module, this is gonna cover logistic
regression and will introduce you to the framework.
That we will be using throughout the course to understand and
build deep networks.
We will be using an application which is OCR,
optical character recognition with a very popular database.
That you probably have used as a part of your machine learning
training, this is called the MNIST database.
We'll talk a little bit more about the database, but
you have probably already seen
some of the images of the handwritten digits.
So we are gonna build an application to recognize those
digits in this course.
The model, as the name of module suggests,
is gonna be logistic regression.
Some of you might be very familiar with binary
logistic regression, which is two classes.
In this case,
we will do multiple classes which means that obviously,
the number of digits that we have range from 0 to 9.
So having two classes that doesn't help, so we would be
figuring out how to use a logistic regression framework.
To detect digits and we'll cover multiclass logistic regression,
some of the concepts that you're gonna learn
here are gonna be loss and mini batches.
Although I alluded to that in the previous module when
introducing you to the workflow for training and testing.
But we will repeat that and
get you introduced in a little bit more formal way, and
then the last one is gonna be a recurring theme.
Every module you will see, there's gonna be a train, test,
predict, workflow which will show you how you can
combine different components together.
Almost like a Lego-like composability to
build this application end to end, train a model and
then test it out, and be ready to do predictions with them.