Let's build our CNN model now that you know
the process of convolution and the strides and padding,
which was a recap from the video before.
In this case, we have two inputs.
And the first one is the input data, the pixel data,
which is specified by the input image,
input_dim_model, which is specified to 128, 28.
And the output here are going to be the number of classes and
is also the labels, and the dimensions of the labels,
which is one-hat encoded, again.
This is the network we are gonna code, which is the first
layer has a filter shape of 5 cross 5, it emits 8 filters.
And we'll have strides of 2,2,
which means in each dimension the stride is gonna be 2.
And we are gonna pad.
Activation is gonna be below here.
Then the second layer is the same thing except we are gonna
learn a more number of filters here.
So imagine that the first layer actually
get you the basic filters, basic characteristics of the images.
And the second layer builds on top of those
filters that we have learned and
enables higher order features that are generated.
We can have arbitrary number of convolutional
layer stack over one another but the final task for
us is to be able to predict the number of digits that
we have in our training setting.
In this case, it's 10.
So the output value of the network has to be
a vector of 10.
In this case, we pass the output of the convolutional layer as
the input to the dense layer.
Which then gets projected into the output dimension of 10 here.
And note that we're gonna use cross entropy with softmax
as our last function,
hence the last layer has the activation specified as none.
Let's see how the code looks like.
It's very simple as we've seen in the video lectures.
We name the first layer to be first_conv,
second one to be second_conv and the last layer as classify.
Now this can be quite useful for you to do so,
which is name the layer so that at the later time you can go and
inspect what the parameters and
the input output shapes are associated with those layers.
Let's see what holds for the data that we have so far.
So we create this model function X, and
note that I have, X is here, what?
X is my input, with the dimensions specified
by this variable, input_dim_model.
So we've created our model with that input and the first thing
we see is the shape of the first convolutional layer.
In this case you can see it's 8 times 14 times 14.
Go back to the animations and the lectures if you are not
convinced that is the right number as shown here.
And once you convinced yourself you can go and
investigate the second layer which I will
provide the code yet, maybe you can do it as an exercise.
And you can investigate the individual weights and
the biases for those layers as well.
Just for illustration,
I have shown you how you can inspect the value of the bias
layer of the last dense layer which is named classify here.
Okay, here are the ways you can understand
the model a little bit better.
One of the things we do to suggest here is to understand
the number of parameters your model has.
And this is a function you can use to print out the number of
parameters that this simply model had.
And this one has 11,274.
Now if you're wondering where these numbers are coming from,
let's tackle the parameters tensors first.
The six parameter tensor correspond to the weight and
bias pair for each of the layers.
So we have two convolution layers, which make up four
parameter tensors and then we have one dense layer.
So there comes another set of weight and bias.
So a total of six parameters are being estimated.
Now let's see what happens in the first convolution layer.
The input data is of the dimension 128,28.
So in this case,
the filters that are gonna be learned will have the size 1, 5,
5 because 5 and 5 are the filter sizes we have specified.
And the output, we have 8 filters.
So total number of values we will learn here are 200,
which is 8 times 1 x 5 x 5.
And then there are gonna be eight bias values correspond
one for each filter.
You can do the second convolution similarly, but
except if you notice here, the input dimension of the next
layer is the output dimension of the previous layer.
In this case we have eight filters in the previous layer.
So the dimension becomes 8 x 5 x 5, this is very important.
So the total number of parameters coming in
from this layer, is gonna be 16 x 8 x 5 x 5 is just 3,200.
And then you can add 16 bias values corresponding to those 16
filters.
The last layer is the dense layer,
which you are quite familiar how that works.
It's all pairwise connected, so there are gonna be the however
many outputs of the previous layer, which is 16x7x7.
If you are not sure where it came from please run the code
for the second layer, print out its shape and
convince yourself that is the right thing.
And then you can multiply it with the number of output values
because these are pairwise connected and
you will get the number 11274.
Now why this is super important to understand the parameters,
it is because it is kind of tied to the amount of data set or
the size the data set you may need to be
able to train this model.
The number of parameters are very large.
You would need a larger amount of data to train the model to
prevent from overfitting.
So it's super important that you understand the model complexity
and also the number of parameters being more
besides requiring more data would also take longer to train.
And you will have, at run time, also you will have to evaluate
the forward pass in the forward pass compute all the values for
the layer to be able to do the prediction.
So it's important you recognize the model complexity.