We use comparison operators with if else statements to help make
decisions in code.
Here, we have an example where we use a x greater than 25 test.
If x is greater than 25, then we print x is already greater than 25.
If it's not true, if x is less or equal to 25, then we'll
execute our else statement and print what the value of x was.
And then assign it a new value of 26, and inform the user.
Let's run that code.
So with x at 23, this evaluates to false or
not true, else statement runs.
If we increase the value to larger than 25,
sorry 26, then we see x is already greater than 25.
We are using decisions in our code.
In this example, we have a gameboard where the player position and
a trap position are set in the code.
We do an if statement checking if we're not in the trap.
If we're not in the trap and that's true, we keep playing.
If we're not in the trap false, that means we're in the trap and
then the game is over.
So let's start with position of 19 and the trap at 18, and
we can keep playing.
And then if I put myself in the trap at position 18,
then my game is over.
The last example uses the equal comparison operator.
First, I use the single equals sign to set the value of my variable
x to 2.
In my comparison statement, I just test if the value is equal to 2, and
then I give the message about the double equals sign is the test for
is equal to.
I use a pass statement if this value is not true.
So we have seen how we can use boolean comparison operators in our
if else statements, and it really does help us make decisions and
make more interesting code.