Since this is our first lab,
we're going to show you a few extra things at the beginning.
All our labs are written as Jupyter Notebooks in Python.
So the first thing we're gonna show you how to do is to
launch the server on your laptop.
So I'm gonna run the command line.
I've got a batch file that takes me to where the tutorials are.
And then I'm gonna activate my Python environment,
my SimTK Python environment.
And not, I'm gonna run the Jupyter Notebook.
This will launch it in a browser, the Jupyter console.
And before we actually load the first notebook, I just want to
show you a few things about Jupyter Notebooks in general.
To get you oriented to how they work.
So I'm starting a new notebook here and the way
Jupyter Notebooks are organized is as a series of cells.
And the two basic cell types are marked down or
rich text cells and code cells.
So let's just start with a simple code cell right here.
If I say something like 3 times 4 and then I say Ctrl Enter,
it actually executes that cell.
And we see the result there is 12.
I can do something, I can put any Python code here so
I'm going to put a little function called predict.
And it will take an m and b parameter and
x and it's treating this as a simple linear.
It will just return the prediction
which is m times x plus b.
And now we can have some values to try this out with.
I'll just bring in numpy's.
We can do arrays.
And I'll make a set of x values, np.
Let's use random.
No actually, let's use array.
And we'll just say 3, 6, 8.
If I say x, and now I'm gonna do a CTRL Enter,
that will execute that entire code block.
And return the value at the end there, which is 3, 6 and
8 as a NumPy array.
Now, I can actually call my function with that array of
values and do a set of predictions.
Let's try that.
So predict and we'll say, m is 3,
b is 2,
and our x value, and CTRL Enter to execute it.
And there we got our prediction.
So that's how the code cells work.
They have these two sort of subcells which is the source
code, in Python in this case, and then the output.
And the output can be text, or it can be images.
So now let's say we were creating a notebook here for
someone to learn about the simple linear models.
So, we can put a cell, say Insert Cell Above here.
And we'll make that a Markdown cell which is the way they
construct the rich text.
And I can use Markdown here and
say something like simple linear model prediction.
This is a simple sample of linear model prediction.
And now when I execute this Markdown text, and
with CTRL Enter.
It'll actually render it as rich text so
I have some bold up there and regular text there.
So that's basically how these Jupyter Notebooks work.