We've learned about variables and data types for string and integer.
Let's see a little bit about the behavior,
the way they work together.
Let's start with a string data type again.
So we're gonna assign student variable to the string name.
We can echo that on the screen to see what is in student and
that will show below.
And that's a string, it's got quotes on it.
It's got letters that are strings, so
we are gonna go over here again and change student.
So, maybe student might be some type of id number.
And so I'm gonna change this to 123456, and
then let's see how that echoes to the screen.
And so now I've changed student, not just reassigned the data, but
reassigned the data type.
We started with a string and now we have an integer.
So, this is not something you can do in every language, but
Python allows your variables to change data type.
And that's important to know, it can be very useful and
it can be something that you'll need to pay attention to because
it can cause problems.
If you intended this to be a string and you somehow left it as
the number, it might still continue to run as an integer.
So let's change it back to a string and this is a string,
again, a different type of ID that has the last name and
some numbers in there as well.
But it's all string because it's in the quotes.
So we run that and so that's legal to run that way too and
of course I can print that.
Because it's a variable I can call it, I could go back up and
reassign it again.
And so if I run this cell, now student should be 123456 and
it's back to a number again.
So we have learned about the two data types, string and integer.
And that in Python, you can assign a variable to string an integer and
change between the data types.