We've worked with some strings printing, and
now let's talk a little bit more what a string is.
So a string, is just a sequence of characters, and so
that just means one or more characters.
And the characters are just the keyboard characters, for
the most part.
So case a through z, lowercase a through z,
as well as the digits 0 through 9, and a variety of punctuation and
characters and just any of the symbols that we see.
We can add some more in there, but basically, all of these pieces
that we see in our keyboard, those are all valid characters.
And we can also have characters that we'll see later how to do that
are not printable, such as a new line character as well.
And so we can echo that to the screen by running,
because the characters are in our quotes.
Just like we did with the print statement earlier,
we could show our string.
So, again, the rules are single quotes matching,
so this starts and ends with single quotes and,
or double quotes matching, start or end with a double quote.
Just run that, and so that runs nicely.
If we don't match our quotes, we can see how that looks,
so it tells us we have a SyntaxError.
And that's just telling us that we have not used
proper Python formatting on the way that we use a string.
And so, because it starts with a double quote and
ends with a single quote, we have to match those.
I could either make them both single or both double.
And then I will make them both double, maybe not with so
many returns.
And then that will work right there.
So we see, in working with strings, that they
are a sequence of characters, so one or more character.
And that the characters have to be in matching quotes, double quotes or
single quotes.