Comparison operators such as greater than, less than or
equal to, can be used to evaluate to a true/false boolean.
Let's take a look at each of the comparison operators Starting
with >, 3 > 5 is False.
3 < 5 is True.
3 > 3 is False.
So we can use a > or =.
3 > or = 3 is True.
These work just like we've seen in our math class.
Assignment versus comparing.
Here we're going to assign points the value of 0.
The single equals sign is used for assignment.
To compare, we use two equals signs.
These points = to 9.
That is false.
If we set the value to 9, we can see the comparison is now true.
Not equal can be confusing when used in comparison.
Here we're gonna assign x the value of 3.
So the not equals sign is used here in this comparison
in the print statement and it returns a boolean true or false.
Is x != 9?
Is x Equal to 3?
Here we see x not equal to 9 is true because x is 3.
And x equal to 3 is true.
So now we can run different comparison operators
that return our boolean values.