All right, so we will start with dissecting into the data first.
And formatting in a way that we can then build our first model
of this course, which is the logistic regression model.
What we do here is we take the image, as shown here,
it's made out of integer values,
28 of them in rows, and then there are 28 columns.
We stretch it out and put it in the form of a vector, okay?
And the first one becomes the first element of the vector,
the second pixel becomes the second element of the vector,
and so on and so forth, and the last one goes at the very end.
Now, for a 28 by 28 image, when you stretch it out,
if you do the arithmetic, you'll find that there are 784 pixels.
We take this array of pixels and treat that as our input.
And it's represented by this input variable,
which we call it as x, and there is an arrow on top of it,
which indicates it's a vector.
Now, it's no longer a simple number like it was in
representing the average day of the temperature.
But instead, there's a set of values,
784 of those, representing each pixel in this array of
28 by 28 numbers representing the digit 3.
The 28 by 28, by the way,
just happens to be the size of the images from this data set.
It doesn't have to be 28 by 28.
It could be anything.
And what we want to do is, instead of directly
classifying this to be a value of 3,
we would classify that as digit 3.
What we do instead is predict what is
the chance this image represents the digit 0.
1, 2, 3, 4, to all the way till 9, so on, so forth.
Now, you can see that, in this case,
this digit is hand-written digit of 3.
So we expect that the value corresponding to that digit
should be relatively high.
And that's what we get in logistic regression modeling.
So the model is going to output ten different values,
and the highest value should
be the one that corresponds to that digit.
So this is our model here.
In this case, instead of m and b being the parameters,
we have W and b, which you will learn shortly what they mean.
But the thing to remember here is that this model
maps input features to discrete output classes, okay?
As opposed to linear regression,
which maps it into a continuous value.
So, in the solar panel example,
the output of the panel could be any number.
In this case, that is not gonna be the situation,
because output of this model has to be a digit between 0 and 9.
And our model is parameterized by a function z.
And if you're wondering what these W and bs are,
these are often referred to as weights and
b is called bias, similar to the slope and the intercept.
And you'll notice that there are gonna be weights corresponding
to 1 for each digit, so there are 10 of these.
And we'll learn what the anatomy of this weight matrix is
shortly.
And because there are ten digits and we're trying to predict
the likelihood of each digit, we have ten such
bias units, or values corresponding to one,
corresponding to each digit, as shown here.