So now we are at the last slide, we have all the pieces
that we need to put together our end to end
Training Validation Test Predict Workflow.
So let's see what we have here that is different,
the only difference that we have here is this model.
We are going to be using a convolution Network here
instead of using logistic regression
or a multi-layer perceptron model in the previous lectures.
So. again we start with the training database here
we sample a mini batch of handwritten digits.
So in this case you will note that we have 128 samples
for the mini batch, but then we have the handwritten digits,
which are now not flattened
out instead they are being red
as one channel for the color in this case it's gray scales,
so that's one if it was a natural scene this would be three
and the image pixel width and the image pixel height both being 28.
The labels are the same they don't change and each of the input image
has a corresponding label, our model is
convolution model here with max pooling.
This is same as the one that we described in the lectures before.
The parameters here are somewhat different
they are the parameters coming in from the convolution
and the dense outputs,
note max pooling does not
change the number of parameters in itself.
Then we have used the same cross entropy with softmax loss function,
the classification error function create the trainer object here
and using the trainer dot train underscore minibatch and providing
the trainer with different instances of randomly sampled
minibatches of handwritten digits and their corresponding labels.
The learners are pretty much the same
options that you have you can explore that
sgd, adagrad and many others that are available with most of the tool kits.
Having found the final model that we want to see how well it performs on
previously unforeseen data during training and use the test data.
We measure the performance of the model by calculating the error
that is how many images of the MS digits are misclassified.
and we repeat this a few times
to get the average performance of these trained model.
Now that we have the trained model we are going to test its performance,
on the test database we will start with the MNIST
test database here, we'll draw many batches of handwritten
images from this test database.
The image data and the corresponding one hot encoded labels,
this would be the input to the model.
We are illustrating the use of convolution with max pooling model
here, these are weights that have been
identified during the training process, we are not going to change that
in testing. We simply iterate through the samples in the test database
and each time we measure how well the classifier does
with this test samples
compared against the labels
that are provided in the test database as well
and then finally return the classification error as percent
incorrectly labeled and missed image. And you have seen that
as we went from logistic regression
to multi-layer perceptron to the convolutions
the error increasingly reduced that means the accuracy of our classifier
is becoming better and better.
Now with the tested model we can deploy this model,
in an application or web service where we take an arbitrary image
of handwritten digit and predict
it's corresponding optically recognized value in this case it's nine
which is the index with the highest value
in the predicted softmax probability array
can use numpy, argmax functions
to identify the index of the array where this has the highest value.
In general you can use numpy operations to craft different ways
to enhance your modeling capabilities
and either pre-process or post-process your data as well.