So now you know, how we can build classifiers, and
we build ten of those to be able to detect a hand written
digit to its corresponding numerical interpretation,
meaning zero to nine.
Here, what it means is that for the digit 3,
you get a very high value and rest of it are relatively low.
However, I would like to give it a probabilistic interpretation.
And compare one digit with other and
in this case if you see it, that is
not possible because all these digits do not sum up to one.
One of the key requirements for
us to give it a probabilistic interpretation.
So, in machine learning and
in deep neutral especially, we use logistic regression
with something we call Softmax which I'll explain shortly.
And this has much better distributional properties.
And statistically it yields better results
when you train models with Softmax as the output layer.
So typically what happens is, instead of a sigmoid function
that we had here before, we do not have anything.
It's a pass through and this becomes our model function.
And the output can be any value from z0 to z9.
What we do then is, normalize these z
scores by first exponentiating them and
then dividing it by the sum of those exponents.
And this yields a vector which is indicative
of the predicted probabilities of a digit 3,
indeed being detected as the digit 3.
When you have trained the model parameters, Ws and Bs,
they should have a very high value and
the others would have a much lower value.
And now you can compare one against the other.
So this is called the logistic regression with Softmax.