>> Let's look at module one's required coding activity.
And the first thing that you want to know about
it if you're reading through the page,
you'll see the code requirements.
And so those are that you use a variable assignment,
so such as setting a greeting
to a string, like a variable.
So I say the variable greeting = "hello",
that you use an input statement
so that you're going to get that feedback,
and maybe assign that to greeting as well.
And then you would use the in keyword.
That's the key to
this entire activity is that we're going to search
a larger string and to see
if specific substrings are contained in there.
And to make our match easier to do,
we're going to convert things to all upper or all
lower so that it's not case-sensitive.
Let's run that solution code.
So the first thing
your program should do is prompt people
for different categories of
food they've eaten in the last 24 hours,
so that would be something like you would say,
I might have meat,
and I might have dairy,
and fruit, and pasta.
And so, you could just go ahead
and just put some different categories in food like that.
And then when you have
enough things in there, you'd put enter,
and then that gets recorded in as a string,
and then you do your string tests,
so then it will print out these various messages.
So this one says, "It is true
that dairy is contained in that string",
and "It is true that nuts is contained in the string",
and "It is false that
seafood and chocolate are contained in the string".
So, this is what your code should look like.
Again, let's make sure that we use all of
the required code elements
and we'll submit those into the edX form.
The edX form is not necessarily the most elegant.
And what I mean by that is that you will
not see your code formatted when you paste it in,
so I placed some solution code in there and
then we see that it all kind of
looks like one line and that's to be expected.
But then you hit the Submit button and,
I got everything right, so there I go.
If I was missing one of the keywords,
then it would say I'm wrong and I would
have one more attempt to get that right.
So, please check again that you have
all of the keywords. Good luck.