Boolean string methods were interesting
because they could test and tell us
if something was upper, lower or maybe
even capitalized. So, we're now we have the
String format Methods
and they're going to actually help us change a String into uppercase
or lowercase or title case et cetera.
So let's take a look at the String format Method.
So, the format Methods allow us to actually alter the string.
So we have a hard coded string right here,
literal string and we're going to use
the lower command and that should change the uppercase letters to lower.
So let's run that, so we see up.
Everything is lowercase now, let's try to edit.
In the upper method, puts it to all caps.
And we can also use the capitalize. And capitalize--
capitalize will capitalize a word or a sentence with the first
word or the first letter of a sentence.
And so you can see here that the
title Miss is now capitalized but there may be
a unintended consequences when you're
using this in a sentence that every word is not capitalized, just the first word
and it doesn't-- it doesn't keep the
old cases, it puts everything else following it to lowercase.
And so that can be useful especially for single words but title is
maybe more interesting and we have the title below for this print
time to save your code and title
looks like a book title and every word gets capitalized. So,
time to save your code
and then there is swap case which can be useful at times, but it's more--
I think find then a use case
and so, you can see I get the opposite, all lower case
becomes all uppercase and capitalized words become
uppercase with the first word lowercase.
So, using String format Methods we can alter strings to be
all uppercase, all lowercase, title case et cetera.
And they be very useful in our programs.