Welcome to the lab for module five,
here we will get a Hands-on experience
with Time series modeling using Recurrence.
And the recurrent cells that you'll be using would be the LSTM blocks,
that we have talked during the video lectures.
Let's get started. So I have the code here in this folder Edx
and you can see all my labs are here, what I'm going to do now is I have
activated the environment here using
source activates cntk-py35 on linux or activate cntk-py35
on Windows. And then I am going to launch my Jupiter environment.
And if you are using the Azure environment, Azure notebooks.
Then it would be simply launching those notebooks
in the Azure notebook portal
and we are going to use the Lab5 here.
We will walk you through Time series predictions with LSTMs,
we will use the same IOT Data from the solar panel.
Example :that we have been using our in our lectures.
So this is the solar panel that we are using for
our exemplar data set. Each of these solar panel
emit how much electricity they are generating on a periodical basis.
However you'll see that not always all the panels would
record what they are generating,
so we have to deal with some missing data and which is part of the data set here.
So we have recordings from the solar panel on a half hourly basis
and we also know the total output of the solar panel for a given day.
So in this lab, what we will do is walk you through the following steps,
set up you're already familiar with by now,
so we will not go into it too much.
We will talk a little bit about Data generation.
A lot of time can be spent in Data generation,
when you are dealing with machine learning and deep learning.
It's good to understand what the data looks like and how you want to
process that before you want to start modeling.
With the process data we are going to start modeling our LSTM Network
and then conclude the lab with the Train test and prediction workflow.
We import different components, different packages from the Python
and in the pyplot different packages in the Python environment
pandas in particular we will be using it I will point you to it,
when we get to that particular part of the lab and we import cntk.
Here are some of the code that is used for testing these notebooks
and is not particularly relevant for the lab,
but we just ignore this for in the moment.
We ensure here that the environment that you're running is
using CNTKs released version 2.0.
This notebook actually takes a fair bit of computation
and to let us run this notebook in a relatively quick time frame,
we set this flag to be true.
However, I would encourage you to also try out by setting
this flag False and see how much
difference you see at the end of the
runs between the fast mode and the fast mode being set to True,
and the fast mode set to False. Let's take a look at the
Data generation. So, you have solar panel
which emits two measures and 30-minute interval.
We have the solar.current which is
the reported value of current produced,
by the solar panel and solar.total is the
total produced for the day in watts/hour.
So here, what you see is at 7am, the solar.current reading
and that solar.total,
and you have a series of these values
reported in your IOT data,
that is streaming from those solar panels.
What we will do then is, we start to process the data,
pre-process this in such a way that
we can then use it for modeling.
We read data into pandas data frame and I do recommend using
pandas dataframe for
doing a lot of reading of data that can
be read in chunks and you want to
process them it-- is a convenient package,
that allows you to process the data very efficiently
and saves you a lot of time.
We will then normalize the data, remember
in the MNIST data we had scaled the digits
between 0 and 1. Similarly, here we are
going to normalize the data, within a 0 to 1 range.
Then we want to group the data by the day.
And finally we want to
append the column - solar.current.max,
and solar.total.max and generate the sequence for each day.
Now, let's see what those sequences look like.
So, the measurements for a day
are grouped into a set of sequences like shown here,
and correspond-- each of them corresponds
to the measurement for a day. So in here, you can
see, these are the two readings that are
available to us and the total that were
generated for that particular day is 10300.
As more and more recordings come in from that particular solar panel,
for a given day, you can see
that more and more readings are getting
accumulated but the output of the solar panel--  total output
from the solar panel remains the same. Remember, some of these readings
may be missing or may not be available,
because the solar panel didn't
report those readings for that particular
time point and we have to deal with those kind of situations.
Now, our sequence would be one of these
instances here. For instance, there would be some anywhere between
8 to14 recordings in our dataset,
when we have finally processed it and cleansed it
and the corresponding. So that would be your
the X - the input and the Y would be
the total current that is generated
by the solar panel for that particular day.
Now, why I said 8 to 14 is that, if we
have less than 8 data points, for any
particular day, then we skip that
pretty skip that data point all together
because it's very unpredictable
and what's going on that particular---
it is very unpredictable, what is going
on that particular day and it could be
that many of the solar panels stopped
functioning and stopped reporting.
So that would lead to a different workflow
if you were to build an application
where you would send an alert saying
that you have fewer than 8 data points
being recorded, so there might be
something that is going on either the
solar panel is flaky or something's going
wrong and if we get more than 14 data
points we are also truncating it in this
case because we feel that 14 data points
more than adequate for us to be able
to predict what the output of the solar
panel would be for that particular day.
These data sets are available in a
comma-separated value file and what we
do here in this function, we the function
generate_solar_data, we take the URL as an input where
the data lies and here you can see that
it's solar.csv once you run the
notebook you will be able to see where
it downloaded, let's see so in this case
my data should have been downloaded
because I've already run the notebook
you can see under the iot folder here, I
have that solar.csv file. You can
investigate that file what's in there
and understand what is the input to this
pre-processing function. We use the
pandas read_csv functionality to read
the data and then we do a normalization
like I was talking about this is
important for our models to function
well where we compress the data into a
range of 0 to 1 and then we group the
data by the date or for a given date.
Once we have the sequences
these sequences collated
that becomes our input here X and the
corresponding Y, let me draw it here.
So this becomes our X and this is becomes Y.