The addition operator can do math and numbers,
such as energies and floats, or it can concatenate strings.
Let's take a look.
Here, I just have a simple math equation, 19 + 3.
And if we echo to the screen by running it,
we see we can get an answer there.
You can change the numbers and use this as your own calculator.
I can also use this to add float numbers.
And that also shows the result below.
So this is a typical mathematical operation, and
use this just like you would in your math.
We can also add strings.
Here, I have two strings, my name + Allysa.
If I echo that below, it displays as a single string.
We can also put these within a print function.
I can do the math operation in the print function and
the result can display.
I can put a number of strings and concatenate them using
the + operator, and they display as a single string.
The additional operator allows us to do math additions with numbers or
to concatenate strings.