Hello World is a simple first program that we use when we're
learning a new programming language.
It helps ensure that our system is working.
We'll run Hello World in Python 3 in our Jupiter notebook.
And we'll use Python 3 throughout the course.
Enter into the cell which we see is a code cell.
The word print is typed in lower case.
The print function which can display a message that is surrounded by
quotations and inside parentheses to the standard output.
Let's type hello world.
Use print in lower case in parentheses containing a message
surrounded by quotation marks.
To run the code, choose Cell, Run Cells and
get the message Hello World.
We can edit to say Hello Students.
Run the cell this time using a keyboard shortcut,
Ctrl + Enter at the same time.
Now you have coded and run the famous Hello World.