Conditionals help us run the flow of our code using
conditional statements that resolve to true or false.
We will look at if, else, and pass statements.
>> The example has an if True statement.
True is a Boolean keyword.
So if True will do whatever code is indented below the if statement.
If it's not true, and in this case it's always true, so
unless I write false, then we will do the else statement.
So let's just quickly look at how this works out when I run it.
So if True, it never gets past if True.
It prints this if statement after if is True.
And the statement after if is True.
To get to the else statement,
we would have to have whatever's here be not True.
And so we can actually use these keywords, not and True.
And then we see that the else statement will print when
something's Not True.
The more typical way we think of Not True, is we think of it as False.
And this is also the Boolean keyword, False.
So as different statements evaluate to True or False,
we can execute either the if statement or the else.
A way to understand that a little more easily is we can set
right here a variable to True or False.
And so, I have someone I know is True.
And if someone I know is True then I'll say, how have you been?
Else, if it's Not True, I'll print nice to meet you.
And so I say how have you been?
And then I could have something later where I determine
that I don't know who that person is, and so is it someone I know?
That is False.
So I look here, if someone I know, if it's True or
False, and I should see that nice to meet you.
And it says nice to meet you.
Sometimes though, when I run a if statement or an else statement,
I really want only one of the conditions to execute.
What that means is I would only wanna print, how have you been or
nice to meet you.
And so if I do not wanna do anything,
I can just write the word pass.
And this is a keyword, it turns green.
And so nothing happens in this case.
And then if I write True.
Then it will run the how have you been path.
So, if statements evaluate if they are True, and
if Not True they will move to the else statement.