Welcome to the tutorial on convolutional network.
We'll continue to work with our Mnest high data set and get you
familiar with how to build model using convolutional network.
You have gone to the videos I'm sure.
You have understood the concepts behind it.
We'll quickly recapitulate some of those concepts in the form of
code and you should be able to relate to that.
And then build your own models on top of data that you
might have, using these basic networks.
And then you can go and graduate to the next level,
where you build really, really deep networks.
Because convolutional networks can be very,
very challenging because of their depth.
And as you have larger depth, you can run into problems like
we have seen in the places where you have vanishing gradients.
If you are not familiar with that terminology,
you will find it in the next module which is with LSTMs.
But in this case, we will build a reasonably small model, yet
cover all the concepts that has been taught in the video
lectures.
So let's see what we have here.
The convolutional network, as you all know, it's feed forward
artificial neural network with learnable weights and biases,
very similar to what we have seen in MLP networks before.
But we'll see how the weights and
biases are learned here and incorporated into the modeling.
I won't read through the text here but I encourage you to
quickly go through it and have a recap of what convolutional
networks are for and how are the different terminologies
associated with these networks gonna be interplaying
with the code that is gonna be introduced to you here.
One thing I would do suggest is that you revise some of these
deeper networks like the AlexNet, the VGG, Inception,
ResNet at the end of the tutorial maybe, because by then
you'll be familiar with the modeling concepts.
And then relate back to these networks and
see how you can build models, these rather deep AlexNet,
VGGs, ResNet which is 152 layers deep on your own.
If you want to fleet forward a bit,
you can go look into the next set of tutorials which
you see in tk202 in the GitHub repository to get a sense
how those networks might look like in form of code.
So this is the same problem we have with the goal of
detecting the digits.
I will train the classifier only this time.
The classifier will be based on convolutional
elements that define a convolutional network.
These are some of the imports, then we select the device.
And I wanna just quickly recap here is that in the previous
tutorial so far we have had this image.
And we have scanned it in raster fashion and
flattened it into 784 pixel.
And by doing so we lost all the spatial relationships
that exist between and its neighboring pixels.
And we will see how we can bring it back.
How we can bring these spatial neighborhoods
back into the play using convolutional networks.
Now even though our dataset is grayscale,
which means that they're single channel.
A lot of the convolution networks use natural scene
images which are multi channel, which is red, green and blue.
So, Even though our
dataset is gray scale as seen here what we have, what we find
in real world is natural scene images have three channels which
is red, green and blue and these can be specified as tuples.
The first number of the tuple is gonna be the number of channels,
then image width and image height.
By doing this, we preserve the spatial relationship between
the pixels, okay.
Now if you had a volumetric scan, that instead of a flat,
2D image, you had a 3D scan.
In which case, this data would be, number of channels would
remain to be three because of the three colors.
You can have volume width, volume height and
volume depth in this case.
So it becomes tuple with four values.
By doing this, CNTK enables you to specify any arbitrary
image with higher dimensional space.
So for instance, if your dataset had 15 colors, 16 colors,
which can happen with satellite imagery,
then this number 3 would become 16, 15, whatever it might be.
So here, we specify back to them this data set.
We are specifying the input dimension of the model to be
(1,28,28), 1 for the grayscale channel and
then 28 and 28 for the image width and height.
And then our dataset, though we have red,
is flattened in raster order.
So the input dimension here is 28 times 28.
By specifying this input_dim_model, you'll see that
when this flattened data that we have been using gets read in,
it will be put back into the two-dimensional
shape which preserves the spatial relationships
between the pixels that we have been talking about.
You're quite familiar by now with the one-hot encoding of
the labeled data.
In this case, again, this digit 3, so the 4th index,
which corresponds to digit 3 is turned on.
This is refered to as the one-hot encoded label.
Here we are gonna use the same CTFDeserializer in this course
and we will sample data using the create_reader function for
training testing purposes.
This is the place where we read the data in.
Feel free to go and
look into this Train-28x28_cntk_text.txt
file to see what the raw data looks like if you want to
convince yourself that indeed the right data is being read in.