Let's look at improving our input messages
by using the input prompt mechanism
and simplify things a little bit.
Previously we used a message
to the user in a print statement and then we put in our input.
Well, that's fine but we have
this message up here  and then below, I have to
put in my answer and when I
improve this with by using  the input prompt,
I can just do it all on a single line.
So, inside of the parenthesis,  I'm allowed to
put in a message, in a string.
And so that will be displayed to the user
and we're going to see right here
that if I run that now,  the prompt message
that is inside the parenthesis  of the input function
is displayed and then I can
enter a name in there.
And now, that is assigned to student name
and I get my name out here. So, let's going forward
just use the input prompt and that will
simplify things and you keep the prompt
with your input statement.
Another thing that we really need to
look at here is that when we enter in
the student name input, we want to know
what kind of type that is.
And we see that, that is a type string.
So, that is a string because it's a name
and we would expect that to be a string.
But let's look back at our initial example
here with small int. What is that?
Well it's also a string.
So, no matter what your intent is  whether you want
this to be a numeric value or a string value,
it's always going to be a string.
And so this is a digit 3 which is
the same as 3 in quotes.
This is rather than the numeric 3. So we would not
be able to add together three plus three.
So, what we've learned is that, we can use
the input prompt that's built into the
input statement by typing inside the
parenthesis and that no matter what
no matter what we type in
to the input statement is always going to be a string.