Before we get into recurrence, let's take a step back and
start from the problem that we started this module with.
Which was trying to forecast the output of a solar panel
based on the average temperature of a given day.
So, in this case we had fitted a line to our
observed data points in black dots here.
And for
any arbitrary day say this was the average temperature,
we can record the corresponding output of the solar panel.
This was our model, say that arbitrary day was Monday, and we
are able to record the Monday's average day temperature, and
we fit a model that was able to predict what could be the solar
panel output for Monday.
Now, wouldn't it be nice, if we are able to additionally
feed some information regarding the previous day's temperature,
say the output of the solar panel on Sunday?
If it is summer,
it's very likely that this value would have a great deal of
influence in what the value predicted on Monday would be.
Now how can you make this happen?
You could conceptually think of building something which pulls
the data from history, which is the output value of day minus 1.
So in the current let's see how that happens.