Here are some tips on the true and false quiz.
You should try to complete it without watching first.
The true false quiz has two parts.
We're gonna create the function, and we're going to call the function
with a true false question statement and the answer.
So I'm going to show you how to call the true false quiz and
you will have to write the function still.
Calling true false quiz or tf_quiz,
I'm going to send two arguments.
And so you'll have to create these parameters in the function.
The first is a statement, octopuses have green blood,
is my question statement, and the second argument is the answer
which is that is not true because octopuses have blue blood.
And then I'm just going to print out the answer that comes back so
let's run that code.
And we see, I can put in there that it's true and it says,
your answer is you can see it's gonna send back correct or
incorrect from the function call.
So we can try that again.
You can test it with false, and it says my answer is correct.
I could give it another question.
Octopuses have three hearts.
And we know that's true.
So let's go ahead and call the function again.
And then you see,
it's echoing out the new statement octopuses have three hearts.
And maybe I think they have five and so I put in false and
it tells me my answer is incorrect.
So now go ahead and write that function.