Now that we have preprocessed data and
we know how to deal with recurrence, how to incorporate
long recurrent architectures using LSTMs.
And we also know how to control over-fitting using dropouts,
in this case.
Let's put together a model.
So the input, I repeat, are 14 data points that
we preprocessed, represented by this pink window here.
And the output is this single value of
the solar panel on a future date.
Here's our network.
If you notice, we've added a dropout layer right here.
This is to control overfitting.
And how does it translate it into code?
It's very simple.
Previously we had recurrent layers of the LSTM blocks here.
We had pulled the last element from the recurrent
sequence here, using sequence.last.
Then we added a Dropout with a probability of 0.2.
This is a parameter you can play around.
And then, since we're emitting just a single value,
we use a dense projection with a value of 1.
Let´s see how the train test and
predict work flow looks like for this particular model.
Now let's see how we can put together the pieces that we
have learned in this module into the train validation workflow.
What are the things that are different here?
The first thing is
the model here is a recurrence based model.
Compared to the MS data we are dealing with sequences here.
We'll see how we factor that in into our modeling work flow.
The overall schema for training, and validation, and
model selection, remains the same.
So we take the solar panel output data from
the training set.
We sample 96 sequences.
This will be called the mini-batch.
Here there are 96 sequences.
And each sequence here represents a value, a numerical
value of the recorded current from the solar panel.
And the corresponding label in this case is the known output of
the solar panel.
Notice that the length of the sequence is changing.
And this can happen because the solar panel may not be
producing any electricity during certain parts of the day,
or some air conditions lead it to not report
a particular time point during the day.
And the length of the sequences keep changing in the case of
time series modeling.
And one need to be aware of it.
The data is then processed by the model,
you can see the model has the recurrence units.
And we pick up the last units output and
pass it to a dropout there.
And then emit the predicted value of the solar panel output.
In this case, unlike the previous exercises,
we are predicting a real number.
Hence, we want to compute the difference
between the models prediction, say we call it
the Y* which is an output of the z in terms of x.
And the known output from the solar panel, Y,
we want to minimize the difference between these two.
And we use squared_error for that purpose.
And that is our loss function.
In this case, we also use the same function for
measuring the error between our prediction and
what we observed as the known output of the solar panel.
So now we have the model, loss and error functions and
a choice of the learner.
This trainer object can now take different instances
of the minibatch samples and
come up with the optimal set of parameters for this model.
Again, you have a range of learners to choose from.
And one should experiment with the different learners, or
in this case I'm calling it solvers.
The test workflow is same as before again,
you have a model that you've already selected.
Now you're going to sample different data points from
the test database and measure the average error between
the predicted value and the observed value.
You start with the test database.
You sample the different readings for
a given day with their corresponding output.
You use the trained model here.
And determine the error between the predicted value
out of the model using this minibatch
sample data and their corresponding labels.
So this function would return the squared error between
the observed and the predicted output from the solar panel.
Note one thing though, is in the model you will not see
any different logic to accommodate the different
lengths in the input sample, these varying lengths.
This is automatically taken care of behind the scenes for you.
Where the length of the recurrence units can be
automatically adjusted based on the length of the sequences.
As one gets into more complex networks
with different kinds of sequence information,
that level of abstraction really helps focus the developers or
the scientists attention on how to architect the model itself.
This is a huge advantage for folks dealing with practical
deep learning problems that they want to solve.
Now coming back to the solar panel data,
once you have the model train.
Any arbitrary day you get a set of readings from the solar
panel, the model will be able to predict the output
from the set of input points for that particular day.
And this can be easily, you can imagine,
be part of a IoT device at your home where it can show how much
electricity you can expect to be generated for
any given day ahead of time based on a few readings that you
may have collected for that particular day.
Or if you change the model slightly you can use any other
recurrences from past days to be able to get a very reliable
estimate of what the solar panel output might be.