Previously we ran into some type errors
when we try to concatenate strings
and numbers inside a print statements.
And we're going to see how we can fix that
using the comma format and it allows us to combine them easily.
So this is the old way that we would try
to combine these elements using the
addition and we know that we can't add
the strings and the numbers together and so,
we get that type error and so the way
that we can fix that is you could create
a string out of the number
or we could use a comma.
So this is a great improvement is now,
I'm allowed to legally combine a number
and a string in the same print statement.
So let's look below with a number variable.
So I have num error equals zero
and then I have this longish print statement
separated with commas using
the comma formatting and I have a string
int equals and then I have a literal number,
and then I have a literal string,
and then I have this number here as well
that is the variable number error which
would be zero and then followed with a string.
So I can alternate strings and numbers
or I can do variable numbers
and hard-coded numbers and let's see how that runs.
And so that works, my 14 shows up fine
and my number of zero errors came up
and indeed we got zero errors in that.
So in this lesson, we learned that we can
combine numbers with strings using
the comma print formatting and then that can
really speed up our display of information.