Incrementing a variable is a common task that we do inside of a loop,
where we wanna count each time a loop executes.
To use a counting variable in a loop where we want to increment by 1,
we can use the following code.
The variable votes is set equal to itself + 1.
Each time this code runs, the votes tally is increased by 1.
Shorthand uses this format.
votes += 1, which means votes equals itself + 1.
Let's run some code, where we set votes = 3.
And then we want to increment it by 1,
using the votes = votes + 1 method.
And then the shorthand, we're gonna increment it by 2.
When the code runs, we see that the votes tally increased from 3
to 4 and then 2 more to 6.
We can run the code again.
Now it moved from 6 to 7 and then 2 more to 9.
To decrement, we use the same format.
Votes equals itself but now we decrease by 1, we subtract.
The shorthand uses the votes -=1.
Votes equals itself- 1.
Let's print out the current value of votes and decrement by 1.
We can run the code again.
Decrement will decrease the value and in this case,
we can count down by 1.
Here, we're going to keep count of the available seats.
We start with 0, then we run a while True loop and we count and
add 1 seat each time seat_count equals itself + 1.
If the seat_count is equal to, or greater than 4,
then we say we're out of seats.
Let's run the code.
Here we see the count incrementing 1, 2, 3, 4, and
then breaking from the loop.
Another use of a while True loop is counting with a decrement.
We start with 4 seats available.
And then we count as each seat is filled, decrementing by 1.
So, seat count equals itself- 1.
When the seat count is equal to or less than zero,
then we say we are out of seats and our final count is 0.
Let's run the code.
So we start with 4 and
then we decrement until we have 0 seats available.
A variable can be incremented or
decremented by setting it equal to itself + or- 1.