Sequence is the order that code runs.
An object needs to be defined before calling.
In this example, we have a freshly opened notebook.
first_name is a variable that we want to to assign a name "Alton" and
we're just gonna call it with a print function.
I get a name error, says 'first_name' is not defined.
I need to run this first cell
in order to assign a value to first name and instantiate the variable.
Now that it's been run, I can run the print statement and print Alton.
In the second example I have defined a function hat_available,
which takes a single parameter color.
If I run this have_hat which calls hat_available,
I run into the same problem.
'hat available' is not defined.
I need to first, run the code that defines hat_available.
Once that is run, I can call hat_available.
A NameError is a common error that occurs when you call something
before it's defined.
In other words, you're calling it out of sequence.