Functions can not only take in values with arguments.
They can also return,
using the return keyword within the body of the function.
In our first example of a function call with a return value,
we're gonna look at msg_double.
In the body of the msg_double function in the code we see
return keyword.
The return keyword is always followed by an object.
In this case, it is the variable called double.
The return value could also be followed by a literal string, or
a number, or any object.
What happens when you call a function with a return value?
Here we call msg_double with the argument let's go
in the quotations, a string.
The parameter phrase gets replaced with
the value let's go in quotation.
The variable double, Adds let's go with a space to itself.
Double gets returned to replace this function call.
When you call a function with a return value,
the return value replaces the function call.
Let's run the code.
We see that the message let's go let's go is printed.
This is the value let's go let's go,
because this function call is replaced by the return value.
And we captured that return value in a variable, and printed it.
Let's look at a slightly lighter example.
This has taken away all of the variables
used in the body of the function, and we just use the parameter value.
The function half_value divides the value by two.
So when we call half_value,
we expect that it will be replaced by the return value.
42 is sent as the argument and is used in the parameter value,
and divided by 2, so we're gonna get 21.
Let's check and see.
So that return value replaced the function call.
And we printed it, and we see that it has a float value of 21.
The keyword return allows a function to send
back a value to the calling function.