We will introduce you to the validation workflow.
The goal here is to select the final model such that
the loss observed during training and the loss observed
on data samples that is not seen during training, are comparable.
As we proceed along the training, which is the blue line
here and find out our different model parameters and one and two
and then we take a different set and called the validation set
which is outside of the training datum and measure the loss
using those parameters here and compute the corresponding loss.
I'm marking my training loss with my blue circles here and
then the corresponding validation loss,
now we go back and choose our final model parameters.
Here, the loss that we'd see in a data set that is not
part of the training set to have the least validation error and
that becomes our final model.
I went to into a little bit more details here
to explain you the process of the model selection.
We will assume this workflow is
already well understood as machine learning basics, and
we will not be repeating the same workflow, and
focus mostly on training, testing, and prediction.
This is going to be considered as a given as we go into
the labs, and moving forward into our further lectures,
where we'll spend very little time explaining to you,
how this final model is selected.
Now that the final model is selected, we can take the test
data, which is different from the training data.
So this is the test data.
We sample some data from our test database.
And measure its performance on the final model.
So the final model say it was the m10 say it,
I'm just making it up here.
So say the 10 estimates of our slope and
bias of the intercept in that case.
So let's say we pick up the 10th slope and
the 10th value of the intercept and use that to measure what
the test error is going to be so this is gonna report test error.
In the context of the solar panel it's gonna be
the difference between the estimated value for
this particular test sample using the parameters
here are gonna be m10 and b10.
It's fixed,
we have already learned that during training phase.
And you'll continue to measure the test error for
several samplings of data from the test database and
report an average error.