>> In this course, we'll learn how to program Python
3.0 using Jupyter Notebooks in your web browser.
Our Jupyter Notebooks will be hosted at
azure.com and will need a Windows account to login,
so that we can run,
edit, and save our notebooks.
To log in, you'll need
a Microsoft account, such as Hotmail,
live.com, Outlook or Office 365,
which you may have gotten from your work or school.
If you don't have one of these accounts,
you can just use any email account,
which can be completed by following
the link from the login screen.
In this course, we'll host
our Jupyter Notebooks at notebooks.azure.com.
Click the "Sign in",
enter the email address
associated with your Microsoft account,
and then enter your password.
Find the notebook link on this page or,
for school course, from the instructor.
Paste the link into the browser address bar.
You'll be able to have read-only
access if you're not logged in,
but if you're logged in,
you'll be able to run the notebooks.
To make a copy of the notebook,
click "Clone" and then click "Clone"
again to save a copy under your own notebook account.
Let's look at the notebook that
we had open for this video.
We saw that we can log in to Windows account,
and that we know how to navigate to a library and clone.
We can get further acquainted with
our Jupyter Notebook by creating a new notebook.
So, let's go to File,
New Notebook, and let's choose Python 3.0.
Note, there are other languages including Python 2.0.
We use Python 3.0 in this course.
When I create a new notebook,
I can give it a title.
The first cell created in
a Jupyter Notebook is a code cell by default.
We can change that into something
called a markdown cell as well.
Markdown cells are where the instructions
and explanations are written for these Jupyter Notebooks.
We can enter some text in markdown cell,
and if we run the cell it'll just display.
It transforms the text so that we can read it.
We also can edit the text with markdown code,
which is a formatting that formats it into
HTML code like a web page,
and we can use headings and make list and run that.
Then, that's what we'll see.
You will not be expected to edit markdown in this course.
You might run into a cell that looks like this state,
that you just need to run that cell to
see it out of the markdown code.
After the markdown, we have a new cell here.
Wherever there's a new cell,
it defaults to a code cell,
and there we can write some simple code,
like a variable x = 3 just like in your math class,
and you can run those cells.
Then, that variable has a value 3 associated with it,
so that when we run the cell to ask this value,
we can output a 3.
That's just a simple preview of how we'll
use code cells in this course.
So, now we know how to log in to
notebooks.azure.com with our Windows login account,
and that we can navigate to
our libraries or have
a link provided to us and we can clone libraries.
Also, we can create notebooks in Python
3.0 and we saw two types of cells,
the code cell and the markdown cell.