We know Strings come in quotes.
But what do you do, when you need to display a quote in a string?
It could be a problem
because you end the string. So let's take a look at
using Strings with quotes in quotes.
So, what does it mean to have quotes in quotes?
Well, you know when we
use a string quote, we can use either
a double quote or a single quote.
In this case, I'm using double quotes to enclose my string here,
but because I'm using double quotes,
I'm allowed to use single quotes inside.
So anytime that I need to display
a single quote, I have to use double quotes for my outer string
and then this becomes a character.
So, go ahead and run that, and we see that works fine
and then there is my single quote.
Now, we just do the reverse, if we want to show a double quote.
So, here I have the teacher
making a announcement and so we need to
put that into double quotes and display those.
So, I have single quotes, around the end
and these double quotes inside.
They just become characters. So, now I see the--
double quotes show. So it has been a problem
previously to show quotes,
and now you have the ability to do it.
You can't show double and single quotes
in the same sentence yet,
but we're still making progress there.