You have so far been introduced to building a model function.
You have know about lost functions and learners,
which help you find the optimal parameters
while training your model.
So, let's put these things together and
build our first workflow for the MNIST dataset.
So we start with the MNIST training database.
We will sample 128 handwritten images.
These are called mini-batches.
These mini-batches are laid out flat.
Just like we have talking about while building the model.
You can see I am choosing 128 images for my mini batch sample.
This could be any arbitrary one.
It doesn't have to 128.
And corresponding to those images,
we have the labels which are one-hot encoded.
The parameters in the logistic regression
models have the weights and the bias.
One weight matrix of dimensions 10 x 784.
And the bias vector has a dimension of 10.
Our model is very simple.
Weight times the image pixels plus the bias vector.
The output of the model is some values
generated from these matrix operation.
As I eluded to you in the previous video,
that we are going to convert this output
into probabilities using softmax.
Those probabilities then feed into my loss function,
which is cross entropy, and we use a combined
function called cross entropy with softmax, in our case.
An output of this function is gonna be the loss.
Optionally, in addition to this model and the loss function, you
can also define another function you call the classification
error, which compares the output of the model.
Classifies it into the corresponding category and
compares the value with the label.
So, in which case, if the input image was an image of
digit 3 and the label was 3, then there would be no error.
As opposed to if the label was 3 and the classification of
the input image was 8, then that would generate an error.
So you can count the number of mistakes the model makes
using this function, called the error function.
Now you can combine all these together
into a trainer object which takes the model,
the loss, the optional error, and the learner.
And you can call the trainer train_minibatch.
And this would update the model parameters
from theta 1 to theta 2 and so on and so forth.
So the learners as I'd alluded to before can be any one of
the SGD Autograd etc, any of your hands on exercises
you'll get to play along with that.
In the previous module we alluded to the fact that as you
train you also want to find out what particular settings
are gonna be the optimal choice for your final module.
And then one other the way of doing this is using
the validation workflow that was explained to you in the previous
module.
And the idea is that you choose the minimum loss that
you can find in your validation step and
use those heater stars as your final model parameters.
Once you have the final model parameters, you can
then test how the model would perform on the test database.
And this gives you a good idea how the model when deployed on
the field, say in a phone or a web service or some application.
How the performance of that model would be and
you report out the average error by iterating through
all the sample in the tested set.
So here is the test workflow, you don't use the training
dataset you use the test dataset, you sample a mini batch
will be different from the training dataset.
And in this case the models are already fixed.
So w * and b * are fixed referring to the theta *
parameter that I has illustrated in the previous slide.
You can now feed the individual data points from your test data
set into your model.
And compare it with one-hot encoded labels to calculate
the error that you would get from the test
dataset by running Trainer.test_minibatch.
And then finally you'd report the classification
error as percent incorrectly labeled MNIST image.
You can choose other error reporting functions as well, but
classification error is one of the popular ones.
Finally, after doing the due diligence of choosing
the right model, and you're happy
with the performance in the test database that you have,
you can then deploy this particular model into an app.
The app or the web service would sample a handwritten image,
provided there's an input into your eval function,
evaluation function here.
You'll take the image as an input and
generate the softmax probabilities associated
with that particular image, belonging to a particular class.
In this case, you can see that the last
index has the large value of point seven.
You can use a simple Numpy Argmax function to go
through this array and find the index where you have the highest
value in this case the nth index longs to the digit 9.
You can do one digit at a time or you can have the eval
function process a whole bunch of images in one go and
generated the corresponding digit from the classifier that
you have just trained.