Let's do brief recap of basic machine learning
terminologies in this video.
We'll start with understanding what the input data is
gonna look like.
We'll define a very simple model.
And we'll predict whatever our target values are gonna be.
These techniques are applicable for both classification and
regression tasks.
But for simplicity, in this video,
we are gonna focus on a regression task.
We have a solar panel where the features x here happens to
be a single feature which is the average day temperature in
Fahrenheit.
And we want to predict based on that feature what is the output
of the solar panel in watts for that particular day.
So our input x is the feature in this case is the average day
temperature and the output is the observed output which is
also can be thought of as labels, except that it's
a real number here, which is the solar panel output in watts.
We have a bunch of observations that these are the readings
already collected from the solar panel for
a given day temperature x here.
We have the corresponding value of the y.
We can now fit a very simple model, it's a line.
So if you go back to your algebra class,
it's defined by a slope, which is the rate of
change of y over rate of change of x.
So, this is the slope, and b is the intercept.
So our model function has two parameters, slope and intercept.
We learned a model where you have the input coming as
the temperature of the day, the z function is our model,
the parameters here are m and b.
With that we can predict for
any arbitrary temperature the value of y.
So for instance say someday we have a very high temperature
here, daytime temperature is this,
the output predicted by our model will be y star.