If you&#39;ve run into some error so far in your programming,
congratulations you are a official developer.
Errors are normal part of programming process so
we have to learn how to trouble shoot them.
Type errors are when types
of different type are not allowed to be combined.
So with addition, you can only combined strings together, and
you can only combine numbers together, but
you can&#39;t combine numbers and strings.
We&#39;re gonna take a look at some of those samples.
In this example we&#39;re trying to combine the string,
my number is, the string literal with this integer 123.
When you run it you might have seen this error previously,
it says we can&#39;t convert int object to a string implicitly.
This error means that the Python compiler is expecting to
add another string to the first string.
When it encounters an integer, and
doesn&#39;t know how to convert it to a string, it gives us this error.
So what we can do here is we can change this number into a string.
And then that will run properly.
So if you se the type error it&#39;s usually means number and string.
It&#39;s the most common way it would work.
Another way you could run into this is with a variable assignment.
And so in this case my number is an integer.
And so now this num_intro where it&#39;s going to introduce the number my
number is 123, we hope that&#39;s going to print out but
we know that we can&#39;t add a integer with a strings so we get this error.
So again, we have to change from integer to string.
Type errors are cause when there is an illegal operation involving
a type.
In examples we saw, we can&#39;t combine integer with a string.
Always combine strings with strings to avoid the type error.