So now you have two options, and
we are going to use the second options of using
logistic regression with Softmax in this module.
And we will continue to use Softmax as our preferred choice.
And when you do that,
keep in mind that you do not want to add any activation layer
like we have omitted here and made it a pass through.
You'll see that in your hands-on lab as well.
Now that we have the output of our classify in the form of
predictive probabilities.
We can take this output here and
compare it with the labels that we got for
this particular digit which is the digit 3.
And see how well we did.
But how can we possibly do that?
Because this is a number and
this is a an array of ten numbers.
With the fourth element indicating the digit 3.
So here we would like to
get to a notion of calculating differences between
the labels that are provided by the training data set and
compare it with our predicted values from the model.
Let's tackle the model first.
We take the image, we flatten it,
we pass it through this model.
The model learns the parameters ws and bs and
generate the corresponding probabilities.
You guys have completely mastered it.
Now let's take the labels, figure out what we can do with.
So for each image that you see here,
there is a corresponding output that you would like to produce,
which is, in this case, the digit 3.
So one way to do it is something called one-hot encoding.
It means that you will create an array of the length
that mimics the number of unique labels in your data set.
In our data set we have zero to nine digits, so
there are 10 possible categories to which an image can be mapped.
We create a container of length 10 here.
That means there are 10 values possible.
And in this case, for the image being the 100 digit of 3,
we want to have the corresponding cell
number to be indicative of
the number being present in the hand with the digits.
So in this case the fourth element which is 0, 1, 2, and
3 would have the value of 1 shown here.
And the rest of it are all 0s.
Now what we do, is we will compare this labelled data,
which we have transformed from the original digit
3 to a one-hot encoding of a vector of length 10.
And we can compare the difference between that and
the probabilities that are predicted by our model.
Again going back to high school maths you can do that
by taking the element wise differences between
these two arrays then some of the squares.
This is called the squared error.
This is one way of calculating the differences.
However, there is a statistically more robust way of
doing it which has better behavior.
I won't go into the technical details of why, but
suffice to say in cases where you are mapping an input
to some categorical set of values, it is preferred that
to use something called a cross entropy error.
Again, it compares each individual values in these
arrays or this is Yi Yj, and the corresponding probabilities,
and some sub the contributions from these two values.
When the values match or come closest, the values for
this cell to that.
And so on and so forth for the entire area is the closest.
This value would have the lowest possible error.
This is called the loss function.
And we will refer to the loss function in the hands on
tutorial, and
in moving forward you will hear a lot about loss functions.
So, when we refer to loss functions,
it could be most of the cases cross entropy error,
especially when the output is of categorical values.
In other words categories, in this case, digits of 0 to 9,
as opposed to continuous values which was the output
of the solar panel.