Python contains all of the basic math operators.
Not just addition, which we've seen,
but also subtraction, multiplication, and division.
Let's review the basic math operators built
into the Python language.
The + sign for addition, the dash or- sign for subtraction, the * for
multiplication and the / also known as forward slash for division.
We do the math in a cell or in a console environment.
We can just echo that right to the screen.
So let's look at 3 + 5.
And we can run that and it will give us our answer right there.
We also can use order of operations.
Things inside of parentheses are evaluated before things
that are outside of parentheses.
So 3 + 7 times the parentheses.
First thing to be evaluated will be the parentheses.
So that was 8 we saw.
And then the multiplication * 7.
And then + 3.
So we see that 7 * 8 is 56.
And plus 3 is 59.
We can also evaluate math inside of a print statement.
So we see here an example of using multiplication.
Division, which will always result in a float.
Here we have order of operations with parentheses first and
then multiplication.
Here we have three statements of addition and subtraction.
Again, order of operations, multiplication will happen first.
In the other order, multiplication will happen first, 5 * 10.
And then,
we have a case where we will do two sets of parenthesis evaluated first.
And then they will be multiplied.
So let's check that one.
3- 1 should be 2.
22 * 3 should be 66, so let's look over here.
It's 2 * 66 and we get 132.
We can use all of the basic math operators to create equations
inside of our programs.