Welcome to module 5.
In this module and the next one,
we are gonna cover recurrent networks and LSTMs.
Now recurrent networks require you to understand
a few new concepts that we will explain.
And it is very important to understand this
concept at a fundamental level
where you build the intuition of how to use recurrence.
And at the same time you also understand
what data you might have and how that data fits into
building the deep models with the current and LSTM cells.
Once you build the model, you can fill out with the different
network architectures and build very,
very interesting use cases.
We'll talk about some of those use cases
towards the end of module six as well.
Let's look at this module.
This module is a fundamental module which will introduce you
to the concepts of recurrence and
LSTMs, before we can get into the advanced use cases that we
will get into towards the end of the next module.
In here, we will start with an application
related to time series forecasting with IOT data.
Remember we had that solar panel example in the very beginning of
the course, we will build on top of it.
We'll introduce to you what recurrence means.
We'll introduce you to the long short term memory cell.
The key concepts in this module are gonna be recurrence, LSTMs,
and Dropout.
And finally, we will walk you through that train, test and
predict workflow.