We'll start with explaining what the data looks like a bit later,
but first let's get the intuition of the task involved
in tagging entities in the Air Traffic Controller Data Set.
We have Text tokens which we would associate class labels.
Each token would have a corresponding class labels and
we have a notion of recurrence here because a sentence or
a sequence would have multiple tokens associated with it.
For instance, we can start with
the first token here in one of the sequences show, and
the label that we will assign to it is O, or other.
And once you process that, we'll also have a history.
Remember, there is no history when we start the recurring
pattern, that history is zero.
So, the next token would be say, Burbank,
and the corresponding label would be From_city.
The following one is to, and this one we will label other,
and so and so forth, the next token being Seattle.
So now the fact that there was to, the word to that appeared
before a name of a city, renders it with a different context.
In this case we label it as a To_city, and
then flights tomorrow.
So think about an application where you have a sentence or
a query that a user makes on an app,
say show Burbank to Seattle flights tomorrow.
You can immediately feed it into some kind of a structured
context, which is the beginning of the location where the person
is gonna start flying, and it's destination,
with the date that is going to be associated with the intended
action of finding a flight for that particular day.
So here you can see there are many inputs.
And there are correspondingly as many tokens associated with it.