Common tasks in using the Jupyter Notebook are to set the programming
language, reset the kernel, and insert new cells.
The first item of setting the programming language,
we always want our notebook in a Python 3 state.
Sometimes they can be in a different version of Python,
such as Python 2 and we see right there that I have it in Python 2.
And what I did to change that is the same thing we're gonna do to get in
into Python 3, which is go to the kernel tab,
which is the operating system that runs this Jupyter notebook.
Hit Change kernel, and then choose Python 3.
Another common issue with a Jupyter notebook is you might write
some code and it puts the notebook in an unstable state.
Either the browser will become frozen or
the code just is running too long and will not finish.
So we reset the kernel, so again we're gonna go to the Kernel menu up
there, and we're gonna either hit Restart or
often you're gonna hit Restart and Clear Output.
And what Clear Output will do is put all of the previously
run code to a starting point so that there is no variables in memory.
So I'm just gonna go ahead and push Restart there to show that and
then it asks for confirmation.
Sometimes it will also ask you if you are ready to restart again after
it has to force something to shutdown.
The last item we saw previously is inserting new cells.
So, to insert a new cell we know that we can
push both Shift + Enter at the same time.
If it is the last cell, it will add a cell at the bottom, but
if you're in a middle cell, if you hit Shift+Enter,
it just runs the cell and then moves to the next cell.
And we may want to have a cell where I have x set up here and
I have z with a variable over there and I go,
I forgot y and so, I wanna insert a cell.
Well there is the Insert menu and I can insert a cell above or below.
In this case, I'll do below and
then I can put my y value in there and I can insert a cell.
So we saw we can change the programming language
from the Kernel tab.
With Change kernel, we can also restart and restart and
clear all the output using the Kernel tab and we can insert
new cells using the Insert menu and insert either above or below.