Let me first introduce you the concept of sequences.
There are different types of sequences that you'll run into.
And in this module I'll introduce you to a couple of
them that we will use.
The first one, the problem said we will use
the time series prediction with IOT data.
We'll have multiple inputs coming into the models, and
we will predict a future value around those inputs.
In this case, the pink buckets are the inputs, and
the blue bucket is the output in this case
a forecasting based on the empty data and the green
blocks are the models that we will build with recurrence.
If this is not familiar to you these will become very clear
towards the end of the module.
And this motif is popularly called many to one,
popularized by Andrej Karpathy from Stanford.
One thing you'll notice is that in the previous modules,
we had the inputs coming from the top.
Now we will have the inputs coming in the bottom following
this particular motif that Andrej has.
And the output will be at the top.
So let's see what it means in the context of the solar
panel data.
So the solar panel data that we have
are the recordings from the solar panel for
the 14 data points that are captured in this pink window.
And we will build a model and this is gonna be
called the recurrent model where Rec stands for recurrence.
We'll explain to you what those mean.
And based on that model,
it will generate a future prediction of what the solar
panel total output is gonna be at a future time.
So in this case, based on this pink window the input here,
we'll predict this tiny red output prediction of
the solar panel.
This is gonna be the example we will use for
this particular module.
However discussing sequence without using text
data is difficult and both of them go hand to hand.
So here is another motif that we will learn which is called many
to many with one to one correspondence.
What I mean here is you'll have many inputs and you'll have
corresponding to those inputs you'll have an output each.
So there are many inputs and
many outputs and each having one to one correspondence.
Again, we'll see how to build models around that.
In this case we are going to use the tagging
the entities in the air traffic controller
popularly known at the ATIS data set.
So what does ATIS data set entail?
It has a token, and we will generate corresponding label.
Here is the tokens combined to form sentences.
So the original ATIS data will have a bunch of
words that come together to make a sentence, and
we are going to label them to some meaningful classifications
that will be generated out of this model.
If you're wondering how
this word gets converted into a numerical entity,
we will cover that in the subsequent lectures.
And here you can see is that burbank is a city, okay?
And so is seattle.
However when we are able to classify these using
history information, which I will describe to you shortly.
You are able to give it a fine grain description of
that this is the from city and this is a to city.