Hopefully, you have had a moment to think through,
from the previous video, how we can overcome
the limitation of having limited history.
So let's come back to that question.
What can we do about limited memory?
First thing, you can add memory, you can grow memory, right?
We have a computer system, we can add more memory, what else?
We can become more efficient in using the memory.
It would mean that you would maybe
try to forget some things that are not as relevant.
Maybe the words like is, the, and, some of
these repeated words that keep coming over and over, you can
not give as much importance to them or even forget it.
So we will see how we can add more memory to our system.
And also become more efficient in forgetting
those somewhat not so important things.
And that's what the LSTM cell will enable you to do.
Long-Short Term Memory cell is one of the possible solutions
that are very, very influential in deep networks.
Because it enables you to remember context for
a much longer period.
And is much more effective in
solving many practical real world problems that you'll see.
So let's start with our history at time t-1.
Remember the dimensions.
This is M dimensional vector.
And we have our current input,
x(t), which is N dimensional.
And the capital X bar is our new Input, which combines x and h.
You could also think of it as x star,
which we have used last video.
Based on this history, and the new input,
you want to generate the new, updated history.
And now we talked about adding new memory.
So let's say that c stands for our new memory concept that
has the ability to add memory to our existing set up,
which encapsulates history through this h vector.
And based on the new input past history and
the past memory, we want to update our memory.
First let's try to forget things
that are not gonna be of much use.
We project x through a sigmoid and a linear function here.
And the output of this one, a value between zero and one.
And we can multiply the output of this function and
where element wise multiplication with my memory,
which has the same dimensions as the output of this forget unit.
We would be able to wipe out things that we do not want to
remember or keep the things we want to remember and
all the intermediate stages.
Depending on the value of this sigmoid function.
Because we control the what to forget and
what not to forget, this concept is called a gate.
And this is called the forget gate.
Now that we have pruned our memory with things we want to
forget, let's figure out what we want to remember.
So we take the input X here, the capital X, and
we project it just like we were doing earlier into an M
dimensional output, this things is n plus m dimension, n plus m.
And the output of this unit is gonna be m dimensional.
And we want to keep the things that we want to update.
That means these are the things in the processed
input channel that we want to retain and update.
So this is called an update gate.
Again notice that this is a sigmoid
function with output being 0 and 1.
This is an essential function to be used for the gates,
because we want to have states only between 0 and 1.
Now that we know what to update our memory with,
let's go ahead and add it to our pruned memory here.
And we will update the next date of my memory which is here.
Which is c of t-1 times the output of
the forget date plus the input which
combines both x and h at t-1 xt and
multiplied with the output of the update gate so
it will be the thing we can remember,
and that becomes the new cell memory.
Now that we have the new cell memory updated,
let's figure out what we want to do with my new history.
So here, what we do is we create a result gate
which takes the input capital expector,
here, and we map parts of the updated memory,
blend it with the result gates.
So that we know how we want to take things from my updated
memory, and pass it as the new state of the history.
Now that we have updated the history here,
we can also pass it through a dense and
a soft max layer to emit the new output state,
should you need one.
So you can see that mathematically,
we are introducing a lot of parameters.
And whenever you do a lot of parameters,
you increase the model capacity here.
So you can see that we have added many more weights and
biases.
Whenever you add these parameters.
So in LSTM cells,
you can see that we have added a lot more parameters.
And by doing so,
we have increased the capacity of the LSTM unit.
Which is one of the popular building blocks for
recount units.
So instead of just having one set of weights and
bias, you now have many more.
This is a key concept, where you are able to increase
the memory as well as by including the forget gates and
updating the ones that you want to update.
You are becoming more and more efficient in
utilizing these existing parameters of the model
to better capture the different time steps.
And as you build longer recurrent units, as you saw in
that passage generation part where we had to refer to
the BBC, that 75 blocks away, it becomes increasingly feasible.
There are other recurrent units like GRU or
Gated Recurrent Units, we haven't covered that here.
For this course, we are gonna focus on LSTM
as our building block of recurrent units.