In this module, we will start with reviewing two applications
that have made convolution networks very very popular.
The first one, image tagging.
You take an image and you give it to this trained model.
It will emit different labels that
are associated with this image and those are the image tags.
In here you can see that this is the image of a leopard
and the top five categories predicted are pretty
reasonably good, with the first one being spot on being leopard.
So this is part of a work that was done by
Alex Krizhevsky's and Hinton's research group in Toronto,
the paper is referenced here.
And it builds on top of a very popular data cell
called ImageNet.
And it has led to groundbreaking research and
breakthroughs in the area of deep learning.
Once you have tagged an image with the different tags.
The next task that automatically comes in your mind is,
where are these images.
Where are these objects located?
In this other application, which you'll see here,
we call it object detection.
The different components in the image are not only tagged but
also their bounding boxes are predicted.
This is a tutorial that is available on our CNTK
website which does object detection using Fast R-CNN.
This is hugely popular for many practical applications in
the domain built on top of image-based data.
Here you can see that within a refrigerator we are able to
detect that this is a bottle of orange juice and
this is some egg cartons in here, and so on and so forth.