We're going to review module four:
Required Coding Activity on string analysis.
And in this activity,
you have some key word requirements listed below.
We have to define a function and use the def key word.
We'll have a while loop,
that will loop while we're inputting a valid input,
so we can't have an empty string entered.
We're going to use if,
and then we're going to either use else or elif.
Also, we'll be using the int,
to cast input into a integer or a digit.
We're going to check if input is digit or is alpha.
And of course, we'll have to get user input and we will
be printing some results to our users.
Let's look at the edx page for this coding activity.
And like the other pages,
there are the assignment requirements,
that we just looked at.
And we'll have that same information
on our Jupiter notebook.
We should use the Jupiter notebook to code our solution.
I've pre-loaded this page with a solution,
so that we can see how it runs.
So it asks us to enter a word or an integer.
If we enter nothing,
it will continue to ask us for input.
So, let's go ahead and just run that again.
Okay, so now we can enter in a word,
so which is right word.
And we see that word is all alphabetical characters.
So it checks if the input is all alpha.
For that message, we can run it
again and I can put in a series of digits.
And it says, "that's a pretty big number",
because that's bigger than 99.
So let's go ahead and run it again.
I could run it with something smaller.
And it says that is "28 is smaller than expected".
We can also just see how the behavior works otherwise.
So if I say 22.5,
it says "that's not all alpha or all digit characters".
And some of us might disagree with that,
but it's looking at the characters,
it's not looking at the data type.
And this may look like it is a float,
but is actually a string,
and it's a string that contains a non-digit.
So likewise, if we are running,
it asks us for a word or integer,
so if I put Alton Derosoa,
it's also not an alpha or a digit
because a space is not
an alphabetical character or a digit.
So, you can go ahead and build that code.
Make sure you keep getting input until it has
something in there that it checks for the empty input.
And then we test whether it is an integer or digit.
If it's a digit, we're going to have to
convert that into a number.
See how big it is, and use some nested comparisons.
So, make sure we're going to use all of these keywords.
And if you're having trouble submitting,
look at some of
the earlier required coding activity videos.