[MUSIC]
Hello and welcome to this online course from Microsoft Learning.
&gt;&gt; At Microsoft our mission is empower every person and
every organization to achieve more.
&gt;&gt; Our EdX courses, taught by Microsoft experts, let
you learn cutting edge technologies through hands on experience.
&gt;&gt; Whether you&#39;re a student or
a seasoned technologist we can empower you to build
innovative applications, services and experiences.
&gt;&gt; So what are the requirements for course completion?
Well, time.
&gt;&gt; On average our courses have four modules,
which are two to four hours each.
&gt;&gt; Watch the videos, including presentations and demonstrations.
&gt;&gt; Like you would attend a lecture on campus.
&gt;&gt; Complete course readings or projects and
hands on learning activities.
&gt;&gt; These are your homework assignments and
probably where you will learn most.
&gt;&gt; Take quizzes to help you prepare for the assessment.
&gt;&gt; The assessments can only be taken once and
you need a passing grade to successfully complete the course.
&gt;&gt; Our courses are free as all learning should be.
&gt;&gt; For a shareable, verified certificate, there is the fee.
&gt;&gt; While our courses offer different experiences,
all of them shared a similar approach.
&gt;&gt; Please review the About page to find specific
information about your course.
&gt;&gt; For example, some courses release all content immediately.
&gt;&gt; While others release modules incrementally over time.
&gt;&gt; Are part of a larger learning program.
&gt;&gt; May require an Azure or Office 365 subscription.
&gt;&gt; Many students use a free trial subscription.
&gt;&gt; Offer opportunities to engage with instructors and peers.
&gt;&gt; The most common indicators of success among the more
than 2 million learners that experienced our online
courses are &gt;&gt; Dedicating enough
time to the course.
&gt;&gt; Demonstrating perseverance.
&gt;&gt; And participating in the discussion groups.
&gt;&gt; Welcome to the world of Microsoft technology.
Choose a path and make your mark.
[MUSIC]